<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-02-27T17:51:41+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/atom.xml</id><title type="html">Op-tec Systems</title><subtitle>Independent automation consultant</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Achilles Certification</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/news/achilles-certification" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Achilles Certification" /><published>2024-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/news/achilles-certification</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/news/achilles-certification">&lt;p&gt;It wouldn’t be right for us to recommend our clients validate their control and automation systems and keep them up to date while not ‘practicing what we preach’. So we’re always looking for the right opportunities to work with third parties who can help us improve our business systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our recent Achilles Gold certification is the latest evidence of this. Achilles audit our business management system against industry best practice. Combined with the BSI, our ISO 9001 auditor, they ensure we adapt to changing client needs, regulations, and market conditions. They also hold us to our commitment to continual improvement&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;View our certificate &lt;a href=&quot;/downloads/Op-tec_Systems_Achilles_Gold_Certificate.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Achilles-badge.png&quot; alt=&quot;Achilles Gold Certification Badge&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Projects</name><email>projects@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="news" /><category term="power" /><category term="pharmaceuticals" /><category term="chemicals" /><category term="oil&amp;gas" /><summary type="html">It wouldn’t be right for us to recommend our clients validate their control and automation systems and keep them up to date while not ‘practicing what we preach’. So we’re always looking for the right opportunities to work with third parties who can help us improve our business systems.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22Achilles-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22Achilles-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22Achilles.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Achilles%20audit%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22Achilles-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22Achilles-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22Achilles.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Achilles%20audit%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Batch Systems</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/batch-systems" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Batch Systems" /><published>2024-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/batch-systems</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/batch-systems">&lt;p&gt;Automation systems used to control batch processes typically feature a ‘Batch Engine’. This software is commonly seen in industries like fine chemicals and pharmaceuticals. Control systems featuring batch engines differ from those used in continuous processes; they follow ‘recipes’ to manufacture discrete quantities of product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;key-features&quot;&gt;Key Features&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The batch engine at the heart of batch control systems coordinates plant equipment using software models and rules defined in the ANSI/ISA88 standard – commonly referred to as ‘S88’. The S88 standard features a physical model, used to identify how plant and equipment fits into the wider enterprise. The procedural model is then used to define the software which utilises control equipment to control the process during a recipe. While most Distributed Control Systems provide S88 compliant batch systems, stand-alone batch engines are also available for SCADA-PLC solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Batch_models.png&quot; alt=&quot;Relationship between models in S88 batch standard&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;benefits&quot;&gt;Benefits&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Batch systems enable multiple products to be manufactured using shared equipment increasing utilisation of the plant. The ‘modularisation’ of a production area, combined with software logic which acquires plant components on behalf of recipes can make it possible to run multiple batches through plants concurrently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logging and auditing features make traceability of raw materials into finished product automatic. Most have comprehensive reporting tools enabling quality control and process optimsation. In time recipes can be optimised based on data on energy and raw materials consumption, processing time, and quality (including the integration of lab results where available).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designing new and modifying existing recipes within batch systems is relatively simple compared with reconfiguring continuous control systems. This means personnel without a background in automation can configure the system according to their requirements without specialist help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recipes can be designed to fully automate production, guide manual operation, or anywhere in between. This means batch systems provide flexibility and control over processes which either cannot be easily automated or aren’t fully developed (prototypes or proof of concepts).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Batch systems support the digitalisation of businesses by enabling the conversion of existing processes and logs into electronic forms. The systems will support electronic signing and authentication requirements within the food and pharmaceutical industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information follow the link below to the Services section of our website where you can learn more about the help we can offer on this topic and many others relating to industrial process and manufacturing automation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/services&quot;&gt;https://op-tec.co.uk/services&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Roger Halliwell</name><email>roger.halliwell@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="knowledge" /><category term="tech-note" /><category term="food&amp;drink" /><category term="pharmaceuticals" /><category term="chemicals" /><summary type="html">Automation systems used to control batch processes typically feature a ‘Batch Engine’. This software is commonly seen in industries like fine chemicals and pharmaceuticals. Control systems featuring batch engines differ from those used in continuous processes; they follow ‘recipes’ to manufacture discrete quantities of product.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22waldemar-7kSnMLGoR9w-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22waldemar-7kSnMLGoR9w-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22waldemar-7kSnMLGoR9w-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Batch%20systems%20follow%20recipes%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22waldemar-7kSnMLGoR9w-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22waldemar-7kSnMLGoR9w-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22waldemar-7kSnMLGoR9w-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Batch%20systems%20follow%20recipes%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Control System Validation Explained</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/control-system-validation-explained" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Control System Validation Explained" /><published>2023-10-18T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-10-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/control-system-validation-explained</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/control-system-validation-explained">&lt;p&gt;As companies continue adopting technology to increase efficiency and automate complex operational processes, external factors exert pressure on capital and operational budgets. External factors squeeze profit margins, making operational excellence more vital than ever. This paper will explore the role of control system validation in ensuring automation technology delivers improvements in efficiency, reliability, and the cost of ownership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your business uses industrial automation technology, you’ll benefit from adopting system validation processes. A comprehensive understanding of control systems validation is crucial to any engineer working on projects to implement this technology. For leaders and managers, knowledge of this process will enable you to maximise the value automation projects bring to your business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;System validation requires investment, so businesses confront common pitfalls. Among these hazards are delayed validation, inadequate inclusion of stakeholders, and poor planning. Such blunders can lead to systems failing to meet user requirements, subpar performance, and unanticipated operational hazards. This whitepaper equips readers with the skills necessary to navigate these obstacles effectively. It teaches them to construct a robust validation strategy, align stakeholders, and orchestrate adequate verification and validation processes. By understanding the nuances of automation system validation, readers can optimise system performance, reduce risks, and increase stakeholder confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adopting the suggested insights presented here will leave you better equipped to navigate the complex landscape of automation system validation, thereby assuring the success and resilience of your business operations in an increasingly automated world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;key-takeaways&quot;&gt;Key Takeaways&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Role of system validation in enhancing dependability, productivity, and safety&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Difference between validation and verification&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How stakeholder engagement ensures system validation aligns with user requirements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoiding common pitfalls, such as delayed initiation and exclusion of key stakeholders&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Best practices for system testing, documentation, and ongoing maintenance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses rely increasingly on control and automation technology. As system complexity grows, ensuring technology does everything we intended and is performing as required becomes crucial. So does our ability to understand how and why equipment functions the way it does, allowing us to maintain, modify and improve it as requirements change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;System validation is the process of documenting and testing technology, to make sure it operates as intended in terms of functionality and performance. The documentation generated allows the system to deliver maximum value to users who know what it is capable of. Inadequate validation can lead to various issues, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deviation from user-specific requirements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Suboptimal system performance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reduced system reliability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Compromised safety and security&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this paper we will explain the significance of validation. In highlighting common mistakes companies make and pointing to best practice hopefully you’ll finish reading inspired and equipped to validate control systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-validation&quot;&gt;What is Validation?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Validation is a systematic process which – if followed – guarantees a system’s adherence to requirements and intended performance. It methodically documents user requirements and establishes comprehensive traceability between these requirements and the final system implementation. For industrial control and automation systems, this process follows the ‘Computer System Validation’ philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ensuring the automation system meets specified requirements is pivotal in guaranteeing its fitness for purpose and alignment with user needs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breaking down validation to its elemental components reveals a straightforward approach:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clearly define the intended functionality with accurate and unambiguous documentation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Construct the system hardware and software in strict adherence to specifications.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Substantiate the system functions precisely as specified through meticulous testing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically, the validation process is categorised into three core areas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Installation Qualification&lt;/strong&gt; - Ensuring the installed system meets the specified requirements.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Operational Qualification&lt;/strong&gt; - Verifying the system functions as intended under normal and abnormal fault conditions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Performance Qualification&lt;/strong&gt; - Validating the automation system yields a product in line with the end user’s specifications, emphasising final product quality and consistency over operational functionality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Validation is instrumental in affirming the system’s intended performance, fostering reliability, accuracy, and consistency&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The validation process typically includes the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Defining Requirements:&lt;/strong&gt; The initial phase involves establishing the requirements the automation system must meet, including functional, performance, and safety aspects. This is typically documented in a User Requirements Specification, produced either by the end-users or a third-party representative.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creating a Validation Plan:&lt;/strong&gt; With requirements in place, the next step is formulating the validation plan. This plan outlines the scope, methods, and expected outcomes of the validation, encompassing Installation Qualification, Operational Qualification, and Performance Qualification.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Executing Validation Plan:&lt;/strong&gt; This phase involves rigorous testing of the automation system to ensure it aligns with the established requirements.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Analysing Results:&lt;/strong&gt; Post-execution, results are scrutinised, identifying discrepancies and proposing enhancement recommendations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Documenting Results:&lt;/strong&gt; Comprehensive documentation of the validation process aids in monitoring progress and addressing potential issues in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;By identifying and rectifying issues early on, validation plays a critical role in risk reduction associated with the automation system&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;verification-vs-validation&quot;&gt;Verification vs. Validation?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Verification and validation are two important concepts in engineering. Unfortunately, they are often confused with one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verification&lt;/strong&gt; is the process of ensuring a system meets its specifications. This tests the system has been implemented correctly and meets all documented requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Validation&lt;/strong&gt; is the process of ensuring a system delivers on project objectives. This typically means it meets the needs of its intended user. This tests the system is usable and meets stakeholder expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, verification checks a system does what it was designed to do. Validation checks the design fulfils user needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The practical difference between verification and validation is the focus of the process. Verification focuses on the implementation of the automation system, while validation focuses on the usability and functionality of the automation system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Project engineering teams usually undertake verification. Validation is typically performed by system users or a third party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This table summarises key differences between verification and validation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Verification&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Validation&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ensures system meets specifications&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ensures system meets needs of users&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Focused on implementation of the system design&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Focused on system usability and functionality&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Typically performed by the project team&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Typically performed by users or a third-party&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Verification ensures the automation system is implemented correctly, while validation ensures the automation system is usable and meets users’ needs. By performing both verification and validation, you can be confident your automation system is of high quality and meets the needs of its users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;relationship-with-the-v-model&quot;&gt;Relationship with the V-model&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The V-model serves as a visual representation of the validation process for computer systems, illustrating the interconnectedness of different phases. It comprises of three main sections: design, build, and test. The build section is a relatively small component which sits at the bottom of the ‘V’. The design process leads up to it, from requirements capture to module/unit design. Following the build the test process features stages which align too design stages, allowing a modular and phased approach to overall system validation. User requirements phase, followed by the design phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/V-model-validation.png&quot; alt=&quot;V-model process guide for control and automation projects&quot; style=&quot;float: left&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the activities described in the diagram above, a Traceability Matrix is produced. The traceability matrix is a document cross-referencing all the user requirements through the relevant design and test documents. The traceability matrix is used throughout the validation process to ensure all user requirements have been fully implemented in the design, build and test phases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The V-model is a helpful tool for validating automation systems. It visually represents the validation process and helps ensure all the necessary steps are taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;costs-and-benefits&quot;&gt;Costs and Benefits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cost of effective validation can vary depending on the size and complexity of the automation system. However, it is important to remember the cost of validation is an investment in the future success of the automation system. A well-validated automation system is more likely to be reliable, efficient, and secure. This can lead to significant savings in time, money, and resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cost of validation can be broken down into two categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Initial Cost&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ongoing Commitments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The benefits of effective validation can outweigh the cost in many cases. For example, a well-validated automation system can:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reduce the number of defects in the automation system.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enhance the system’s reliability.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Augment the system’s efficiency.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reduce the risk of problems with the automation system.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide comprehensive documentation needed for future changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;initial-cost&quot;&gt;Initial Cost&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initial validation costs can be significant, especially for large and complex automation systems. Creating test cases can be expensive, as it requires time and expertise to identify all possible scenarios the automation system should be tested. The cost of executing test cases can also be high, as it can require significant resources to run the tests on all the different platforms and environments the automation system is expected to run on. The cost of analysing test results can also be high, as it requires time and expertise to identify and understand the results of the tests. 
A point to note here is ‘don’t start from scratch’. Several templates are available regarding the documentation needed to validate an automation system. One of the best resources is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ispe.org/initiatives/regulatory/what-gamp&quot;&gt;Good Automated Manufacturing Guide&lt;/a&gt; published by the International Society of Pharmaceutical Engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ongoing-commitments&quot;&gt;Ongoing Commitments&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ongoing validation cost is often lower than the initial cost, but it is still important to budget for it. The cost of maintaining test cases can be high, as it requires time and effort to keep them up to date as the automation system changes. The cost of executing test cases as the automation system changes can also be high, as it requires time and resources to run the tests on the new versions of the automation system. The cost of analysing test results can also be high, as it requires time and expertise to identify and understand the results of the tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;benefits&quot;&gt;Benefits&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Effective validation yields many benefits, underscoring its critical role in system development and maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initial benefits, realised during project execution, include ensuring supplied control systems meet project and business objectives, managing change, and providing a framework for project management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the system’s operation, benefits continue to be realised in reduced maintenance costs, third parties can be given access to documentation and so don’t need to undertake system audits, and modifications and upgrades can be planned without interrupting production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following table lists some key benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Benefit&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Value&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Facilitates future modifications&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;A thoroughly validated system offers a comprehensive documentation framework, easing the process of future modifications and updates.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reduces Mean Time To Repair&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Well-documented systems streamline fault tracing, leading to a reduction in Mean Time To Repair and minimising downtime.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Enhances system quality&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Validation serves as a mechanism for identifying and rectifying defects within the automation system, thereby elevating its overall quality and performance.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Fosters user confidence&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Users are more inclined to trust and rely on an automation system which has undergone thorough validation, instilling confidence in its reliability and efficacy.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ensures regulatory compliance&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;In specific industries, validation may be a mandatory prerequisite to meet regulatory standards. For instance, the FDA mandates validation for medical devices prior to market release.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stakeholders&quot;&gt;Stakeholders&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early identification and involvement of stakeholders is paramount to the validation process. A proactive approach ensures a successful validation process and guarantees the resulting system aligns with the needs and aspirations of all interested parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stakeholders in control system validation are people with a vested interest in the technology’s success. They include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Project Managers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;System Engineers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Automation Developers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quality Assurance Engineers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;End Users&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Senior Management Team&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;avoiding-pitfalls&quot;&gt;Avoiding Pitfalls&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many common mistakes companies make when validating their automation systems. The table below outlines some validation mistakes and their consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Mistake&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Consequence&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Validating too late&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Identifying and rectifying problems later in the project execution process is both costly and can lead to quality issues as compromises are made to accommodate changes.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Excluding key stakeholders&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The requirements capture process is not comprehensive, leading to new requirements being “discovered” late in the day – see above.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Poor planning&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Poor management has a huge impact on project success, ideally, the project team will be trained and have experience in system validation.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Using non-standard methodology&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Inconsistency and lack of repeatability in the validation process impact not only project delivery but also the lifecycle benefits of system validation.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avoiding these common pitfalls is crucial for a successful validation process. By addressing these issues proactively, companies can ensure your industrial control and automation systems meet quality, reliability, and performance standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;best-practices&quot;&gt;Best Practices&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many best practices for validating automation systems. Some of the most important are outlined below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Best Practice&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Rationale&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Diverse Environment Testing. Test the automation system across a spectrum of environments, encompassing various operating systems, hardware setups, and datasets.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;This ensures the automation system performs reliably across different scenarios and environments.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Comprehensive Data Testing. Thoroughly test the automation system using a wide range of data, including both standard and unconventional datasets.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;This validates the system’s ability to handle diverse inputs, enhancing its robustness and adaptability.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sustained Performance Testing. Conduct periodic tests to confirm the automation system maintains its expected performance over time.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;This is particularly critical for systems deployed in mission-critical applications, ensuring they remain reliable and consistent.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Checklist Utilisation. Employ a detailed checklist as a guiding tool to ensure all necessary steps are executed during the validation process.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;A checklist provides a structured approach, minimising the risk of overlooking vital validation tasks.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thorough Documentation. Document all results obtained during the validation process.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Comprehensive documentation serves as a crucial reference point, enabling the tracking of validation progress and identifying potential issues for future resolution.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Recommendations for Enhancement. Derive actionable recommendations for system improvement because of the validation process.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Implementing these recommendations enhances the current automation system and serves as a proactive measure to prevent future issues.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies can improve their automation systems’ quality, reliability, and performance by adhering to best practices. This ensures these systems operate optimally across various environments and datasets, even in critical applications. Furthermore, the systematic approach provided by these practices facilitates thorough validation and sets the stage for continuous improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this whitepaper, we’ve explained the control system validation process at a high level, illuminating its critical role in ensuring the success and reliability of automation systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Effective validation represents a strategic investment in the future performance of your automation ecosystem. By adhering to best practices, engaging key stakeholders, and avoiding common pitfalls, companies can reduce ownership costs and maintain their systems’ performance throughout their lifecycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value of validation extends beyond compliance. It equips organisations with the resilience and adaptability needed to navigate an ever-evolving technological landscape. Well-documented systems expedite troubleshooting and instil confidence in users, fostering a culture of trust and reliability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you‘d like help or advice regarding the process described, please contact us for a no pressure, no-obligation discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fas fa-phone-alt&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;abbr title=&quot;Phone&quot;&gt;&lt;/abbr&gt; &amp;nbsp; &lt;a href=&quot;tel:00441616604293&quot; id=&quot;number&quot;&gt;+44 161 660 4293&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fas fa-envelope&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;abbr title=&quot;Email&quot;&gt;&lt;/abbr&gt; &amp;nbsp; &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:projects@op-tec.co.uk?subject=Maximising%20the%20return%20from%20technology%20projects&quot;&gt;projects&amp;#64;op-tec.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Download a PDF copy of this article &lt;a href=&quot;https://op-tec.co.uk/downloads/Control_System_Validation_Explained.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;u&gt;here&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Obiefuna Obidike</name><email>obiefuna.obidike@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="knowledge" /><category term="chemicals" /><category term="power" /><category term="pharmaceuticals" /><category term="oil&amp;gas" /><category term="whitepaper" /><summary type="html">As companies continue adopting technology to increase efficiency and automate complex operational processes, external factors exert pressure on capital and operational budgets. External factors squeeze profit margins, making operational excellence more vital than ever. This paper will explore the role of control system validation in ensuring automation technology delivers improvements in efficiency, reliability, and the cost of ownership.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22Validation-AI-generated-thumb.png%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22Validation-AI-generated-thumb.png%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22Validation-AI-generated.png%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Is%20your%20control%20system%20fully%20validated?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22Validation-AI-generated-thumb.png%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22Validation-AI-generated-thumb.png%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22Validation-AI-generated.png%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Is%20your%20control%20system%20fully%20validated?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Towards absolute reliability</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/towards-absolute-reliability" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Towards absolute reliability" /><published>2023-10-11T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-10-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/towards-absolute-reliability</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/towards-absolute-reliability">&lt;p&gt;Whatever the sector, the industry, the process, the machine, the component, things will go wrong. Component failures cause machine downtime, processes get interrupted, an entire industry may be affected by the same root cause, bringing similar problems across a whole sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One recent example is the food retail sector. Refrigeration fails during the hot spells of (even our British) summers. Why? If reliability can be improved, then how?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Because refrigeration systems become overloaded when ambient exceeds the temperature that the system was designed to operate in. High temperature will cause rising condensing pressure until a protection switch operates to shut the system down before something bursts. The refrigeration effect is lost, stock is lost, sales are lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what if the operating characteristics of the machine could be modified so that overload conditions were never reached? What if an alert could be raised to indicate that incipient overload conditions were developing and that corrective action was being taken automatically, together with indication of the impact on overall performance? How would I operate this machine if I had manual access to all the controls? If you see a pothole in the road ahead you don’t drive into it, you don’t stop at it, you steer round it and continue your journey. This can be automated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking the refrigeration high pressure switch as the example, high pressure trips can be avoided by increasing the condenser cooling available, or reducing the heat transfer to a level that the condenser can deal with. If the condenser is at maximum capacity, then limiting the heat pumped by the compressors will keep the system operating with reduced refrigeration effect, an alert can be generated, and corrective action can be taken before a total failure occurs. The refrigeration effect is retained, stock is saved, sales increase because competitors have had failures, and their refrigerated shelves are empty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A variety of other conditions can stop a refrigeration system in addition to high condensing pressure. For example, high (or low) evaporating pressure, discharge gas over-temperature, motor over-temperature, motor over-current, oil pressure failure, oil flow failure, to name a few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frequently these analogue values are converted into a digital input by a limit switch. Alternatively, systems use analogue inputs to a control system and then process them to stop the process when a threshold is reached as if they were a limit switch. This is not getting the best out of a PLC. A PLC programmed to take corrective action by ‘steering round the pothole’, applying an override function to limit the output may be written into any control loop where it will prevent threshold values from being exceeded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking the refrigeration system high condensing pressure example, there will be a control loop having increasing output with increasing process variable, a limit loop having decreasing output as displacement from the limit value reduces, and a minimum value selector so that the limit overrides the control, keeping the system machine or process running in a safe operating condition. When the override is active the heat load on the condenser can be limited by shutting down the least critical evaporators or reducing the capacity of the compressors, or both. Simultaneously, an alert can be generated, and work put in hand to have the fault rectified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result: downtime avoided, productivity increased, and a step taken towards Absolute Reliability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does it work? Yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How long has it been around for? Decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who did it first? I did, using Staefa’s AS1000 back in 1991. Any challengers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why isn’t it more widely used? Smart controllers have never been this cheap in real terms, so only now is it gaining acceptance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Connect smart controllers with smart programmers and you’re ahead of the competition.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Peter Jackson</name><email>peter.jackson@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="knowledge" /><category term="food&amp;drink" /><category term="textiles" /><category term="power" /><category term="chemicals" /><summary type="html">Whatever the sector, the industry, the process, the machine, the component, things will go wrong. Component failures cause machine downtime, processes get interrupted, an entire industry may be affected by the same root cause, bringing similar problems across a whole sector.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-pixabay-159298-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-pixabay-159298-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22pexels-pixabay-159298.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Drop%20in%20performance%20or%20complete%20shutdown%20-%20you%20can%20decide%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-pixabay-159298-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-pixabay-159298-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22pexels-pixabay-159298.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Drop%20in%20performance%20or%20complete%20shutdown%20-%20you%20can%20decide%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Front-End Engineering Design (FEED)</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/FEED-study" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Front-End Engineering Design (FEED)" /><published>2023-07-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-07-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/FEED-study</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/FEED-study">&lt;p&gt;An early but crucial stage of project development. The FEED is a comprehensive analysis and planning process which helps define the scope, requirements, and feasibility of a project before detailed design work and implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;key-features&quot;&gt;Key Features&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While scopes vary to reflect the proposed project, a FEED study typically provides a thorough examination of the project’s technical, economic, and environmental aspects. This involves conducting engineering assessments, evaluating potential risks and challenges, and developing a preliminary design. The study also considers the project’s financial viability, estimating costs and potential returns on investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;benefits&quot;&gt;Benefits&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FEED studies allow project stakeholders to make informed decisions based on a solid foundation of information. By conducting a detailed analysis early on, potential issues and bottlenecks can be identified and addressed before significant investments are made. This helps minimise risks and uncertainties, ultimately leading to a more efficient and successful project execution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FEEDs provide a clear roadmap for a project’s development. They outline objectives, deliverables, and timelines, allowing all parties involved to have a shared understanding of the project’s scope and requirements. This helps streamline subsequent engineering and construction phases, reducing the likelihood of costly delays or rework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Project owners may require the information provided by a FEED study to secure financing and gain support from stakeholders. By providing a comprehensive overview of the project’s technical and economic feasibility, FEEDs make it easier to obtain the approvals needed to secure capital. They also help build confidence among stakeholders by demonstrating the project has been thoroughly evaluated and planned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information follow the link below to the Services section of our website where you can learn more about the help we can offer on this topic and many others relating to industrial process and manufacturing automation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/services&quot;&gt;https://op-tec.co.uk/services&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Roger Halliwell</name><email>roger.halliwell@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="knowledge" /><category term="tech-note" /><category term="food&amp;drink" /><category term="textiles" /><category term="power" /><category term="chemicals" /><summary type="html">An early but crucial stage of project development. The FEED is a comprehensive analysis and planning process which helps define the scope, requirements, and feasibility of a project before detailed design work and implementation.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-yan-krukau-7793723-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-yan-krukau-7793723-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22pexels-yan-krukau-7793723.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22FEEDs%20are%20a%20crucial%20stage%20of%20project%20planning%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-yan-krukau-7793723-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-yan-krukau-7793723-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22pexels-yan-krukau-7793723.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22FEEDs%20are%20a%20crucial%20stage%20of%20project%20planning%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Hit that ‘Save’ button</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/hit-that-save-button" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hit that ‘Save’ button" /><published>2023-05-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-05-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/hit-that-save-button</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/hit-that-save-button">&lt;p&gt;We all fall short of this in some manner. I would love to take you down memory lane to bring your thought closer to the adverse effect of not saving your work.  You remember the good old days when Microsoft Office applications were without the auto-save feature, right? Now say you are just about finishing a thirty-page masterpiece document, feeling happy with yourself, so you decide to step into the kitchen to heat some water and make a cuppa tea. Your three-year-old decides to innocently help you with typing and, in doing so, magically turns off your PC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you step back in to finish your typing, and you are welcomed with a cute smile and a “Daddy/Mummy, I helped you finish the typing and turned off your PC”. I don’t know about most of you, but chains of thoughts would undoubtedly go through my mind. I will anxiously consider whether I should be happy with the gesture or sad because I may not have “Hit That Save Button”. Amongst my thought will be imagining trying to recreate my masterpiece to the standard it was or trying to imagine the cost of re-writing my masterpiece. A price which may range from forfeiting the planned time to spend with friends, go on a vacation, possible financial price or even as simple as forfeiting the cuppa tea you had planned to drink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we know, all that mishaps can be avoided by following the process of saving your work by hitting the save button. A process Microsoft has deemed fit to automate, Hoorah! Now our kids can break our PCs, right? Nah, I don’t think so too.  Undoubtedly, Microsoft did a great job ensuring our work is saved automatically on their application. However, it is our sole responsibility to ensure our processes are in place to save our work locally and securely on an external storage medium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enough of my blabbing about Microsoft, let us bring it down to our niche. As an industrial staff, it is crucial to ensure you have processes in place to “Hit that Save button” for your firm. No, I am not just talking about a document-saving process, I am also talking about saving the “money-making” process. Every business has a process for making money. Be it by installing the latest “whizzy” tech to fast-track production or employing the “brightest” personnel. In trying to etch towards that juicy ROI you so deserve, the main question remains, &lt;strong&gt;“Have you taken time to ensure the cost you incur in installing super tech or hiring a great mind has a process to hit the save button automatically?”&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer this and more, you will most likely need a Digital Benchmark Analysis. The report will disclose those hidden weak spots in your money-making process and ensure that your technological and human work is automatically saved, just like our very own Microsoft Word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, there are tons of Digital Benchmark analyzing software, at Op-tec Systems we have worked with most industries and understand the work and cost you put in. By doing so, we decided you should not incur more expenses as you seek your truth. Feel free to Generate Your &lt;a href=&quot;/digital-benchmark&quot;&gt;Free Digital Benchmark Report&lt;/a&gt; and ensure that ROI is securely within your grasp.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Obiefuna Obidike</name><email>obiefuna.obidike@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><summary type="html">We all fall short of this in some manner. I would love to take you down memory lane to bring your thought closer to the adverse effect of not saving your work. You remember the good old days when Microsoft Office applications were without the auto-save feature, right? Now say you are just about finishing a thirty-page masterpiece document, feeling happy with yourself, so you decide to step into the kitchen to heat some water and make a cuppa tea. Your three-year-old decides to innocently help you with typing and, in doing so, magically turns off your PC.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22vincent-botta-bv_rJXpNU9I-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22vincent-botta-bv_rJXpNU9I-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22vincent-botta-bv_rJXpNU9I-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Does%20your%20business%20do%20unnecessary%20rework?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22vincent-botta-bv_rJXpNU9I-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22vincent-botta-bv_rJXpNU9I-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22vincent-botta-bv_rJXpNU9I-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Does%20your%20business%20do%20unnecessary%20rework?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The benefits of automation in workplace safety</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/benefits-of-automation-technology-in-workplace-safety" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The benefits of automation in workplace safety" /><published>2023-03-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/benefits-of-automation-technology-in-workplace-safety</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/benefits-of-automation-technology-in-workplace-safety">&lt;p&gt;In today’s workplace, automation technology is becoming more prevalent. Workplace accidents can have a significant negative impact on a business, ranging from low staff morale to huge reputational and financial costs. Organisations can use automation to reduce workplace accidents alongside realising productivity increases. This article will outline how automation can be a valuable tool for reducing the likelihood and consequences of industrial accidents while improving efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;hierarchy-of-controls&quot;&gt;Hierarchy of Controls&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is common practice for Health &amp;amp; Safety managers to use the hierarchy of controls to mitigate risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/HierarchyOfControls.png&quot; alt=&quot;Hierarchy of controls&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the hierarchy of control as a risk management framework helps identify the most effective and reliable methods of risk mitigation. This hierarchical structure starts with the elimination of the hazard and progresses downward to using personal protective equipment (PPE) as a last resort. While elimination and substitution are the most challenging options to implement into an existing process, automation kicks in as a cost-effective engineering control measure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several ways in which automation technology can be used to mitigate workplace risks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Physically distancing employees from hazards&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Automation makes remote work possible as it can physically distance workers from hazards. The use of automation helps in completing potentially dangerous jobs which would otherwise be done by workers - limiting human exposure to hazardous enviroments or situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robots might be operated to handle dangerous materials in an industrial environment, lowering the risk of worker exposure. Robotic welders, for instance keep workers away from sparks, fumes, and other potential welding risks while being supervised by skilled workers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Automation technology can also be applied to remotely monitor and control processes, enabling employees to work at a safe distance. By limiting exposure to hazards, the likelihood and severity of accidents is eventually reduced, resulting in a safe and healthy work environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automating repetitive tasks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By automating repetitive tasks businesses increase workplace safety and boost productivity as a result. Numerous manual jobs, like working on an assembly line or entering data, can be monotonous and exhausting, and this increases the likelihood of mistakes and accidents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By taking over certain tasks, automation technologies can assist to alleviate these repetitive tasks and free up workers to engage on other complex jobs. Since automated systems are frequently more capable of working quickly and accurately than humans, this can also help to increase the overall effectiveness of the work process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reducing employee fatigue&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accidents may occur as a result of worker errors. Errors might occur as a result of miscommunication, confusion but also exhaustion. By taking over jobs that are physically demanding or need continuous attention for extended periods of time, automation technology has the potential to alleviate employee tiredness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Continuous process monitoring&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Automated systems can continuously produce data and monitor process in real-time. This makes it possible for such systems to respond to emergencies far more promptly than humans. Automated systems can stop accidents and equipment damage by shutting down machinery or warning staff before a potentially dangerous situation worsens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Safety relays can be used to connect sensors and interlocks to cut off power to motors and actuators preventing a possibly hazardous event. An example would be automatic shutting down of boilers and turbines in thermal power plants should the amount of water in the steam drum exceed a safe level. This shutdown safeguards both the equipment from catastrophic damage and workers from potential harm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nevertheless, a word of caution - while automation helps in mitigating existing risks, it can create new unanticipated hazards. Therefore, it is crucial to conduct a fresh risk assessment exercise in order to put in place safety measures so as to manage the impact of the new risks.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To sum up, automation technology can drastically lower the risk of accidents, making the workplace safer while increasing uptime and productivity. With the advent of AI and IoT into the workplace, the process can become even more effective and efficient. By strategically integrating automation technologies, businesses can create a safer and more productive work environment for their employees, benefiting the organisation and its workers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Pravesh Teckmun</name><email>teckmun@icloud.com</email></author><category term="knowledge" /><category term="food&amp;drink" /><category term="textiles" /><category term="power" /><category term="chemicals" /><summary type="html">In today’s workplace, automation technology is becoming more prevalent. Workplace accidents can have a significant negative impact on a business, ranging from low staff morale to huge reputational and financial costs. Organisations can use automation to reduce workplace accidents alongside realising productivity increases. This article will outline how automation can be a valuable tool for reducing the likelihood and consequences of industrial accidents while improving efficiency.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22possessed-photography-dRMQiAubdws-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22possessed-photography-dRMQiAubdws-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22possessed-photography-dRMQiAubdws-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Robots%20can%20improve%20safety%20as%20well%20as%20productivity%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22possessed-photography-dRMQiAubdws-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22possessed-photography-dRMQiAubdws-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22possessed-photography-dRMQiAubdws-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Robots%20can%20improve%20safety%20as%20well%20as%20productivity%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">SCADA</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/SCADA" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SCADA" /><published>2023-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/SCADA</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/SCADA">&lt;p&gt;SCADA systems are used to collect process data, display plant status information, and provide users with control over automated processes. SCADA systems are highly configurable, able to provide a wide variety of monitoring and control functions to the diverse roles which make up an operational workforce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;key-technologies&quot;&gt;Key Technologies&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SCADA systems make use of proprietary database technology and/or open platforms such as SQL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commonly the user interface often referred to as the HMI (Human Machine Interface) comprises a screen hierarchy where the plant is split into logical areas. For example, a tank farm feeding a chemicals manufacturing facility would be displayed on one screen and the process vessel reactors on other screens while common services and utilities on further screens. For a chemical plant each screen resembles a PI&amp;amp;D (Piping and Instrumentation Diagram) where instruments, motors and valves etc are also included.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/SCADA.png&quot; alt=&quot;System overview - SCADA&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To collect data from plant-level Operational Technology (OT) SCADA systems make use of open industrialised protocols like OPC and MQTT, as well as being compatible with proprietary communications utilised by specialised or legacy systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Process information is made available to Information Technology (IT) via application programming interfaces, accessed using methods such as SQL, OData and ODBC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;benefits&quot;&gt;Benefits&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Visualisation and Control&lt;/strong&gt; – Access to real-time plant conditions via fixed operator displays and mobile devices. Remote control and optimisation of automated processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reporting&lt;/strong&gt; – Scheduled and event driven reports deliver time-sensitive information to users via email, text message or device notifications. Alert operations staff to process conditions, maintenance staff to potential equipment failures and keep management up-to-date on operational performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Historian&lt;/strong&gt; – Plant data is able to be both recorded and archived using SCADA systems. In this respect the SCADA system acts as a data repository with search and analysis features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information follow the link below to the Services section of our website where you can learn more about the help we can offer on this topic and many others relating to industrial process and manufacturing automation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/services&quot;&gt;https://op-tec.co.uk/services&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Roger Halliwell</name><email>roger.halliwell@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="knowledge" /><category term="tech-note" /><category term="food&amp;drink" /><category term="textiles" /><category term="power" /><category term="chemicals" /><summary type="html">SCADA systems are used to collect process data, display plant status information, and provide users with control over automated processes. SCADA systems are highly configurable, able to provide a wide variety of monitoring and control functions to the diverse roles which make up an operational workforce.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22iStock-1422487368-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22iStock-1422487368-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22iStock-1422487368.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22SCADA%20system%20being%20used%20for%20analysis%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22iStock-1422487368-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22iStock-1422487368-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22iStock-1422487368.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22SCADA%20system%20being%20used%20for%20analysis%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Unified Namespace</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/unified-namespace" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unified Namespace" /><published>2023-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/unified-namespace</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/unified-namespace">&lt;p&gt;A unified namespace is intended to be the ‘single source of truth’ for an organisation’s production data and is a key component of network architectures which make the most of the Industry 4.0 concept. Manufacturers who implement a unified namespace build networks in a hub and spoke layout providing all major systems a direct link to the unified namespace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;key-technologies&quot;&gt;Key Technologies&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unified namespace, or central repository, is the hub of an organisation’s networks. It features details of every data point in the organisation and all information passses through it. Software providing this service is commonly referred to as a ‘data broker’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/unified-namespace.png&quot; alt=&quot;Network overview - unified namespace&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Network architectures which utilise a unified namespace don’t conform to the traditional Purdue Enterprise Reference Architecture, the standard model for company networks since the 1990’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success of this approach relies on lighteight ‘report by exception’ communication protocols (e.g. MQTT). This ensures the data broker(s) which making up the unified namespace can handle the huge amount of data flowing through them and minimises loading on ‘satellite’ systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;benefits&quot;&gt;Benefits&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reduced system and network complexity&lt;/strong&gt; – Maximum of 2 connections between any two systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scalable architecture which supports digitalisation&lt;/strong&gt;  – Minimises cost of future modification, expansion or integration. Reduces cost of experimentation, proof of concepts and improvements projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lower integration costs&lt;/strong&gt; – Addition of new systems or data points simplied with changes only required to a single connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supports OT/IT convergence&lt;/strong&gt; – Having a centralised and shared resource necessitates teams responsible for operational and information technology to work effectively together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Removes need for system knowledge&lt;/strong&gt; – Object-orientated/contextualised approach allows creation of digital twins. Enables people with little or even no knowledge of operational technology will be able to navigate and use data from the UNS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Standard presentation for data from different providers&lt;/strong&gt; – Plant or equipment with the same functions from different suppliers can be presented in a uniform and consistent manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information follow the link below to the Services section of our website where you can learn more about the help we can offer on this topic and many others relating to industrial process and manufacturing automation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/services&quot;&gt;https://op-tec.co.uk/services&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Richard Banyard</name><email>richard.banyard@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="knowledge" /><category term="tech-note" /><category term="food&amp;drink" /><category term="textiles" /><category term="power" /><category term="chemicals" /><summary type="html">A unified namespace is intended to be the ‘single source of truth’ for an organisation’s production data and is a key component of network architectures which make the most of the Industry 4.0 concept. Manufacturers who implement a unified namespace build networks in a hub and spoke layout providing all major systems a direct link to the unified namespace.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22clint-mckoy-9oYHSMxt7tg-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22clint-mckoy-9oYHSMxt7tg-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22clint-mckoy-9oYHSMxt7tg-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Have%20you%20moved%20to%20a%20hub%20and%20spoke%20architecture?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22clint-mckoy-9oYHSMxt7tg-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22clint-mckoy-9oYHSMxt7tg-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22clint-mckoy-9oYHSMxt7tg-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Have%20you%20moved%20to%20a%20hub%20and%20spoke%20architecture?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Will it work?</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/will-it-work" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Will it work?" /><published>2022-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/will-it-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/will-it-work">&lt;p&gt;I went to visit Sally down at Sale the other day, we had a good conversation over a “cuppa tea”. Just as I was about to set up and leave Sally informed me she had a bit of an engineering task she believed I would be able to fix. Sure, I affirmed because I am always down for a challenge, only for her to inform me her shower soap holder had broken, and she had a new part to fix it. However, she didn’t know how to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was expecting a challenging task. Nevertheless, I was challenged as it turns out she had ordered a very beautiful soap holder, but the fitting system was made for shower poles with a 25mm pole diameter and hers was 22mm. The challenge was explaining that while good, her solution wouldn’t work with the wrong parameters. I called two days later to check up, she had the right one and could fix it up herself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar events happen within our niche. A few days back, I went down south to a client site to commission equipment they had designed to dry their product quicker. My role was to ensure the equipment they had set up would perform the task efficiently. The equipment consisted of blowers blowing air through air knives and a chain conveyor system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supposed to be a straightforward task, right? That was my thought process until I interacted with the equipment. On my first run with the damp product, I realized parts of the product were dry and other parts were not. A simple solution adjusts the air knife position parameter to effectively dry the remaining part of the product. As simple as it sounds, it went from being simple to being manually demanding as the designers of the equipment had not created room for parameter adjustments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is we got the desired result after manually modifying the equipment. However, the equipment needs to be shipped back and modified to accommodate optimizable adjustment hence some cost on someone’s side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what do a non-fitting shower soap holder and non-adjustable drying equipment have to do with me you may wonder?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equipment in both cases didn’t meet expectations because crucial questions, were answered correctly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1) What is the problem we want to overcome?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2) What parameters directly affect the problem?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3) How does each parameter impact the problem?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost all of us are spot on with the first question. However, when it comes to the second and third, most of us are found wanting. Sally, my friend, was spot on with the first question. 
However, she didn’t understand the parameters that would be used to implement the solution (question 2) and couldn’t go further to answering question 3. With my friends down south, you can see that questions 1 and 2 were answered. However, question 3 was left out so the solution parameters couldn’t be modified to meet their expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In providing solutions for your project, you need to understand the parameters that &lt;strong&gt;Op&lt;/strong&gt;enly relate to your solution and the &lt;strong&gt;tec&lt;/strong&gt;nologies behind these parameters. That way you would be closer to implementing your solution as “plug and play”.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Obiefuna Obidike</name><email>obiefuna.obidike@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><category term="software" /><category term="food&amp;drink" /><category term="textiles" /><category term="chemicals" /><category term="power" /><summary type="html">I went to visit Sally down at Sale the other day, we had a good conversation over a “cuppa tea”. Just as I was about to set up and leave Sally informed me she had a bit of an engineering task she believed I would be able to fix. Sure, I affirmed because I am always down for a challenge, only for her to inform me her shower soap holder had broken, and she had a new part to fix it. However, she didn’t know how to.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22Will-it-work-thumb.png%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22Will-it-work-thumb.png%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22Will-it-work.png%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Oh%20really...?%20by%20BakaSchwarz%20on%20DeviantArt%20by%20Unknown%20Author,%20licensed%20under%20CC%20BY-NC-ND%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22Will-it-work-thumb.png%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22Will-it-work-thumb.png%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22Will-it-work.png%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Oh%20really...?%20by%20BakaSchwarz%20on%20DeviantArt%20by%20Unknown%20Author,%20licensed%20under%20CC%20BY-NC-ND%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>