<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-01-26T19:49:17+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/atom.xml</id><title type="html">Op-tec Systems</title><subtitle>This is a description of Op-tec's awesome site.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Don’t know where to start? Try the basics</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/views/cyber-security-basics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Don’t know where to start? Try the basics" /><published>2021-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/views/cyber-security-basics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/views/cyber-security-basics">&lt;p class=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;Often in life, getting the simple things right is key to success. For example, when we're feeling overworked, overcommitted and overwhelmed it can be hard to prioritise things like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;tab&quot;&gt; - Eating well&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;tab&quot;&gt; - Being active &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;tab&quot;&gt; - Sleeping enough&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;tab justify&quot;&gt;But when we focus on and prioritise the basics it increases our resilience and allows us to put everything else into perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;tab justify&quot;&gt;The same is true for cyber security. One of the best ways to make your systems resilient to attack is to have comprehensive backups and a regularly tested incident response plan. Unlike high-tech solutions, these work every time, for all types of breach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;tab justify&quot;&gt;I know.... writing and testing procedures is not as exciting as buying new technology. But I assure you it's far more cost-effective, even if you pay someone else to manage the process for you. Your systems and organisation will be more resilient as a result, and less dependent on third parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;tab justify&quot;&gt;Would you benefit from focusing more on the basics?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;tab justify&quot;&gt;Get in touch if you'd like to speak with one of the team about how we can help you establish processes for backup, restore and disaster recovery:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fas fa-phone-alt&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;abbr title=&quot;Phone&quot;&gt;&lt;/abbr&gt; &amp;nbsp; &lt;a href=&quot;tel:00441616604293&quot; id=&quot;number&quot;&gt;+44 161 660 4293&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;                 
&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fas fa-envelope&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;abbr title=&quot;Email&quot;&gt;&lt;/abbr&gt; &amp;nbsp; &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:projects@op-tec.co.uk?subject=Support%20for%20800xA&quot;&gt;projects&amp;#64;op-tec.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Richard Banyard</name><email>richard.banyard@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="views" /><summary type="html">Often in life, getting the simple things right is key to success. For example, when we're feeling overworked, overcommitted and overwhelmed it can be hard to prioritise things like: - Eating well - Being active - Sleeping enough But when we focus on and prioritise the basics it increases our resilience and allows us to put everything else into perspective. The same is true for cyber security. One of the best ways to make your systems resilient to attack is to have comprehensive backups and a regularly tested incident response plan. Unlike high-tech solutions, these work every time, for all types of breach. I know.... writing and testing procedures is not as exciting as buying new technology. But I assure you it's far more cost-effective, even if you pay someone else to manage the process for you. Your systems and organisation will be more resilient as a result, and less dependent on third parties. Would you benefit from focusing more on the basics? Get in touch if you'd like to speak with one of the team about how we can help you establish processes for backup, restore and disaster recovery: &amp;nbsp; +44 161 660 4293 &amp;nbsp; projects&amp;#64;op-tec.co.uk</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-digital-buggu-311269.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22pexels-digital-buggu-311269_feature.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-digital-buggu-311269.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Could%20it%20pay%20to%20concentrate%20on%20the%20basics?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-digital-buggu-311269.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22pexels-digital-buggu-311269_feature.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-digital-buggu-311269.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Could%20it%20pay%20to%20concentrate%20on%20the%20basics?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Support available for ABB System 800xA</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/800xA" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Support available for ABB System 800xA" /><published>2020-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/800xA</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/800xA">&lt;p class=&quot;tab&quot;&gt;800xA is the world's leading* distributed control system (DCS). However its power and flexibility come with a cost. It's not known as the easiest system to work with - making it hard to find quality independent support, ensure updates and backups are managed correctly, and the configuration keeps pace with changes to plant and operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;tab&quot;&gt;If you're looking for help with 800xA you may be experiencing one or more of these challenges:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Routine maintenance and updates&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;
  If left too long it can take days rather than minutes to recover from system failures or security incidents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Changes and modifications&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt; Out of date control systems aren't fit for purpose, leading people to work around, rather than benefit from them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Integrating 3rd party equipment&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt; Crucial to capture, store and analyse valuable process data but often seen as a nice to have, then never done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Adding extra features and functions&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt; Your sophisticated DCS isn't delivering the benefits promised thanks to constraints during the initial project. It now feels too hard or too expensive to add extra functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;tab&quot;&gt;Op-tec's engineers have a wealth of experience working with 800xA and offer services which complement software support you may already be getting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;tab&quot;&gt;Get in touch if you'd like to learn more about how we can help reduce the cost of owning this incredibly powerful technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fas fa-phone-alt&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;abbr title=&quot;Phone&quot;&gt;&lt;/abbr&gt; &amp;nbsp; &lt;a href=&quot;tel:00441616604293&quot; id=&quot;number&quot;&gt;+44 161 660 4293&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;                 
&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fas fa-envelope&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;abbr title=&quot;Email&quot;&gt;&lt;/abbr&gt; &amp;nbsp; &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:projects@op-tec.co.uk?subject=Support%20for%20800xA&quot;&gt;projects&amp;#64;op-tec.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* 800xA is the world's number one DCS based on global market share. This is based on annual reports by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.arcweb.com/&quot;&gt;ARC Advisory Group&lt;/a&gt; which for the last 20 years have found 800xA to be the most common DCS. ABB's history of acquisitions has gone a long way to securing this accolade. Many of these installations will have been originally supplied by one of the companies ABB has bought over the years:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Taylor&lt;/b&gt; &lt;small&gt;founded 1851, acquired by Combustion Engineering in 1983&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;b&gt;Bailey Controls&lt;/b&gt; &lt;small&gt;founded 1916, became part of Elsag Bailey Process Automation in 1989&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;b&gt;Combustion Engineering&lt;/b&gt; &lt;small&gt;merger of Grieve Grate and American Stoker in 1912, acquired 1990&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;b&gt;Fischer &amp; Porter&lt;/b&gt; &lt;small&gt;founded 1937, acquired by Elsag Bailey Process Automation in 1994&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;b&gt;Elsag Bailey Process Automation&lt;/b&gt; &lt;small&gt;merger of Bailey Controls and Elsag Group in 1989, acquired 1998&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;b&gt;Alfa Laval Automation&lt;/b&gt; &lt;small&gt;merger of SattControl and Alfa Laval in 1986, acquired 1998&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  
  
  
  


&lt;script type=&quot;application/ld+json&quot;&gt;{&quot;@context&quot;: &quot;https://schema.org&quot;,&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;FAQPage&quot;,&quot;mainEntity&quot;: 
[
{&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Question&quot;,&quot;name&quot;: &quot;What does ABB stand for?&quot;,&quot;acceptedAnswer&quot;: {&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Answer&quot;,&quot;text&quot;: &quot;Asea Brown Boveri.&quot;
}},
{&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Question&quot;,&quot;name&quot;: &quot;When did ABB first release 800xA?&quot;,&quot;acceptedAnswer&quot;: {&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Answer&quot;,&quot;text&quot;: &quot;ABB launched System 800xA in 2004.&quot;
}},
{&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Question&quot;,&quot;name&quot;: &quot;What's the latest version of 800xA?&quot;,&quot;acceptedAnswer&quot;: {&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Answer&quot;,&quot;text&quot;: &quot;The latest release of System 800xA (as of Dec 2020) is version 6.1.&quot;
}},            
{&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Question&quot;,&quot;name&quot;: &quot;What does 800xA stand for?&quot;,&quot;acceptedAnswer&quot;: {&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Answer&quot;,&quot;text&quot;: &quot;The system forms part of ABB's '800' product line, ‘xA’ stands for Extended Automation.&quot;
}},            
{&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Question&quot;,&quot;name&quot;: &quot;Is 800xA really 'the worlds number one' distributed control system?&quot;,&quot;acceptedAnswer&quot;: {&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Answer&quot;,&quot;text&quot;: &quot;This title, often quoted in ABB's marketing material, is based on research by the ARC Advisory Group. ARC have found 800xA to be the distributed control system (DCS) with largest global market share for the last 20 years.&quot;
}}]
}&lt;/script&gt;</content><author><name>Projects</name><email>cornelius@thewhip.com</email></author><category term="knowledge" /><summary type="html">800xA is the world's leading* distributed control system (DCS). However its power and flexibility come with a cost. It's not known as the easiest system to work with - making it hard to find quality independent support, ensure updates and backups are managed correctly, and the configuration keeps pace with changes to plant and operations. If you're looking for help with 800xA you may be experiencing one or more of these challenges: Routine maintenance and updates If left too long it can take days rather than minutes to recover from system failures or security incidents. Changes and modifications Out of date control systems aren't fit for purpose, leading people to work around, rather than benefit from them. Integrating 3rd party equipment Crucial to capture, store and analyse valuable process data but often seen as a nice to have, then never done. Adding extra features and functions Your sophisticated DCS isn't delivering the benefits promised thanks to constraints during the initial project. It now feels too hard or too expensive to add extra functions. Op-tec's engineers have a wealth of experience working with 800xA and offer services which complement software support you may already be getting. Get in touch if you'd like to learn more about how we can help reduce the cost of owning this incredibly powerful technology. &amp;nbsp; +44 161 660 4293 &amp;nbsp; projects&amp;#64;op-tec.co.uk * 800xA is the world's number one DCS based on global market share. This is based on annual reports by the ARC Advisory Group which for the last 20 years have found 800xA to be the most common DCS. ABB's history of acquisitions has gone a long way to securing this accolade. Many of these installations will have been originally supplied by one of the companies ABB has bought over the years: Taylor founded 1851, acquired by Combustion Engineering in 1983 Bailey Controls founded 1916, became part of Elsag Bailey Process Automation in 1989 Combustion Engineering merger of Grieve Grate and American Stoker in 1912, acquired 1990 Fischer &amp; Porter founded 1937, acquired by Elsag Bailey Process Automation in 1994 Elsag Bailey Process Automation merger of Bailey Controls and Elsag Group in 1989, acquired 1998 Alfa Laval Automation merger of SattControl and Alfa Laval in 1986, acquired 1998</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22engineers-using-simulator-3862149.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22engineers-using-simulator-3862149.jpg%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22engineers-using-simulator-3862149.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22engineers-using-simulator-3862149.jpg%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Using data to inform maintenance</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/using-data-to-inform-maintenance" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Using data to inform maintenance" /><published>2020-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/using-data-to-inform-maintenance</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/using-data-to-inform-maintenance">&lt;p&gt;How you use data analysis to inform maintenance activity can have a huge impact on the efficiency of your operations. It may never be possible to eliminate the risk of an unplanned shutdown entirely, but smart use of plant data can significantly reduce it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re sick of praying for things to keep working until the end of the day / week / month / year, keep reading!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are simple explanations of common maintenance approaches. If you’re new to the concept of data-informed maintenance, know there are companies out there already pushing far beyond these techniques. For example, using machine learning to identify external factors such as weather patterns or employee behaviour to better inform predictions. Or allowing their systems to automatically order spare parts and schedule preventative work before human operators have the chance to notice anything’s up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most likely you’ll say to yourself “we already do this” as you read through. If so, ask whether your existing processes are as effective as they could be. We see people manually undertaking this work &lt;strong&gt;a lot&lt;/strong&gt;, storing records on paper or retrieving it from ‘offline’ equipment only to import it into another system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So read on, then ask: ‘Could my organisation improve it’s maintenance regimes?’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;corrective-maintenance&quot;&gt;Corrective maintenance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wait until something breaks, then take action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“If it ain’t broke, don’t fix it”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it requires doing nothing this is often seen as the most cost-effective option. Only true if the cost of downtime, in-house expertise, and spare parts is less than those associated with a data-driven approach if this is the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If equipment in question is critical to operations rapid repair or replacement will be necessary to minimise disruption. Also referred to as reactive maintenance. This approach risks significant costs should catastrophic failure occur, where repair or replacement is not possible within a defined timeframe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No data is needed for this approach. Information available is often used to diagnose the cause of failures after the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;e.g. replacing a blown bulb&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;preventive-maintenance&quot;&gt;Preventive maintenance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intervene before failure becomes likely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“When was the cambelt last changed?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maintenance activities are performed before they’re required; typically at predetermined intervals based on historical records or manufacturer recommendations. Sometimes referred to as ‘proactive maintenance’ this technique allows work to be carried out during planned shutdowns minimising disruption. Taking this approach means performing maintenance before it’s needed, so the assumption is the resource needed to do this if cheaper than implementing a more data-driven approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This technique can be improved over time by using measurement, analysis and periodic testing to better inform service intervals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;e.g. changing car engine oil every 10,000 miles&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;risk-based-maintenance&quot;&gt;Risk-based maintenance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the impact into account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Get that boiler serviced before winter”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The effect a failure will have on operations and it’s likelihood is used to allocate available resource efficiently. The condition of assets will also be monitored to ensure changing risks, as equipment and machinery ages, is taken into account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quantity and quality of data used can vary widely, from the objective analysis of an employee to automated anaylsis of assets over time. It may also be useful to consider factors other than just equipment condition, such as market demand or stock levels.  Information gathered can also inform the schedule for replacing or upgrading equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;e.g. waiting until a shutdown to install software updates&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;condition-based-maintenance&quot;&gt;Condition-based maintenance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monitor ‘health’ for warning signs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“No signs of wear…“&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maintenance work is informed through performance monitoring of equipment. Typically, key parameters are recorded over time, and trends which indicate pending failure identified. Manual inspection during outages can also be used to determine when work needs to be carried out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Automated systems record device parameters over time. Maintenance is required when values deviate from ‘normal’ indicating the probability of a failure has increased to an unacceptable level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;e.g. a motor drawing more current than usual&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;predictive-maintenance&quot;&gt;Predictive maintenance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specific thresholds for action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“What does this warning light mean?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People are automatically alerted when specific scenarios are detected. The characteristics and failure modes of an asset will be known, so when partnered with condition monitoring pending failure can be detected and people warned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on how sophisticated a piece of equipment is, this may be a single error or warning light or a detailed fault code which accurately indentifies the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;e.g. car running in “limp mode” until it’s taken to the garage&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prescriptive-maintenance&quot;&gt;Prescriptive maintenance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recommended action provided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The freezer says it needs defrosting”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Users receive specific recommended actions to prevent failure. So rather than a description of the problem, they are given information about the action they need to take to avoid a failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No time is needed to fault-find or diagnose problems, as the piece of equipment states exacty what is required to address the situation. This also reduces the skill and expertise personnel need to be able to operate and maintain the asset. Original Equipment Manufacturers (OEMs) may provide this functionality for ‘user serviceable’ equipment, but ensure that more complicated or costly fixes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;e.g. dashboard: check tyre pressures&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reliability-centered-maintenance&quot;&gt;Reliability-centered maintenance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Identifying the best maintenance approach for each asset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“We can’t suffer a failure”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Past breakdowns are analysed to identify the best maintenance approach for each item of equipment, based on it’s historic and/or anticipated reliability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this instance an assets performance and reliability inform the most appropriate maintenance regime. New equipment will be maintained largely in line with the manufacturers recommendations. Then more weight given to historical records of condition and failure rate as the equipment ages. Like risk-based maintenance, when implemented properly this method is labour intensive, requiring knowledge of an assets’ failure modes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;e.g. establishing the safe minimum level of maintenance for an aircraft&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Projects</name><email>cornelius@thewhip.com</email></author><category term="knowledge" /><summary type="html">How you use data analysis to inform maintenance activity can have a huge impact on the efficiency of your operations. It may never be possible to eliminate the risk of an unplanned shutdown entirely, but smart use of plant data can significantly reduce it.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22praying-man-small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22praying-man.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22praying-man-small.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Not%20the%20most%20effective%20maintenance%20regime%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22praying-man-small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22praying-man.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22praying-man-small.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Not%20the%20most%20effective%20maintenance%20regime%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Do you invest in training people?</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/do-you-invest-in-training-people" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do you invest in training people?" /><published>2020-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/do-you-invest-in-training-people</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/do-you-invest-in-training-people">&lt;p&gt;When you purchase new equipment or technology how much do you invest in training people?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it’s negligible, or an afterthought when improvements aren’t realised, how do things look now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a graduate engineer I was baffled when my old employer moved to a newer version of Windows. They put on a huge number of training courses offering staff the chance to learn the new features available in the operating system and Office applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me it looked like a huge waste of time and money. Surely everyone has a computer at home? Surely people keep up with current technology and ways of working in their own time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was wrong, some do. Most don’t. Looking back, I’ve no doubt the training was worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’m still doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve never had formal training on MS Windows or Office. I’m eternally grateful when someone shows me a useful feature I didn’t know about. I’ve even been known to say “How am I only finding out about this now, this is going to save me loads of time….”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I’ll ask you again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you purchase new equipment or technology how much do you invest in training people?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Richard Banyard</name><email>richard.banyard@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><summary type="html">When you purchase new equipment or technology how much do you invest in training people?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22Picture1.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22Picture1.jpg%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22Picture1.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22Picture1.jpg%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Are you a grandmaster or a centaur?</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/are-you-a-grandmaster-or-a-centaur" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are you a grandmaster or a centaur?" /><published>2020-10-07T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-10-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/are-you-a-grandmaster-or-a-centaur</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/are-you-a-grandmaster-or-a-centaur">&lt;p&gt;May 1997 was a turning point in the world of chess. Garry Kasparov, chess grandmaster and world-champion at the time, was beaten by IBM’s Deep Blue 2.5 - 3.5 in a 6 match tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Popular attention subsequently moved to Go, where humans still had the edge. It took until March of 2016 before Google’s AlphaGo beat Lee Sedol 4 - 1. Since, it has been largely accepted that computers can out-compete humans when it comes to strategy board games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However after Kasparov’s defeat in 1997, he championed ‘freestyle chess’, to see how far technology could push the level of chess being played by teams made up of anyone or anything. As freestyle tournaments became more common something very interesting happened. Centaurs - humans using readily available chess software and off-the-shelf laptops - were able to win against the most advanced artificial intelligence running on supercomputers. There’s more: the best centaurs weren’t grandmasters, but amateur chess players with backgrounds such as gaming and programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does this tell us?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In freestyle chess you don’t have to be a grandmaster to beat the best AI. In fact being a grandmaster doesn’t improve your chances as much as being familiar with computers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People who train themselves using YouTube can now finish DIY projects with a level of quality previously only achieved by professionals who know the ‘trade secrets’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies are increasingly focused on retaining organisational knowledge in their processes and systems, reducing the impact of staff turnover. In fact the latest ISO 9001 quality standard is now explicit about this (clause 7.1.6 if you’ve got a copy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me the future looks like it belongs to those who, like centaurs, know how to best use technology. Not those who’ve amassed the most knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In which case the highest performing businesses will be those who’ve invested in their systems, processes and technology - and focused on making them easy for people to use.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Richard Banyard</name><email>richard.banyard@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><summary type="html">May 1997 was a turning point in the world of chess. Garry Kasparov, chess grandmaster and world-champion at the time, was beaten by IBM’s Deep Blue 2.5 - 3.5 in a 6 match tournament.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22tono-graphy-WtdIwprWnB4-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22tono-graphy-WtdIwprWnB4-unsplash.jpg%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22tono-graphy-WtdIwprWnB4-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22tono-graphy-WtdIwprWnB4-unsplash.jpg%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Are you choosing to drive blind?</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/are-you-driving-blind" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are you choosing to drive blind?" /><published>2020-03-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/are-you-driving-blind</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/are-you-driving-blind">&lt;p&gt;It sounds like madness, but I believe many manufacturers are doing just this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine you've bought a new car but the dashboard was an optional extra, you spent the money on metallic paint instead....&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200&quot; src=&quot;/images/Peugeot_206_WRC.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Peugeot 206 World Rally Championship car on two wheels&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Operating a factory without knowing the status and health of critical equipment is equivalent to driving a car without knowing the oil temperature or how much fuel is in the tank. Things are fine just now, and might be until you visit a garage... but Sod's law suggests a failure won't come just before the planned outage, but when the plant is under pressure to meet an important deadline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200&quot; src=&quot;/images/dashboard1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;car dashboard&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crazier, but no less common, is the purchase of expensive technology then a failure to integrate it with existing systems. I liken this to buying a retro-fit speedometer then allowing the mechanic to install it outside (it's cheaper and easier this way, try to imagine the project has already overspent and overrun....). Now every journey involves slowing, winding down the window to stick your head out - whenever you want to check how far you've come or how fast you're going! Surely paying staff to walk around a site to monitor or control equipment locally is just as inconvenient?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, alarms and alerts. Without lights to warn of impending problems, your new car will quickly depreciate in value and lose performance as faults go unnoticed causing lasting damage. I for one am always a little nervous of any taxi driver that can ignore multiple warnings from the dashboard, but at least they haven't taped over the lamps! I see operators of everything from printing presses to power stations with no central display for alarms and warnings. Witnessing alarms being ignored (because they've been there so long) or instruments looped out (because they aren't reliable) frequently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200&quot; src=&quot;/images/dashboard2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;car dashboard with warning lights&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, have I made fair comparisons? Is your organisation driving blind?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;p.s. if you're interested in the top photo, it's Juuso Pykälistö (FIN) in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2003_World_Rally_Championship&quot;&gt;2003 Swedish Rally&lt;/a&gt;, not driving blind, but pushing his &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peugeot_206_WRC&quot;&gt;Peugeot 206 WRC&lt;/a&gt; to its limits. Taken by Christopher Batt [&lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 2.0&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Richard Banyard</name><email>richard.banyard@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><summary type="html">It sounds like madness, but I believe many manufacturers are doing just this. Imagine you've bought a new car but the dashboard was an optional extra, you spent the money on metallic paint instead.... Operating a factory without knowing the status and health of critical equipment is equivalent to driving a car without knowing the oil temperature or how much fuel is in the tank. Things are fine just now, and might be until you visit a garage... but Sod's law suggests a failure won't come just before the planned outage, but when the plant is under pressure to meet an important deadline. Crazier, but no less common, is the purchase of expensive technology then a failure to integrate it with existing systems. I liken this to buying a retro-fit speedometer then allowing the mechanic to install it outside (it's cheaper and easier this way, try to imagine the project has already overspent and overrun....). Now every journey involves slowing, winding down the window to stick your head out - whenever you want to check how far you've come or how fast you're going! Surely paying staff to walk around a site to monitor or control equipment locally is just as inconvenient? Finally, alarms and alerts. Without lights to warn of impending problems, your new car will quickly depreciate in value and lose performance as faults go unnoticed causing lasting damage. I for one am always a little nervous of any taxi driver that can ignore multiple warnings from the dashboard, but at least they haven't taped over the lamps! I see operators of everything from printing presses to power stations with no central display for alarms and warnings. Witnessing alarms being ignored (because they've been there so long) or instruments looped out (because they aren't reliable) frequently. So, have I made fair comparisons? Is your organisation driving blind? p.s. if you're interested in the top photo, it's Juuso Pykälistö (FIN) in the 2003 Swedish Rally, not driving blind, but pushing his Peugeot 206 WRC to its limits. Taken by Christopher Batt [CC BY-SA 2.0]</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22Peugeot_206_WRC.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22Peugeot_206_WRC.jpg%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22Peugeot_206_WRC.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22Peugeot_206_WRC.jpg%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Transferring is the worst</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/transferring-is-the-worst" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transferring is the worst" /><published>2020-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/transferring-is-the-worst</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/transferring-is-the-worst">&lt;p&gt;You’ll know the scenario. I’m in France at the moment, but had a similar experience before Christmas in Ireland. It happens when I need to travel between unfamiliar places without enough time or inclination to properly research the best mode of transport. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, what should have been an easy journey of just 8km turned into a saga lasting several hours thanks to missed buses and failed connections. I’d literally have been better off walking!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repeating the experience in (yet) another place made me think... it’s not the main journey, but the much shorter transfer that often causes problems. The same is true when it comes to transferring data. Most of my clients have robust processes in place for updating their systems, migrating large amounts of historical data or remotely connecting to their control systems. However small, incidental, transfers often slip under the radar:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Capturing screenshots to email to a support engineer&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Importing a new company logo to update the HMI&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Extracting a one-off alarm report&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the short-term, ensuring individuals are aware of how to reduce the risks associated with USB sticks is a good start. Longer-term your procedures need to provide a quick and easy way to move 'incidental' data or you encourage people to work around them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The NCSC have a lot of guidance on this, much will be overkill for smaller control systems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncsc.gov.uk/guidance/pattern-safely-importing-data&quot;&gt;An architecture pattern for safely importing data into a system from an external source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best solution for you will (as always) depend on the output of your risk assessment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Want a hand with this stuff?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Richard Banyard</name><email>richard.banyard@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><summary type="html">You’ll know the scenario. I’m in France at the moment, but had a similar experience before Christmas in Ireland. It happens when I need to travel between unfamiliar places without enough time or inclination to properly research the best mode of transport. Last week, what should have been an easy journey of just 8km turned into a saga lasting several hours thanks to missed buses and failed connections. I’d literally have been better off walking! Repeating the experience in (yet) another place made me think... it’s not the main journey, but the much shorter transfer that often causes problems. The same is true when it comes to transferring data. Most of my clients have robust processes in place for updating their systems, migrating large amounts of historical data or remotely connecting to their control systems. However small, incidental, transfers often slip under the radar: Capturing screenshots to email to a support engineer Importing a new company logo to update the HMI Extracting a one-off alarm report In the short-term, ensuring individuals are aware of how to reduce the risks associated with USB sticks is a good start. Longer-term your procedures need to provide a quick and easy way to move 'incidental' data or you encourage people to work around them. The NCSC have a lot of guidance on this, much will be overkill for smaller control systems: An architecture pattern for safely importing data into a system from an external source The best solution for you will (as always) depend on the output of your risk assessment: Want a hand with this stuff?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22Stansted_Airport_Transit_route_diagram.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22Stansted_Airport_Transit_route_diagram.jpg%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22Stansted_Airport_Transit_route_diagram.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22Stansted_Airport_Transit_route_diagram.jpg%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">ATT&amp;amp;CK!</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/ATT&CK!" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ATT&amp;amp;CK!" /><published>2020-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/ATT&amp;CK!</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/ATT&amp;CK!">&lt;p&gt;The MITRE ATT&amp;amp;CK&lt;sup&gt;&amp;reg;&lt;/sup&gt; knowledge base for ICS is now publicly available. If you've not got time to check it out now, at least click on this link and bookmark it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a database of adversary tactics and techniques based on real-world observations. It contains very useful knowledge for those performing risk assessments and/or setting up monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you're the person responsible for security of your site's industrial networks, I strongly recommend you take a look if you aren't familiar already:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://collaborate.mitre.org/attackics/index.php/Main_Page&quot;&gt;https://collaborate.mitre.org/attackics/index.php/Main_Pages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;
&lt;p&gt;Need help getting on top of the security of your industrial networks?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Richard Banyard</name><email>richard.banyard@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><summary type="html">The MITRE ATT&amp;amp;CK&amp;reg; knowledge base for ICS is now publicly available. If you've not got time to check it out now, at least click on this link and bookmark it. This is a database of adversary tactics and techniques based on real-world observations. It contains very useful knowledge for those performing risk assessments and/or setting up monitoring. So if you're the person responsible for security of your site's industrial networks, I strongly recommend you take a look if you aren't familiar already: https://collaborate.mitre.org/attackics/index.php/Main_Pages &amp;nbsp; Need help getting on top of the security of your industrial networks?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22MITRE_ATTACK_logo_Lockup-black.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22MITRE_ATTACK_logo_Lockup-black.jpg%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22MITRE_ATTACK_logo_Lockup-black.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22MITRE_ATTACK_logo_Lockup-black.jpg%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Windows 7 end of life announcement</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/Windows-7-end-of-life" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Windows 7 end of life announcement" /><published>2019-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/Windows-7-end-of-life</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/Windows-7-end-of-life">&lt;p&gt;In case you've missed it, Microsoft support for Windows 7 and Server 2008 ends on 14th Jan 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the links to Microsoft's statements on the matter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://support.microsoft.com/en-gb/help/4057281/windows-7-support-will-end-on-january-14-2020&quot;&gt;https://support.microsoft.com/en-gb/help/4057281/windows-7-support-will-end-on-january-14-2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://support.microsoft.com/en-gb/help/4456235/end-of-support-for-windows-server-2008-and-windows-server-2008-r2&quot;&gt;https://support.microsoft.com/en-gb/help/4456235/end-of-support-for-windows-server-2008-and-windows-server-2008-r2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What the internet will tell you this means?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
When you 'Google', IT industry websites will come up top and recommend you upgrade all machines as a matter of urgency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What this actually means?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Assuming you're already keeping asset and risk registers up to date. Re-assess the risks of continuing to use these operating systems following 14th January, and make sure any additional mitigations needed are in place before then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Still running Windows 7 in the office or on a machine directly connected to the internet?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Listen to the IT websites and upgrade ASAP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unsure or don't have a Cyber Security Management System in place?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get in touch.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Richard Banyard</name><email>richard.banyard@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><summary type="html">In case you've missed it, Microsoft support for Windows 7 and Server 2008 ends on 14th Jan 2020. Here's the links to Microsoft's statements on the matter: https://support.microsoft.com/en-gb/help/4057281/windows-7-support-will-end-on-january-14-2020 https://support.microsoft.com/en-gb/help/4456235/end-of-support-for-windows-server-2008-and-windows-server-2008-r2 What the internet will tell you this means? When you 'Google', IT industry websites will come up top and recommend you upgrade all machines as a matter of urgency. What this actually means? Assuming you're already keeping asset and risk registers up to date. Re-assess the risks of continuing to use these operating systems following 14th January, and make sure any additional mitigations needed are in place before then. Still running Windows 7 in the office or on a machine directly connected to the internet? Listen to the IT websites and upgrade ASAP. Unsure or don't have a Cyber Security Management System in place? Get in touch.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22Win7.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22Win7.jpg%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22Win7.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22Win7.jpg%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Have you got what it takes to make decisions?</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/make-better-decisions" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Have you got what it takes to make decisions?" /><published>2019-10-09T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-10-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/make-better-decisions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/make-better-decisions">&lt;p&gt;Tough decisions are never easy, even with the right information. So asking yourself or someone else to make a serious decision, with information that is presented poorly, not current or even relevant, isn't a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However many control system users are doing this everyday by using poorly designed or maintained Human Machine Interfaces (HMI).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of a HMI is to provide information to system users, allowing them to make decisions. However, good HMI design takes time, time that is often 'saved' when projects are delivered. This leaves a legacy of control systems with terrible user interfaces, which at best waste time and energy, but at worst represent a significant risk to plant personnel and equipment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good opportunity to improve displays comes when systems are upgraded. Unfortunately there is often the same pressure to save time and money, along with reluctance from system users to make changes to interfaces they are familiar with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is unfortunate, as good HMI design can reduce load on users while improving their effectiveness. Often the time delay between an undesirable event occurring and a remedial action being taken is significant, wasting resources and impacting profitability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Op-tec always recommend software well equipped with display objects compliant with industry best practise, for example &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eemua.org/Products/Publications/Print/EEMUA-Publication-201.aspx&quot;&gt;EEMUA 201&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hse.gov.uk/comah/sragtech/techmeascontrol.htm&quot;&gt;HSE guidance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Demo-HMI-Macboook+Iphone-Mock.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Inductive Automation's Ignition SCADA&quot; width=&quot;200&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;small&gt;Inductive Automation's Ignition SCADA&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Richard Banyard</name><email>richard.banyard@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><summary type="html">Tough decisions are never easy, even with the right information. So asking yourself or someone else to make a serious decision, with information that is presented poorly, not current or even relevant, isn't a good idea. However many control system users are doing this everyday by using poorly designed or maintained Human Machine Interfaces (HMI). The purpose of a HMI is to provide information to system users, allowing them to make decisions. However, good HMI design takes time, time that is often 'saved' when projects are delivered. This leaves a legacy of control systems with terrible user interfaces, which at best waste time and energy, but at worst represent a significant risk to plant personnel and equipment. A good opportunity to improve displays comes when systems are upgraded. Unfortunately there is often the same pressure to save time and money, along with reluctance from system users to make changes to interfaces they are familiar with. This is unfortunate, as good HMI design can reduce load on users while improving their effectiveness. Often the time delay between an undesirable event occurring and a remedial action being taken is significant, wasting resources and impacting profitability. Op-tec always recommend software well equipped with display objects compliant with industry best practise, for example EEMUA 201 and HSE guidance. Inductive Automation's Ignition SCADA</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22Demo-HMI-Macboook+Iphone-Mock.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22Demo-HMI-Macboook+Iphone-Mock.jpg%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22Demo-HMI-Macboook+Iphone-Mock.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22Demo-HMI-Macboook+Iphone-Mock.jpg%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>