<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-08-02T17:30:43+01:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/atom.xml</id><title type="html">Op-tec Systems</title><subtitle>This is a description of Op-tec's awesome site.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Avoid getting locked into a single automation vendor</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/how-to-avoid-vendor-lock-in" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Avoid getting locked into a single automation vendor" /><published>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/how-to-avoid-vendor-lock-in</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/how-to-avoid-vendor-lock-in">&lt;p&gt;If you represent a large multi-national company, and are looking to standardise on one automation vendor who will become a strategic partner, this article isn’t for you. With your scale you’ll have enough power over your chosen supplier to agree pricing structures, encourage development of new products, and ensure support for your equipment continues for as long as you need it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For everyone else, particularly SMEs, the downsides of being reliant on a single supplier often outweigh the ups. Do any of these sound familiar: lack of bargaining power; no access to the latest innovations until they’re adopted by your supplier; feeling forced into product updates; excessive license costs to transfer data into other systems?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If so keep reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The established automation vendors have a wealth of industry experience and expertise, product portfolios which meet almost every need, and provide high-quality support throughout the lifecycle of their products. The flip side to this is their ability to lock customers into their ecosystems, securing future revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So is it possible to benefit from the undoubtedly high quality products and services offered by the main vendors without getting locked-in? I believe so. Below is high-level guidance for how to do so, followed by more detailed considerations intended to help engineers with the practical implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guidance&quot;&gt;Guidance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-own-your-digital-infrastructure&quot;&gt;1. Own your ‘digital infrastructure’&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t just your networks and computer systems, but the intellectual property built into software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the centre of any business which has digitally transformed is a datastore containing every data point and piece of information about the company’s operations. This isn’t unstructured data, a lot of effort will have gone into developing data structures which model physical assets. These ‘Digital Twins’ not only define the characteristics of individual pieces of equipment, but also how they communicate with one another and the human workforce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having ownership and control of this central datastore sounds like a no-brainer, it contains the inner workings of your business and a substantial amount of its IP after all. But you’d be surprised at how many companies let automation vendors design these data structures. In so doing, handing them control over how they operate now and into the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-standardise-on-open-technology&quot;&gt;2. Standardise on ‘Open Technology’&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wherever possible Open communication protocols should be used, between equipment provided by different suppliers and perhaps more importantly within systems and solutions. Do not accept arguments about proprietary technology being cheaper and more efficient. This may be the case during project execution, but will almost certainly not be over the equipment’s lifecycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, you should standardise on certain protocols and technology to reduce costs associated with operation and maintenance. But an architecture built using well selected open technologies will ensure you always have a choice of supplier for any future maintenance, modification or migration work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-produce-accurate-and-comprehensive-user-requirement-specifications&quot;&gt;3. Produce accurate and comprehensive User Requirement Specifications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time invested in developing complete User Requirement Specification (URS) documents will rarely be wasted - only if you later decide not to proceed with the project. These are the vehicle for communicating your work to this point to your supply chain. Not only do accurate and comprehensive URSs make it easier to evaluate proposals, but also ensure your suppliers deliver according to your needs and not what’s easiest or most profitable for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;URSs which identify and set out how your supplier’s scope of supply will contribute to your business’s objectives also make evaluated success on contribution to the business rather than simply ‘delivered to scope’ far easier and speeds up the rate at which your organisation learns lessons and improves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-align-your-procurement-strategy-to-your-objectives&quot;&gt;4. Align your procurement strategy to your objectives&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And not cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can’t be emphasised enough. If cost was the only factor driving technology projects you’d evaluate every one against the cost of simply maintaining your current equipment. No, the benefits of technology projects need to be clearly identified and built into your procurement process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to note, this doesn’t necessitate making crucial decisions on qualitative measures of success – business cases which put a monetary value on achieving strategic objectives are a powerful tool to prioritise and justify investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implementation&quot;&gt;Implementation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-own-your-digital-infrastructure-1&quot;&gt;1. Own your ‘digital infrastructure’&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digital infrastructure, as we define it, can be broken into hardware and software components. To ensure your physical infrastructure is capable of supporting equipment from any vendor and future expansion and upgrade, you’ll need to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create and maintain an up-to-date asset register which documents all ‘active’ devices and the connections between them and external systems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Determine standards for connections at all levels of your system architecture, considering different requirements for resilience, bandwith and determinism&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decide where your central datastore/unified namespace/single source of truth will or does reside&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Review your asset register identifying objects with similar characteristics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A strong relationship with your IT department is crucial to your success. They’re your gateway to delivering data to users via higher level company networks, and can support you with expertise and resources in areas such as networking, security and cloud computing.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The software component of your infrastructure is all about establishing standards you can impose on suppliers of automation, which define how your facility runs. This largely takes the form of data structures for communications between systems, and the digital twins which reside in your central datastore. Standards are required for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Communications between equipment, systems and the human workforce&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Object types for tangible assets like shop floor equipment and fleet vehicles, as well as intangible assets like production batches and material deliveries&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All types of HMI&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data structures for all databases and communication pathways&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Security models for managing access to data and information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-standardise-on-open-technology-1&quot;&gt;2. Standardise on ‘Open Technology’&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideally all communications between your automation systems and system components should be via open protocols. In practice this isn’t always in your control, for example packaged equipment must be treated in many cases as a ‘black box’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider how far down in your architecture you wish to specify the protocols in use. You may, for example, be willing to tolerate proprietary communciation between a PLC’s processor and input/output cards. In which case you’ll have to accept using equipment from the same manufacturer for any future upgrade or expansion of this device - unless complete replacement is acceptable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now review your facility in light of this decision:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Review existing systems, noting the protocols used to communciate within individual systems (between CPUs, I/O modules, HMIs, …), and across the entire facility (between PLCs, SCADA systems, smart devices, historians, reporting tools, …)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Record this information in your asset register&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a list of the communication protocols in use across your site, noting which are proprietary and which open&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Determine the protocols you wish to standardise on for each type of communication path&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-produce-accurate-and-comprehensive-user-requirement-specifications-1&quot;&gt;3. Produce accurate and comprehensive User Requirement Specifications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Centralising requirements for HMI design, communication protocols, HMI design, alarming, etc. will ensure technology you invest in is consistent in quality and will communciate with any other system you install in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll need to create a URS, however brief, to define every project you undertake. However this will become easier as you build a core library of standards detailing your expectations and requirements for suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many specification documents you need, and the level of detail they go into, depends on many factors. These include: the scale and complexity of your operations, the currentl level of automation, in-house skills and expertise, and existing relationships with suppliers. If you are early in this process prioritise according to where your company will see the greatest gains. Below is a list of questions to get you thinking:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How much do you anticipate spending on automation in the coming years?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What impact has an over-reliance on certain suppliers had on your business to this point?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you have skills and expertise in-house?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can you allocate sufficient resource to this, not just now, but in the future?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-align-your-procurement-strategy-to-your-objectives-1&quot;&gt;4. Align your procurement strategy to your objectives&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investments in automation should be treated by the business as strategic, as those into CRM or ERP systems. Not all automation solutions are the same, and companies will have to live with the costs of selecting the wrong technology for decades. Particularly if they allow suppliers to deliver to their own specifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those responsible for procuring automation, should be educated in these consequences along with the potential upsides of putting in digital technology which will drive performance increases across the organisation. Buyers must be incentivised to provide the technology which will best deliver on the company’s strategic objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Incorporate learning back into your specification documents and guidance to buyers. Sometimes the true cost of a particular technology is only revealed once the equipment is in production, or even when the time comes to replace it. The main vendors are very adept at concealing the costs of maintaining, upgrading and modifying their systems so every effort should be made to anticipate this in your URS documentation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Systems should be supplied with any functionality and license costs included, which allow connection via open protocols. This is particularly important for users of distributed control systems (DCS), where 5 figure sums are not uncommon for the equipment and licenses needed to allow data to be retrieved from systems via OPC an extremely common industrial ethernet-based protocol. Include the additional costs suppliers apply to such functionality in any comparisons you make between solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putting the processes and procedures in place to ensure you correctly specify automation projects to avoid being locked into a suppliers’ ecosystem is not free. It may put more pressure on your existing engineering team, or even require you to recruit or contract the necessary expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether this expense is worth it will depend on your situation. By ‘commoditising’ the components of your automation systems you’ll have much greater control over the technology available and what you pay for it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Richard Banyard</name><email>richard.banyard@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="knowledge" /><summary type="html">If you represent a large multi-national company, and are looking to standardise on one automation vendor who will become a strategic partner, this article isn’t for you. With your scale you’ll have enough power over your chosen supplier to agree pricing structures, encourage development of new products, and ensure support for your equipment continues for as long as you need it.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22hasan-almasi-aIRBGPafi74-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22hasan-almasi-aIRBGPafi74-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22hasan-almasi-aIRBGPafi74-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Is%20a%20single%20vendor%20system%20based%20on%20open%20technology%20possible?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22hasan-almasi-aIRBGPafi74-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22hasan-almasi-aIRBGPafi74-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22hasan-almasi-aIRBGPafi74-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Is%20a%20single%20vendor%20system%20based%20on%20open%20technology%20possible?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Waking up your data</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/waking-up-your-data" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Waking up your data" /><published>2021-04-13T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-04-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/waking-up-your-data</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/waking-up-your-data">&lt;p&gt;We live in an ever more competitive age where increasing the capability of our assets is becoming more and more important. However, we rarely think in terms of how important the data that surrounds us is and how it can help improve our operations. Many well-known institutions and blue chip companies are effectively ‘Sleeping Giants’ when it comes to this issue. They find it difficult to recognise the importance of their data because the nature of their business hasn’t changed. Simply not considering themselves technology firms, they see established supply chains, tried and tested operating procedures, and fixed assets their competitive advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what separates less data centric companies from those happy to invest in technology who analyse every heartbeat of their operations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer often lies in culture and the way manufacturing demand is perceived. All industries are subject to manufacturing and/or performance targets driven by the need to remain competitive.  However, historically much of heavy industry has been less concerned with performance, whereas ‘lighter’ industries tend to think much more in terms of cost per unit. It’s more common to see certain industries focused on how costs are measured, how the manufacturing process runs and how all of this affects product manufacturing throughput and quality. The fact many lighter industries are also discrete manufacturing entities and subject to market ‘Pull’ conditions also tends to necessitate a ‘high efficiency’ mindset. Continuous and heavy industries seem more likely to succumb to “we’ve always done it this way” thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, there are good and bad examples in all industries. Whichever way you look at it making improvements in your processes to save money can only be a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real issue is a company’s vision and strategy and whether they include the improvement of its manufacturing processes, to both increase product manufacturing capacity and improve quality. Both are key factors which ultimately increase a company’s profitability and competitiveness, but require investment. These important issues are subject to specific standards regarding asset management, the most notable being ISO 5500x (i.e. ISO 55000, 55001 and 55002) which were derived from the BSI PSA 55 2014 standard. These standards advocate a systematic process for managing company assets which: increases reliability, reduces downtime, improves quality, reduces waste, increases customer satisfaction, and ultimately makes the company more competitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investment… in our personal lives we are only too keen to invest when it provides a good return and ensures the roof doesn’t fall down. But at work one of the most common phrases remains “sweating the assets”, even if it seems to the detriment of efficiency and reliability. Surely this doesn’t make sense when for a fraction of the cost of the benefits the plant can be made to run more reliably and efficiently saving £££’s in the process?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Sweating the assets” (also known as the ‘Breakdown strategy’, incidentally) will one day result in catastrophic failure, halting production completely. Companies following such a strategy would benefit enormously from adopting the ISO 55000 standard – unless closure of the plant is in the short-term plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ISO 55000 aligns a company’s objectives and goals with a method of ensuring they are implemented via a process of continuous improvement. Once adopted as company policy by senior management the system provides a vehicle and framework for improvement. Stakeholders will be reassured the company is proactively and systematically improving the business and ensuring its sustainability and profitability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting back to the title of this article… a key concept is the ‘Hidden Plant’ and using data to uncover potential gains and enable you to measure the benefit of improvements. Once you’ve put in place a system for capturing and analysing your plant’s data you can make changes to your processes in alignment with your company’s objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These systems enable predictive maintenance to be planned reducing preventative action which shuts down plant unnecessarily. Continuously monitoring the health of assets over time also shows their gradual degradation. This tells you the most economical time to replace equipment, avoiding it operating outside defined levels of performance or where the likelihood of catastrophic failure is too great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the vast majority of cases the essential data required to improve the running and performance of your plant is already in place. The issue is how to display this data in a way that is meaningful to the plant operations staff and what the cost of this is versus the benefits. So let’s look at how we can determine whether the investment needed to provide an Asset Management system outweighs the cost of the investment. Let’s take an example where the cost of an Asset Performance System is £30k and its lifetime is 10 years:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An average cost saving of £3k/year would justify the investment. For many production facilities, one single breakdown lasting as little as 30 minutes could cost as much as £30k. So if one half-hour unplanned outage is prevented the company recovers its initial investment. Additional benefits would also be the collation and visualisation of data at the company’s HQ where the monitoring of each manufacturing facility is carried out by performance personnel, thus likely enabling local staff to be redeployed resulting in further savings via increased efficiency. Add to this maintenance savings, increased predictability (and therefore quality) and longer asset life, and hopefully the benefits of Asset Management are clear to see.*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The figure below shows how a large number of plants can benefit from a single Asset Management System. Data is published by each site location and analysed centrally, with advisory or control information sent back ensuring each plant runs optimally and continuous improvement actions can be quickly implemented across the organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/asset-management-example.png&quot; alt=&quot;Asset Management Example&quot; style=&quot;float: left&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;small&gt;Example of organisation-wide asset management system&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested to learn more about how automation technology can help you get more from your existing assets then understanding how your current situation compares to industry best practice is a good place to start. Click the button below to find out about how your bespoke Digital Benchmark Report™ provides you with this, and tailored recommended actions you can take to improve your company’s digital infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-benchmark&quot; class=&quot;btn&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Get your Digital Benchmark Report&lt;/b&gt;&amp;trade;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*This business case has been greatly simplified, ignoring the cost of capital among the many other factors which can influence investment decisions in organisations. If building business cases is an area you need help in, we are experienced in working with our clients to build robust and measurable project justifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Download a PDF copy of this article &lt;a href=&quot;https://op-tec.co.uk/downloads/Waking_up_your_data_-_Op-tec_Systems.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;u&gt;here&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Roger Halliwell</name><email>roger.halliwell@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><summary type="html">We live in an ever more competitive age where increasing the capability of our assets is becoming more and more important. However, we rarely think in terms of how important the data that surrounds us is and how it can help improve our operations. Many well-known institutions and blue chip companies are effectively ‘Sleeping Giants’ when it comes to this issue. They find it difficult to recognise the importance of their data because the nature of their business hasn’t changed. Simply not considering themselves technology firms, they see established supply chains, tried and tested operating procedures, and fixed assets their competitive advantage.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-thisisengineering-3861969_small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-thisisengineering-3861969_small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22pexels-thisisengineering-3861969.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22How%20valuable%20is%20your%20data?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-thisisengineering-3861969_small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-thisisengineering-3861969_small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22pexels-thisisengineering-3861969.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22How%20valuable%20is%20your%20data?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Quantum Leap Technologies</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/client-profile/QL-Tech" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quantum Leap Technologies" /><published>2021-04-07T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-04-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/client-profile/QL-Tech</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/client-profile/QL-Tech">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Even if you can’t recall exactly where you were when you heard the news of the Gulf of Mexico Deepwater Horizon disaster, it’s likely that you will remember quite a lot about one of the most environmentally and commercially damaging incidents in the history of oil and gas operations, which cost the lives of 11 people. After the immediate explosion, oil continued leaking from the well at a rate of up to 60,000 barrels a day.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A company based in Aberdeen, Scotland, has developed an ingenious solution for blowout prevention in collaboration with Op-tec Systems that involves repurposing electric motors and drivetrain technology similar to carmaker Tesla’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We were contracted by a large oil and gas company in the USA to build a blowout prevention application for offshore drilling and extraction operations,” says Ben Bamford, founder and CEO of Quantum Leap Technologies (QL Tech). “They were looking for new ideas of how to control that equipment and to ensure a high level of assurance that the issues were being addressed.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thinking-laterally&quot;&gt;Thinking laterally&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conventional way of preventing, managing or suppressing a blowout or similar emergency is to use huge, gas-filled bottles to push liquid out at high pressure. QL Tech and Op-tec came up with something rather different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We took the heart of a Tesla Model S car: the battery, inverter and motor. Instead of putting wheels on it, we attached a pump to the electric motor,” Ben says. “Our solution, which provides hydraulic fluid to operate the safety equipment, is powered from a battery system and can accelerate output equivalent to doing 0 to 60 mph in a few seconds. We were integrating advanced technology that has recently come to the fore and been qualified for electric car applications. The engineering challenge was to demonstrate that the system can be used robustly for a safety application.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Battery power is maintained by trickle-feed of electricity so that it is always ready to be deployed, with zero notice. The whole system had to be made sufficiently robust to withstand the harsh environment at a marine depth of 3,000 metres, including ultra-high pressure, currents, temperature and the corrosive influence of saltwater, and to do so in an emergency where time was critical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-project-put-into-practice-ideas-and-objectives-that-op-tec-and-ql-tech-have-in-common&quot;&gt;The project put into practice ideas and objectives that Op-tec and QL Tech have in common.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Op-tec helped us with PLC (programmable logic control) and software elements. Richard (Banyard) and I are kindred spirits, in feeling there is so much more that can be done with low-cost hardware, the application of a bit more machine intelligence and a bit more focus on integrating with existing systems,” Ben explains. “Some of the new pieces of technology and commoditised software building blocks are really changing the game.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;QL Tech has three operating divisions: Integrated Power Solutions, which provides class-leading battery, inverter and control systems; 57 Degrees, which develops and delivers intelligent robotics for industrial applications; and Leap Automation, which provides accessible, affordable automation services to the manufacturing sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unusually for the automation sector, it is a vertically-integrated company. It designs and builds its own robot arms and tools, as well as working with specialist collaborators and partners, like Op-tec. It has a novel approach to the application of artificial intelligence, as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dont-over-engineer-solutions-that-arent-needed&quot;&gt;Don’t over-engineer solutions that aren’t needed&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Building a robot arm is easier and cheaper than it has ever been before and we have found that, in many applications, artificial intelligence-driven robots don’t need the same level of precision of conventional robots,” Ben explains. It’s quite a bold assertion when precision for many automated tasks is essential. “Some robots are being sold to food and drink companies, for example, that are over -engineered, in our view. Very much more basic systems can provide tremendous amounts of value. By engineering solutions that are specific to the customers we can make the economics work and hit economies of scale much sooner.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ben mentioned a brewery that had examined a machine to automate the sorting and packing of cans. QL Tech suggested a solution that, instead of being absolutely precise, was ‘good enough’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our solution was much simpler mechanically but much more complex from a software perspective,” he continues. “The artificial intelligence we are using and the vision system we have built-in allows the robot to interpret the world around it. We don’t need the cans to be in exactly the right spot; it just needs to be in the right area and the robot will pick and pack it successfully.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;QL Tech is bringing similar thinking to a solution for painting undersea pipe and pumping applications, and to systems for detecting faults in food processing lines, such as spotting and removing defective bread rolls. Quantum Leap Technologies believes so strongly in its approach to business that it allows customers to rent a solution and to try before buying, which helps reduce risk and make automation more available for SMEs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Download a PDF copy of this article &lt;a href=&quot;https://op-tec.co.uk/downloads/QL_Tech_&amp;amp;_Op-tec_Systems_-_Better_than_Cure.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;u&gt;here&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Projects</name><email>projects@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="client-profile" /><summary type="html">Even if you can’t recall exactly where you were when you heard the news of the Gulf of Mexico Deepwater Horizon disaster, it’s likely that you will remember quite a lot about one of the most environmentally and commercially damaging incidents in the history of oil and gas operations, which cost the lives of 11 people. After the immediate explosion, oil continued leaking from the well at a rate of up to 60,000 barrels a day.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-zukiman-mohamad-87236.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-zukiman-mohamad-87236.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-zukiman-mohamad-87236.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-zukiman-mohamad-87236.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Much ado about heating</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/Much-ado-about-heating" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Much ado about heating" /><published>2021-03-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-03-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/Much-ado-about-heating</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/Much-ado-about-heating">&lt;p&gt;There is much debate on the efficacy of heat pumps for domestic heating, but heat pumps alone are not the answer. There are a number of technologies in the heat transfer, energy storage and electricity supply industries that need to be integrated, and done successfully, the whole will be greater than the sum of the parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an attempt to add light as well as heat to the discussion we must consider the heat pump paradox: When you need it most it gives you least. And to make sure it gives you enough in the worst case scenario, you have to over-size it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worst case scenario would be an air source heat pump operating in the depths of winter. Being expected to produce viable domestic hot water and heat a dwelling simultaneously  really is scraping the bottom of the cost-efficiency barrel and should be considered as the desperate last resort. It will work, but  the plant will be uneconomically oversized, it will be working at the limits of its envelope, there will be frequent periods without heat due to defrosts, efficiency will be at its lowest and the demand for, and hence the price of, electricity will be at its highest. This is what the heat-pump user remembers long after the glossy advertising brochures have been recycled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The air-source heat pump needs some help. Consider adding alternative resources, such as a borehole to transfer heat from deep beneath the ground. If the ground can offer a higher grade source of heat than ambient air, then it would make sense to use that as the preferred heat source. The challenge then is that as surely as digging coal out, or pumping oil out of the ground, the energy source viability will be depleted gradually unless you have the luxury of local volcanic activity, which can bring its own problems. You still have the issue of high electricity price, but the plant could be more economically sized, and efficiency for at least the first year will far exceed what air source could achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summer, domestic hot water is the dominant but lesser heating demand, air temperature is high, sun is shining on the photo-voltaic panels, fresh breezes are spinning the turbines, and on the smart grid electricity demand and hence the price, is low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the heat pump paradox: When you need it least it gives you most. And if a heat pump is sized for winter operation then it will give you far more than you actually need in summer. The excess capacity can be used to replace the heat extracted from the ground during winter whilst providing the benefit of comfort cooling, and this can be done while electricity is plentiful and cheap and the air heat source is good, so the ground can now used as an efficient heat sink to store cheap energy when the heat pump efficiency and cost-effectiveness is at its best. Summer is the perfect opportunity to deposit heat into the energy bank surrounding the borehole, for use later, in winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dual source, dual sink heat pump technology is well proven in hundreds of commercial and retail premises throughout the land, and the principles hold good to fulfil a domestic role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smart Grid technology is also well proven and can feed electricity price and availability data into controllers equipped with the intelligence to use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowledge is having information. Wisdom is knowing how to use knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logical steps would be the combination of the air source heat pump with its ground resource counterpart, capitalising on the best efficiencies at the best times as identified by smart grid pricing, to maximise heat transfer and minimise expenditure on electricity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Integrating an intelligent controller that can measure and record the heat transfer from air-resource to load, or air-resource to ground-resource, or ground-resource to load, and learn to optimise the energy usage, would enable selection of the most appropriate operating mode to maximise the overall annual efficiency of not merely an intelligent heat pump installation, but wise heat pump operation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Peter Jackson</name><email>peter.jackson@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><summary type="html">There is much debate on the efficacy of heat pumps for domestic heating, but heat pumps alone are not the answer. There are a number of technologies in the heat transfer, energy storage and electricity supply industries that need to be integrated, and done successfully, the whole will be greater than the sum of the parts.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-2581922.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-2581922.jpg%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-2581922.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-2581922.jpg%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Get to know Richard Banyard</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/richard-banyard" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Get to know Richard Banyard" /><published>2021-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/richard-banyard</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/richard-banyard">&lt;p&gt;Richard Banyard took a typical route into engineering, studying control and automation at Sheffield before enrolling onto ABB’s graduate scheme. During his 10 years with ABB, Richard worked in a variety of roles from project engineering, internal sales and technical management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since buying Op-tec Systems Richard has relocated and grown the business year-on-year. Keeping the focus on client outcomes, Richard continues to build on a strong foundation of robust processes, broad expertise and deep understanding of the pressures facing UK industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read what Richard has to say here on our blog, he’s also been featured in the following publications:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://issuu.com/the-eic/docs/insideenergyfebruary2021&quot;&gt;one-to-one interview&lt;/a&gt; in the February 2021 edition of the EIC’s Inside Energy (pages 6-7)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Projects</name><email>projects@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="knowledge" /><summary type="html">Richard Banyard took a typical route into engineering, studying control and automation at Sheffield before enrolling onto ABB’s graduate scheme. During his 10 years with ABB, Richard worked in a variety of roles from project engineering, internal sales and technical management.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22Richard-working.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22Richard-working-feature.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22Richard-working.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Richard%20Banyard,%20Op-tec's%20MD%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22Richard-working.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22Richard-working-feature.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22Richard-working.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Richard%20Banyard,%20Op-tec's%20MD%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Maximise your ROI from technology projects</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/why-technology-projects-fail-to-deliver" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Maximise your ROI from technology projects" /><published>2021-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/why-technology-projects-fail-to-deliver</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/why-technology-projects-fail-to-deliver">&lt;p&gt;There are several pitfalls I see affecting technology projects time and time again. To help clients avoid them I’ve written a lot about the common problems I see and how to overcome them. The blog post is the first of many which aim to share this knowledge with a wider audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;productisation&quot;&gt;Productisation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many products, services and ‘solutions’ offered by consultancies and vendors aren’t designed to address the needs of the end-user. Instead they are designed to be easy to sell repeatably, and generate opportunities for recurring revenue. This isn’t a problem in itself, in terms of technology it would be cost prohibitive to engineer solutions to every problem from first principles. But it does mean the components of every project or service are ‘productised’ to some degree and systems sold on the merits of these products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conflicts of interest arise when the end-user/purchaser hasn’t been able to translate their long-term strategic objectives into the functional requirements. These don’t just help determine the most suitable solutions from the marketplace but also the true measures of success.
When purchasing, engineering or project management decisions aren’t based on strategic objectives. Not being able to relate products to the benefits they deliver can lead to undesirable outcomes…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is you if the sales presentation ‘chimed’ - the solution discussed delivered the key objectives your management team laid out in their strategy meeting – but the final solution failed to live up to expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your procurement function may have focused on costs rather than benefits. If so, they will have pushed the supplier to reduce cost, meaning the add-on components needed to deliver the key benefits were removed from the scope of supply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it was your supplier’s own engineering team. A common situation is the solution ‘sold’ is uncomfortable for engineers to deliver, due to its complexity or novelty. They may not have experience working with ‘products’ proposed, so don’t get the best out of them. They may be uncertain the resulting solution would meet more basic criteria such as availability and reliability so remove ‘bells and whistles’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another group who could be responsible are project managers on either side. They may not be properly incentivised to deliver strategic objectives. Or could see hitting budget or timing expectations as more important measures of success. In which case they’re likely to unknowingly compromise the return a project delivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the cause, a lack of clear communication of, and focus on, the benefits to be delivered and why they are so important to achieve can result in a project’s value not being fully realised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fixing-scope&quot;&gt;Fixing scope&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way focus shifts to costs and deadlines, is when a project’s scope is fixed prematurely. Yes, late changes cost more to make than they would if they were picked up earlier in the project…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, suppliers never have the time and resources to fully engineer a solution during the bid and proposal stage. Likely similarities with past projects were used to quickly create a specification and price, then this work ‘tweaked’ to meet any unique requirements. Internal Sales Engineers have a significant influence on the design, but they tend to be generalists rather than subject matter experts. It’s only a good way into the project when people with specialist knowledge of the technology have taken every requirement into account (as they finish design work and you move to the build phase).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now ask yourself if it’s sensible to the fix the scope at the beginning of the project, before subject matter experts have been given time to fully evaluate the requirements and complete the detailed design. Doing so risks missing out of the knowledge and expertise they bring to the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, making changes during the second half of this process is more costly. That’s why any changes proposed must be carefully scrutinised against the strategic objectives of the project. Assuming the original scope will achieve the outcomes you desire, regardless of any new knowledge acquired by subject matter experts, is very dangerous. It can easily lead to change requests being evaluated with a focus on cost and time, with benefits the project is meant to deliver taking a back seat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;integration&quot;&gt;Integration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology projects are a focused period of activity, they typically involve working with suppliers, maybe also advisors, consultants, vendors, and other third parties. As such they are often thought of as a standalone activity, executed alongside operations then delivered and completed.
This is a trap, which many organisations who fail to properly integrate new technology fall into. The organisation isn’t aligned with the technology, so can’t use it to best effect and so expected returns aren’t realised. In a future article I’ll discuss this in more detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, get in touch if you’d like to find out more about how we help manufacturers with their technology projects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fas fa-phone-alt&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;abbr title=&quot;Phone&quot;&gt;&lt;/abbr&gt; &amp;nbsp; &lt;a href=&quot;tel:00441616604293&quot; id=&quot;number&quot;&gt;+44 161 660 4293&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fas fa-envelope&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;abbr title=&quot;Email&quot;&gt;&lt;/abbr&gt; &amp;nbsp; &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:projects@op-tec.co.uk?subject=Maximising%20the%20return%20from%20technology%20projects&quot;&gt;projects&amp;#64;op-tec.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Richard Banyard</name><email>richard.banyard@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="knowledge" /><summary type="html">There are several pitfalls I see affecting technology projects time and time again. To help clients avoid them I’ve written a lot about the common problems I see and how to overcome them. The blog post is the first of many which aim to share this knowledge with a wider audience.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22jaikishan-patel-G1r9ySGtdWQ-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22jaikishan-patel-G1r9ySGtdWQ-unsplash_feature.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22jaikishan-patel-G1r9ySGtdWQ-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Where%20did%20it%20go%20wrong?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22jaikishan-patel-G1r9ySGtdWQ-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22jaikishan-patel-G1r9ySGtdWQ-unsplash_feature.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22jaikishan-patel-G1r9ySGtdWQ-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Where%20did%20it%20go%20wrong?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Tennants Fine Chemicals</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/client-profile/tennants-fine-chemicals" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tennants Fine Chemicals" /><published>2021-02-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/client-profile/tennants-fine-chemicals</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/client-profile/tennants-fine-chemicals">&lt;p&gt;Tennants Fine Chemicals Ltd supplies a global customer base with around 24,000 tonnes of chemicals a year from Leek, Staffordshire, plus seven other sites across the UK, Americas, Europe, and China. It is the UK’s leading producer of acetate esters and aroma chemicals; its products are used in cosmetics, metalworking fluids, paper, plastics, oilfield exploration, pharmaceuticals and other applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our processes are largely but not fully automated,” says Phil Malpas BEng (Hons), Electrical Controls and Instrumentation Engineer with Tennants. “Some plants are more automated than others. We have a centralised &lt;a href=&quot;/latest/control-system-types&quot; title=&quot;Distributed Control System&quot;&gt;DCS&lt;/a&gt; and separate &lt;a href=&quot;/latest/control-system-types&quot; title=&quot;Supervisory Control And Data Acquisition&quot;&gt;SCADA&lt;/a&gt; system.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;aligning-automated-and-manual-systems&quot;&gt;Aligning automated and manual systems&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DCS and SCADA are not always found in the same production environment. Here, the DCS is process-oriented, tightly controlling each step of an operation. While the SCADA is focused on acquisition and collation of the data operations personnel use to make decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When we run batch sequencing, for example, we can make the systems pretty automated. The chemicals will run through a system on their own, with limited operator input,” Phil says. “We use the DCS to ensure the system is being controlled or processes within the normal design operating window. A vessel’s pressure might be between 0 - 1 bar, for example; if you have over pressure, you might have a data concern. Where we have a pressure transmitter and monitor, the basic logic system will provide an alert to a “door open” event, for example.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;/latest/control-system-types&quot; title=&quot;Programmable Logic Controller&quot;&gt;PLC&lt;/a&gt; is used to sequence control in a certain order and to maintain it in a safe way. Automation of data input reduces the risk of human error and helps prevent hazardous issues arising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;partners-in-time&quot;&gt;Partners in time&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Op-tec Systems has played an important role in the process of automation and upgrade at Tennants for nearly 20 years. It has helped the company to upgrade its hardware and software to the latest versions, clean up and document signal databases and system architecture. All of which has helped resolve several issues of monitoring and management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have installed new thermal, process and remote controllers. It has enabled improved visibility of the entire plant,” says Chemical Engineer Martin Higgs, based at the company’s Staffordshire facility. “Op-tec were instrumental in helping us to diagnose problems and create fixes. Since then, everything has been working fine.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-long-term-partnership&quot;&gt;A long-term partnership&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An important further improvement was the installation of a remote control system in a hazardous area at Tennants several years ago, also implemented by Op-tec.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Richard Banyard of Op-tec is an independent expert and has assisted with developing our system and maintaining the backroom DCS, providing technical assistance and support,” Phil explains. “He has also been assisting us with aspects of control such as cyber security.” And now Tennants has automated its processes further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We moved away from the manual intervention and operation of valves and pumps and put their operation onto the DCS, a huge step forward for us,” says Martin Higgs. “This meant that the plant could be controlled mostly from the control room. A few years ago, we converted two of our oldest plants and put them onto the DCS as well. In terms of efficiency, this is a major benefit.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Op-tec has also helped train Martin and colleagues to become more self-sufficient, and understand then resolve control system issues. In the future, Op-tec will support with system upgrades and extending automation further. The process of doing so will, inevitably, raise some issues. Manufacturers like Tennants appreciate improvement can be disruptive; examining and changing long-established practices can be uncomfortable but they are necessary in order to retain or regain competitiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key to a successful transformation is to have a partner who understands what has already been achieved and what is being sought, and can help to map, plan and guide the company on the journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Download a PDF copy of this article &lt;a href=&quot;https://op-tec.co.uk/downloads/Tennants_Fine_Chemiclas_&amp;amp;_Op-tec_Systems_-_Partners_in_Time.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;u&gt;here&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Projects</name><email>projects@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="client-profile" /><summary type="html">Tennants Fine Chemicals Ltd supplies a global customer base with around 24,000 tonnes of chemicals a year from Leek, Staffordshire, plus seven other sites across the UK, Americas, Europe, and China. It is the UK’s leading producer of acetate esters and aroma chemicals; its products are used in cosmetics, metalworking fluids, paper, plastics, oilfield exploration, pharmaceuticals and other applications.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22aron-visuals-BXOXnQ26B7o-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22aron-visuals-BXOXnQ26B7o-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Where%20did%20it%20go%20wrong?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22aron-visuals-BXOXnQ26B7o-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22aron-visuals-BXOXnQ26B7o-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Where%20did%20it%20go%20wrong?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Don’t know where to start? Try the basics</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/cyber-security-basics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Don’t know where to start? Try the basics" /><published>2021-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/cyber-security-basics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/cyber-security-basics">&lt;p&gt;Often in life, getting the simple things right is key to success. For example, when we're feeling overworked, overcommitted and overwhelmed it can be hard to prioritise things like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;tab&quot;&gt; - Eating well&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;tab&quot;&gt; - Being active &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;tab&quot;&gt; - Sleeping enough&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when we focus on and prioritise the basics it increases our resilience and allows us to put everything else into perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same is true for cyber security. One of the best ways to make your systems resilient to attack is to have comprehensive backups and a regularly tested incident response plan. Unlike high-tech solutions, these work every time, for all types of breach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know.... writing and testing procedures is not as exciting as buying new technology. But I assure you it's far more cost-effective, even if you pay someone else to manage the process for you. Your systems and organisation will be more resilient as a result, and less dependent on third parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Would you benefit from focusing more on the basics?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get in touch if you'd like to speak with one of the team about how we can help you establish processes for backup, restore and disaster recovery:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fas fa-phone-alt&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;abbr title=&quot;Phone&quot;&gt;&lt;/abbr&gt; &amp;nbsp; &lt;a href=&quot;tel:00441616604293&quot; id=&quot;number&quot;&gt;+44 161 660 4293&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;                 
&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fas fa-envelope&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;abbr title=&quot;Email&quot;&gt;&lt;/abbr&gt; &amp;nbsp; &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:projects@op-tec.co.uk?subject=Support%20for%20800xA&quot;&gt;projects&amp;#64;op-tec.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Richard Banyard</name><email>richard.banyard@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><summary type="html">Often in life, getting the simple things right is key to success. For example, when we're feeling overworked, overcommitted and overwhelmed it can be hard to prioritise things like: - Eating well - Being active - Sleeping enough But when we focus on and prioritise the basics it increases our resilience and allows us to put everything else into perspective. The same is true for cyber security. One of the best ways to make your systems resilient to attack is to have comprehensive backups and a regularly tested incident response plan. Unlike high-tech solutions, these work every time, for all types of breach. I know.... writing and testing procedures is not as exciting as buying new technology. But I assure you it's far more cost-effective, even if you pay someone else to manage the process for you. Your systems and organisation will be more resilient as a result, and less dependent on third parties. Would you benefit from focusing more on the basics? Get in touch if you'd like to speak with one of the team about how we can help you establish processes for backup, restore and disaster recovery: &amp;nbsp; +44 161 660 4293 &amp;nbsp; projects&amp;#64;op-tec.co.uk</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-digital-buggu-311269.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22pexels-digital-buggu-311269_feature.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-digital-buggu-311269.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Could%20it%20pay%20to%20concentrate%20on%20the%20basics?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-digital-buggu-311269.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22pexels-digital-buggu-311269_feature.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-digital-buggu-311269.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Could%20it%20pay%20to%20concentrate%20on%20the%20basics?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Support available for ABB System 800xA</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/800xA" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Support available for ABB System 800xA" /><published>2020-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/800xA</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/800xA">&lt;p&gt;800xA is the world's leading* distributed control system (DCS). However its power and flexibility come with a cost. It's not known as the easiest system to work with - making it hard to find quality independent support, ensure updates and backups are managed correctly, and the configuration keeps pace with changes to plant and operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're looking for help with 800xA you may be experiencing one or more of these challenges:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Routine maintenance and updates&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;
  If left too long it can take days rather than minutes to recover from system failures or security incidents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Changes and modifications&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt; Out of date control systems aren't fit for purpose, leading people to work around, rather than benefit from them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Integrating 3rd party equipment&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt; Crucial to capture, store and analyse valuable process data but often seen as a nice to have, then never done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Adding extra features and functions&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt; Your sophisticated DCS isn't delivering the benefits promised thanks to constraints during the initial project. It now feels too hard or too expensive to add extra functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Op-tec's engineers have a wealth of experience working with 800xA and offer services which complement software support you may already be getting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get in touch if you'd like to learn more about how we can help reduce the cost of owning this incredibly powerful technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fas fa-phone-alt&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;abbr title=&quot;Phone&quot;&gt;&lt;/abbr&gt; &amp;nbsp; &lt;a href=&quot;tel:00441616604293&quot; id=&quot;number&quot;&gt;+44 161 660 4293&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;                 
&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fas fa-envelope&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;abbr title=&quot;Email&quot;&gt;&lt;/abbr&gt; &amp;nbsp; &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:projects@op-tec.co.uk?subject=Support%20for%20800xA&quot;&gt;projects&amp;#64;op-tec.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* 800xA is the world's number one DCS based on global market share. This is based on annual reports by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.arcweb.com/&quot;&gt;ARC Advisory Group&lt;/a&gt; which for the last 20 years have found 800xA to be the most common DCS. ABB's history of acquisitions has gone a long way to securing this accolade. Many of these installations will have been originally supplied by one of the companies ABB has bought over the years:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Taylor&lt;/b&gt; &lt;small&gt;founded 1851, acquired by Combustion Engineering in 1983&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;b&gt;Bailey Controls&lt;/b&gt; &lt;small&gt;founded 1916, became part of Elsag Bailey Process Automation in 1989&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;b&gt;Combustion Engineering&lt;/b&gt; &lt;small&gt;merger of Grieve Grate and American Stoker in 1912, acquired 1990&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;b&gt;Fischer &amp; Porter&lt;/b&gt; &lt;small&gt;founded 1937, acquired by Elsag Bailey Process Automation in 1994&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;b&gt;Elsag Bailey Process Automation&lt;/b&gt; &lt;small&gt;merger of Bailey Controls and Elsag Group in 1989, acquired 1998&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;b&gt;Alfa Laval Automation&lt;/b&gt; &lt;small&gt;merger of SattControl and Alfa Laval in 1986, acquired 1998&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  
  
  
  


&lt;script type=&quot;application/ld+json&quot;&gt;{&quot;@context&quot;: &quot;https://schema.org&quot;,&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;FAQPage&quot;,&quot;mainEntity&quot;: 
[
{&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Question&quot;,&quot;name&quot;: &quot;What does ABB stand for?&quot;,&quot;acceptedAnswer&quot;: {&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Answer&quot;,&quot;text&quot;: &quot;Asea Brown Boveri.&quot;
}},
{&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Question&quot;,&quot;name&quot;: &quot;When did ABB first release 800xA?&quot;,&quot;acceptedAnswer&quot;: {&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Answer&quot;,&quot;text&quot;: &quot;ABB launched System 800xA in 2004.&quot;
}},
{&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Question&quot;,&quot;name&quot;: &quot;What's the latest version of 800xA?&quot;,&quot;acceptedAnswer&quot;: {&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Answer&quot;,&quot;text&quot;: &quot;The latest release of System 800xA (as of Dec 2020) is version 6.1.&quot;
}},            
{&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Question&quot;,&quot;name&quot;: &quot;What does 800xA stand for?&quot;,&quot;acceptedAnswer&quot;: {&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Answer&quot;,&quot;text&quot;: &quot;The system forms part of ABB's '800' product line, ‘xA’ stands for Extended Automation.&quot;
}},            
{&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Question&quot;,&quot;name&quot;: &quot;Is 800xA really 'the worlds number one' distributed control system?&quot;,&quot;acceptedAnswer&quot;: {&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Answer&quot;,&quot;text&quot;: &quot;This title, often quoted in ABB's marketing material, is based on research by the ARC Advisory Group. ARC have found 800xA to be the distributed control system (DCS) with largest global market share for the last 20 years.&quot;
}}]
}&lt;/script&gt;</content><author><name>Projects</name><email>projects@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="knowledge" /><summary type="html">800xA is the world's leading* distributed control system (DCS). However its power and flexibility come with a cost. It's not known as the easiest system to work with - making it hard to find quality independent support, ensure updates and backups are managed correctly, and the configuration keeps pace with changes to plant and operations. If you're looking for help with 800xA you may be experiencing one or more of these challenges: Routine maintenance and updates If left too long it can take days rather than minutes to recover from system failures or security incidents. Changes and modifications Out of date control systems aren't fit for purpose, leading people to work around, rather than benefit from them. Integrating 3rd party equipment Crucial to capture, store and analyse valuable process data but often seen as a nice to have, then never done. Adding extra features and functions Your sophisticated DCS isn't delivering the benefits promised thanks to constraints during the initial project. It now feels too hard or too expensive to add extra functions. Op-tec's engineers have a wealth of experience working with 800xA and offer services which complement software support you may already be getting. Get in touch if you'd like to learn more about how we can help reduce the cost of owning this incredibly powerful technology. &amp;nbsp; +44 161 660 4293 &amp;nbsp; projects&amp;#64;op-tec.co.uk * 800xA is the world's number one DCS based on global market share. This is based on annual reports by the ARC Advisory Group which for the last 20 years have found 800xA to be the most common DCS. ABB's history of acquisitions has gone a long way to securing this accolade. Many of these installations will have been originally supplied by one of the companies ABB has bought over the years: Taylor founded 1851, acquired by Combustion Engineering in 1983 Bailey Controls founded 1916, became part of Elsag Bailey Process Automation in 1989 Combustion Engineering merger of Grieve Grate and American Stoker in 1912, acquired 1990 Fischer &amp; Porter founded 1937, acquired by Elsag Bailey Process Automation in 1994 Elsag Bailey Process Automation merger of Bailey Controls and Elsag Group in 1989, acquired 1998 Alfa Laval Automation merger of SattControl and Alfa Laval in 1986, acquired 1998</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22engineers-using-simulator-3862149.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22engineers-using-simulator-3862149.jpg%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22engineers-using-simulator-3862149.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22engineers-using-simulator-3862149.jpg%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Using data to inform maintenance</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/using-data-to-inform-maintenance" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Using data to inform maintenance" /><published>2020-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/using-data-to-inform-maintenance</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/using-data-to-inform-maintenance">&lt;p&gt;How you use data analysis to inform maintenance activity can have a huge impact on the efficiency of your operations. It may never be possible to eliminate the risk of an unplanned shutdown entirely, but smart use of plant data can significantly reduce it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re sick of praying for things to keep working until the end of the day / week / month / year, keep reading!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are simple explanations of common maintenance approaches. If you’re new to the concept of data-informed maintenance, know there are companies out there already pushing far beyond these techniques. For example, using machine learning to identify external factors such as weather patterns or employee behaviour to better inform predictions. Or allowing their systems to automatically order spare parts and schedule preventative work before human operators have the chance to notice anything’s up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most likely you’ll say to yourself “we already do this” as you read through. If so, ask whether your existing processes are as effective as they could be. We see people manually undertaking this work &lt;strong&gt;a lot&lt;/strong&gt;, storing records on paper or retrieving it from ‘offline’ equipment only to import it into another system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So read on, then ask: ‘Could my organisation improve it’s maintenance regimes?’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;corrective-maintenance&quot;&gt;Corrective maintenance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wait until something breaks, then take action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“If it ain’t broke, don’t fix it”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it requires doing nothing this is often seen as the most cost-effective option. Only true if the cost of downtime, in-house expertise, and spare parts is less than those associated with a data-driven approach if this is the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If equipment in question is critical to operations rapid repair or replacement will be necessary to minimise disruption. Also referred to as reactive maintenance. This approach risks significant costs should catastrophic failure occur, where repair or replacement is not possible within a defined timeframe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No data is needed for this approach. Information available is often used to diagnose the cause of failures after the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;e.g. replacing a blown bulb&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;preventive-maintenance&quot;&gt;Preventive maintenance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intervene before failure becomes likely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“When was the cambelt last changed?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maintenance activities are performed before they’re required; typically at predetermined intervals based on historical records or manufacturer recommendations. Sometimes referred to as ‘proactive maintenance’ this technique allows work to be carried out during planned shutdowns minimising disruption. Taking this approach means performing maintenance before it’s needed, so the assumption is the resource needed to do this if cheaper than implementing a more data-driven approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This technique can be improved over time by using measurement, analysis and periodic testing to better inform service intervals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;e.g. changing car engine oil every 10,000 miles&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;risk-based-maintenance&quot;&gt;Risk-based maintenance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the impact into account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Get that boiler serviced before winter”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The effect a failure will have on operations and it’s likelihood is used to allocate available resource efficiently. The condition of assets will also be monitored to ensure changing risks, as equipment and machinery ages, is taken into account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quantity and quality of data used can vary widely, from the objective analysis of an employee to automated anaylsis of assets over time. It may also be useful to consider factors other than just equipment condition, such as market demand or stock levels.  Information gathered can also inform the schedule for replacing or upgrading equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;e.g. waiting until a shutdown to install software updates&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;condition-based-maintenance&quot;&gt;Condition-based maintenance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monitor ‘health’ for warning signs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“No signs of wear…“&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maintenance work is informed through performance monitoring of equipment. Typically, key parameters are recorded over time, and trends which indicate pending failure identified. Manual inspection during outages can also be used to determine when work needs to be carried out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Automated systems record device parameters over time. Maintenance is required when values deviate from ‘normal’ indicating the probability of a failure has increased to an unacceptable level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;e.g. a motor drawing more current than usual&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;predictive-maintenance&quot;&gt;Predictive maintenance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specific thresholds for action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“What does this warning light mean?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People are automatically alerted when specific scenarios are detected. The characteristics and failure modes of an asset will be known, so when partnered with condition monitoring pending failure can be detected and people warned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on how sophisticated a piece of equipment is, this may be a single error or warning light or a detailed fault code which accurately indentifies the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;e.g. car running in “limp mode” until it’s taken to the garage&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prescriptive-maintenance&quot;&gt;Prescriptive maintenance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recommended action provided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The freezer says it needs defrosting”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Users receive specific recommended actions to prevent failure. So rather than a description of the problem, they are given information about the action they need to take to avoid a failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No time is needed to fault-find or diagnose problems, as the piece of equipment states exacty what is required to address the situation. This also reduces the skill and expertise personnel need to be able to operate and maintain the asset. Original Equipment Manufacturers (OEMs) may provide this functionality for ‘user serviceable’ equipment, but ensure that more complicated or costly fixes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;e.g. dashboard: check tyre pressures&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reliability-centered-maintenance&quot;&gt;Reliability-centered maintenance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Identifying the best maintenance approach for each asset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“We can’t suffer a failure”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Past breakdowns are analysed to identify the best maintenance approach for each item of equipment, based on it’s historic and/or anticipated reliability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this instance an assets performance and reliability inform the most appropriate maintenance regime. New equipment will be maintained largely in line with the manufacturers recommendations. Then more weight given to historical records of condition and failure rate as the equipment ages. Like risk-based maintenance, when implemented properly this method is labour intensive, requiring knowledge of an assets’ failure modes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;e.g. establishing the safe minimum level of maintenance for an aircraft&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Projects</name><email>projects@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="knowledge" /><summary type="html">How you use data analysis to inform maintenance activity can have a huge impact on the efficiency of your operations. It may never be possible to eliminate the risk of an unplanned shutdown entirely, but smart use of plant data can significantly reduce it.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22praying-man-small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22praying-man.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22praying-man-small.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Not%20the%20most%20effective%20maintenance%20regime%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22praying-man-small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22praying-man.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22praying-man-small.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Not%20the%20most%20effective%20maintenance%20regime%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>