<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-05-25T15:48:29+01:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/atom.xml</id><title type="html">Op-tec Systems</title><subtitle>Independent automation consultant</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Hit that ‘Save’ button</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/hit-that-save-button" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hit that ‘Save’ button" /><published>2023-05-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-05-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/hit-that-save-button</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/hit-that-save-button">&lt;p&gt;We all fall short of this in some manner. I would love to take you down memory lane to bring your thought closer to the adverse effect of not saving your work.  You remember the good old days when Microsoft Office applications were without the auto-save feature, right? Now say you are just about finishing a thirty-page masterpiece document, feeling happy with yourself, so you decide to step into the kitchen to heat some water and make a cuppa tea. Your three-year-old decides to innocently help you with typing and, in doing so, magically turns off your PC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you step back in to finish your typing, and you are welcomed with a cute smile and a “Daddy/Mummy, I helped you finish the typing and turned off your PC”. I don’t know about most of you, but chains of thoughts would undoubtedly go through my mind. I will anxiously consider whether I should be happy with the gesture or sad because I may not have “Hit That Save Button”. Amongst my thought will be imagining trying to recreate my masterpiece to the standard it was or trying to imagine the cost of re-writing my masterpiece. A price which may range from forfeiting the planned time to spend with friends, go on a vacation, possible financial price or even as simple as forfeiting the cuppa tea you had planned to drink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we know, all that mishaps can be avoided by following the process of saving your work by hitting the save button. A process Microsoft has deemed fit to automate, Hoorah! Now our kids can break our PCs, right? Nah, I don’t think so too.  Undoubtedly, Microsoft did a great job ensuring our work is saved automatically on their application. However, it is our sole responsibility to ensure our processes are in place to save our work locally and securely on an external storage medium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enough of my blabbing about Microsoft, let us bring it down to our niche. As an industrial staff, it is crucial to ensure you have processes in place to “Hit that Save button” for your firm. No, I am not just talking about a document-saving process, I am also talking about saving the “money-making” process. Every business has a process for making money. Be it by installing the latest “whizzy” tech to fast-track production or employing the “brightest” personnel. In trying to etch towards that juicy ROI you so deserve, the main question remains, &lt;strong&gt;“Have you taken time to ensure the cost you incur in installing super tech or hiring a great mind has a process to hit the save button automatically?”&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer this and more, you will most likely need a Digital Benchmark Analysis. The report will disclose those hidden weak spots in your money-making process and ensure that your technological and human work is automatically saved, just like our very own Microsoft Word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, there are tons of Digital Benchmark analyzing software, at Op-tec Systems we have worked with most industries and understand the work and cost you put in. By doing so, we decided you should not incur more expenses as you seek your truth. Feel free to Generate Your &lt;a href=&quot;/digital-benchmark&quot;&gt;Free Digital Benchmark Report&lt;/a&gt; and ensure that ROI is securely within your grasp.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Obiefuna Obidike</name><email>obiefuna.obidike@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><summary type="html">We all fall short of this in some manner. I would love to take you down memory lane to bring your thought closer to the adverse effect of not saving your work. You remember the good old days when Microsoft Office applications were without the auto-save feature, right? Now say you are just about finishing a thirty-page masterpiece document, feeling happy with yourself, so you decide to step into the kitchen to heat some water and make a cuppa tea. Your three-year-old decides to innocently help you with typing and, in doing so, magically turns off your PC.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22vincent-botta-bv_rJXpNU9I-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22vincent-botta-bv_rJXpNU9I-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22vincent-botta-bv_rJXpNU9I-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Does%20your%20business%20do%20unnecessary%20rework?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22vincent-botta-bv_rJXpNU9I-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22vincent-botta-bv_rJXpNU9I-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22vincent-botta-bv_rJXpNU9I-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Does%20your%20business%20do%20unnecessary%20rework?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The benefits of automation in workplace safety</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/benefits-of-automation-technology-in-workplace-safety" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The benefits of automation in workplace safety" /><published>2023-03-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/benefits-of-automation-technology-in-workplace-safety</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/benefits-of-automation-technology-in-workplace-safety">&lt;p&gt;In today’s workplace, automation technology is becoming more prevalent. Workplace accidents can have a significant negative impact on a business, ranging from low staff morale to huge reputational and financial costs. Organisations can use automation to reduce workplace accidents alongside realising productivity increases. This article will outline how automation can be a valuable tool for reducing the likelihood and consequences of industrial accidents while improving efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;hierarchy-of-controls&quot;&gt;Hierarchy of Controls&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is common practice for Health &amp;amp; Safety managers to use the hierarchy of controls to mitigate risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/HierarchyOfControls.png&quot; alt=&quot;Hierarchy of controls&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the hierarchy of control as a risk management framework helps identify the most effective and reliable methods of risk mitigation. This hierarchical structure starts with the elimination of the hazard and progresses downward to using personal protective equipment (PPE) as a last resort. While elimination and substitution are the most challenging options to implement into an existing process, automation kicks in as a cost-effective engineering control measure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several ways in which automation technology can be used to mitigate workplace risks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Physically distancing employees from hazards&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Automation makes remote work possible as it can physically distance workers from hazards. The use of automation helps in completing potentially dangerous jobs which would otherwise be done by workers - limiting human exposure to hazardous enviroments or situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robots might be operated to handle dangerous materials in an industrial environment, lowering the risk of worker exposure. Robotic welders, for instance keep workers away from sparks, fumes, and other potential welding risks while being supervised by skilled workers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Automation technology can also be applied to remotely monitor and control processes, enabling employees to work at a safe distance. By limiting exposure to hazards, the likelihood and severity of accidents is eventually reduced, resulting in a safe and healthy work environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automating repetitive tasks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By automating repetitive tasks businesses increase workplace safety and boost productivity as a result. Numerous manual jobs, like working on an assembly line or entering data, can be monotonous and exhausting, and this increases the likelihood of mistakes and accidents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By taking over certain tasks, automation technologies can assist to alleviate these repetitive tasks and free up workers to engage on other complex jobs. Since automated systems are frequently more capable of working quickly and accurately than humans, this can also help to increase the overall effectiveness of the work process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reducing employee fatigue&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accidents may occur as a result of worker errors. Errors might occur as a result of miscommunication, confusion but also exhaustion. By taking over jobs that are physically demanding or need continuous attention for extended periods of time, automation technology has the potential to alleviate employee tiredness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Continuous process monitoring&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Automated systems can continuously produce data and monitor process in real-time. This makes it possible for such systems to respond to emergencies far more promptly than humans. Automated systems can stop accidents and equipment damage by shutting down machinery or warning staff before a potentially dangerous situation worsens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Safety relays can be used to connect sensors and interlocks to cut off power to motors and actuators preventing a possibly hazardous event. An example would be automatic shutting down of boilers and turbines in thermal power plants should the amount of water in the steam drum exceed a safe level. This shutdown safeguards both the equipment from catastrophic damage and workers from potential harm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nevertheless, a word of caution - while automation helps in mitigating existing risks, it can create new unanticipated hazards. Therefore, it is crucial to conduct a fresh risk assessment exercise in order to put in place safety measures so as to manage the impact of the new risks.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To sum up, automation technology can drastically lower the risk of accidents, making the workplace safer while increasing uptime and productivity. With the advent of AI and IoT into the workplace, the process can become even more effective and efficient. By strategically integrating automation technologies, businesses can create a safer and more productive work environment for their employees, benefiting the organisation and its workers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Pravesh Teckmun</name><email>teckmun@icloud.com</email></author><category term="knowledge" /><category term="food&amp;drink" /><category term="textiles" /><category term="power" /><category term="chemicals" /><summary type="html">In today’s workplace, automation technology is becoming more prevalent. Workplace accidents can have a significant negative impact on a business, ranging from low staff morale to huge reputational and financial costs. Organisations can use automation to reduce workplace accidents alongside realising productivity increases. This article will outline how automation can be a valuable tool for reducing the likelihood and consequences of industrial accidents while improving efficiency.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22possessed-photography-dRMQiAubdws-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22possessed-photography-dRMQiAubdws-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22possessed-photography-dRMQiAubdws-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Robots%20can%20improve%20safety%20as%20well%20as%20productivity%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22possessed-photography-dRMQiAubdws-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22possessed-photography-dRMQiAubdws-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22possessed-photography-dRMQiAubdws-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Robots%20can%20improve%20safety%20as%20well%20as%20productivity%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">SCADA</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/SCADA" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SCADA" /><published>2023-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/SCADA</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/SCADA">&lt;p&gt;SCADA systems are used to collect process data, display plant status information, and provide users with control over automated processes. SCADA systems are highly configurable, able to provide a wide variety of monitoring and control functions to the diverse roles which make up an operational workforce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;key-technologies&quot;&gt;Key Technologies&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SCADA systems make use of proprietary database technology and/or open platforms such as SQL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commonly the user interface often referred to as the HMI (Human Machine Interface) comprises a screen hierarchy where the plant is split into logical areas. For example, a tank farm feeding a chemicals manufacturing facility would be displayed on one screen and the process vessel reactors on other screens while common services and utilities on further screens. For a chemical plant each screen resembles a PI&amp;amp;D (Piping and Instrumentation Diagram) where instruments, motors and valves etc are also included.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/SCADA.png&quot; alt=&quot;System overview - SCADA&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To collect data from plant-level Operational Technology (OT) SCADA systems make use of open industrialised protocols like OPC and MQTT, as well as being compatible with proprietary communications utilised by specialised or legacy systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Process information is made available to Information Technology (IT) via application programming interfaces, accessed using methods such as SQL, OData and ODBC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;benefits&quot;&gt;Benefits&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Visualisation and Control&lt;/strong&gt; – Access to real-time plant conditions via fixed operator displays and mobile devices. Remote control and optimisation of automated processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reporting&lt;/strong&gt; – Scheduled and event driven reports deliver time-sensitive information to users via email, text message or device notifications. Alert operations staff to process conditions, maintenance staff to potential equipment failures and keep management up-to-date on operational performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Historian&lt;/strong&gt; – Plant data is able to be both recorded and archived using SCADA systems. In this respect the SCADA system acts as a data repository with search and analysis features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information follow the link below to the Services section of our website where you can learn more about the help we can offer on this topic and many others relating to industrial process and manufacturing automation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/services&quot;&gt;https://op-tec.co.uk/services&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Roger Halliwell</name><email>roger.halliwell@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="knowledge" /><category term="tech-note" /><category term="food&amp;drink" /><category term="textiles" /><category term="power" /><category term="chemicals" /><summary type="html">SCADA systems are used to collect process data, display plant status information, and provide users with control over automated processes. SCADA systems are highly configurable, able to provide a wide variety of monitoring and control functions to the diverse roles which make up an operational workforce.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22iStock-1422487368-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22iStock-1422487368-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22iStock-1422487368.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22SCADA%20system%20being%20used%20for%20analysis%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22iStock-1422487368-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22iStock-1422487368-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22iStock-1422487368.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22SCADA%20system%20being%20used%20for%20analysis%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Unified Namespace</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/unified-namespace" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unified Namespace" /><published>2023-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/unified-namespace</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/unified-namespace">&lt;p&gt;A unified namespace is intended to be the ‘single source of truth’ for an organisation’s production data and is a key component of network architectures which make the most of the Industry 4.0 concept. Manufacturers who implement a unified namespace build networks in a hub and spoke layout providing all major systems a direct link to the unified namespace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;key-technologies&quot;&gt;Key Technologies&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unified namespace, or central repository, is the hub of an organisation’s networks. It features details of every data point in the organisation and all information passses through it. Software providing this service is commonly referred to as a ‘data broker’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/unified-namespace.png&quot; alt=&quot;Network overview - unified namespace&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Network architectures which utilise a unified namespace don’t conform to the traditional Purdue Enterprise Reference Architecture, the standard model for company networks since the 1990’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success of this approach relies on lighteight ‘report by exception’ communication protocols (e.g. MQTT). This ensures the data broker(s) which making up the unified namespace can handle the huge amount of data flowing through them and minimises loading on ‘satellite’ systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;benefits&quot;&gt;Benefits&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reduced system and network complexity&lt;/strong&gt; – Maximum of 2 connections between any two systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scalable architecture which supports digitalisation&lt;/strong&gt;  – Minimises cost of future modification, expansion or integration. Reduces cost of experimentation, proof of concepts and improvements projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lower integration costs&lt;/strong&gt; – Addition of new systems or data points simplied with changes only required to a single connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supports OT/IT convergence&lt;/strong&gt; – Having a centralised and shared resource necessitates teams responsible for operational and information technology to work effectively together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Removes need for system knowledge&lt;/strong&gt; – Object-orientated/contextualised approach allows creation of digital twins. Enables people with little or even no knowledge of operational technology will be able to navigate and use data from the UNS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Standard presentation for data from different providers&lt;/strong&gt; – Plant or equipment with the same functions from different suppliers can be presented in a uniform and consistent manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information follow the link below to the Services section of our website where you can learn more about the help we can offer on this topic and many others relating to industrial process and manufacturing automation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/services&quot;&gt;https://op-tec.co.uk/services&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Richard Banyard</name><email>richard.banyard@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="knowledge" /><category term="tech-note" /><category term="food&amp;drink" /><category term="textiles" /><category term="power" /><category term="chemicals" /><summary type="html">A unified namespace is intended to be the ‘single source of truth’ for an organisation’s production data and is a key component of network architectures which make the most of the Industry 4.0 concept. Manufacturers who implement a unified namespace build networks in a hub and spoke layout providing all major systems a direct link to the unified namespace.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22clint-mckoy-9oYHSMxt7tg-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22clint-mckoy-9oYHSMxt7tg-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22clint-mckoy-9oYHSMxt7tg-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Have%20you%20moved%20to%20a%20hub%20and%20spoke%20architecture?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22clint-mckoy-9oYHSMxt7tg-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22clint-mckoy-9oYHSMxt7tg-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22clint-mckoy-9oYHSMxt7tg-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Have%20you%20moved%20to%20a%20hub%20and%20spoke%20architecture?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Will it work?</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/will-it-work" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Will it work?" /><published>2022-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/will-it-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/will-it-work">&lt;p&gt;I went to visit Sally down at Sale the other day, we had a good conversation over a “cuppa tea”. Just as I was about to set up and leave Sally informed me she had a bit of an engineering task she believed I would be able to fix. Sure, I affirmed because I am always down for a challenge, only for her to inform me her shower soap holder had broken, and she had a new part to fix it. However, she didn’t know how to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was expecting a challenging task. Nevertheless, I was challenged as it turns out she had ordered a very beautiful soap holder, but the fitting system was made for shower poles with a 25mm pole diameter and hers was 22mm. The challenge was explaining that while good, her solution wouldn’t work with the wrong parameters. I called two days later to check up, she had the right one and could fix it up herself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar events happen within our niche. A few days back, I went down south to a client site to commission equipment they had designed to dry their product quicker. My role was to ensure the equipment they had set up would perform the task efficiently. The equipment consisted of blowers blowing air through air knives and a chain conveyor system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supposed to be a straightforward task, right? That was my thought process until I interacted with the equipment. On my first run with the damp product, I realized parts of the product were dry and other parts were not. A simple solution adjusts the air knife position parameter to effectively dry the remaining part of the product. As simple as it sounds, it went from being simple to being manually demanding as the designers of the equipment had not created room for parameter adjustments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is we got the desired result after manually modifying the equipment. However, the equipment needs to be shipped back and modified to accommodate optimizable adjustment hence some cost on someone’s side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what do a non-fitting shower soap holder and non-adjustable drying equipment have to do with me you may wonder?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equipment in both cases didn’t meet expectations because crucial questions, were answered correctly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1) What is the problem we want to overcome?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2) What parameters directly affect the problem?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3) How does each parameter impact the problem?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost all of us are spot on with the first question. However, when it comes to the second and third, most of us are found wanting. Sally, my friend, was spot on with the first question. 
However, she didn’t understand the parameters that would be used to implement the solution (question 2) and couldn’t go further to answering question 3. With my friends down south, you can see that questions 1 and 2 were answered. However, question 3 was left out so the solution parameters couldn’t be modified to meet their expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In providing solutions for your project, you need to understand the parameters that &lt;strong&gt;Op&lt;/strong&gt;enly relate to your solution and the &lt;strong&gt;tec&lt;/strong&gt;nologies behind these parameters. That way you would be closer to implementing your solution as “plug and play”.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Obiefuna Obidike</name><email>obiefuna.obidike@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><category term="software" /><category term="food&amp;drink" /><category term="textiles" /><category term="chemicals" /><category term="power" /><summary type="html">I went to visit Sally down at Sale the other day, we had a good conversation over a “cuppa tea”. Just as I was about to set up and leave Sally informed me she had a bit of an engineering task she believed I would be able to fix. Sure, I affirmed because I am always down for a challenge, only for her to inform me her shower soap holder had broken, and she had a new part to fix it. However, she didn’t know how to.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22Will-it-work-thumb.png%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22Will-it-work-thumb.png%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22Will-it-work.png%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Oh%20really...?%20by%20BakaSchwarz%20on%20DeviantArt%20by%20Unknown%20Author,%20licensed%20under%20CC%20BY-NC-ND%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22Will-it-work-thumb.png%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22Will-it-work-thumb.png%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22Will-it-work.png%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Oh%20really...?%20by%20BakaSchwarz%20on%20DeviantArt%20by%20Unknown%20Author,%20licensed%20under%20CC%20BY-NC-ND%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Is Computer System Validation worth the paper it’s written on?</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/is-computer-validation-worth-the-paper-its-written-on" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is Computer System Validation worth the paper it’s written on?" /><published>2022-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/is-computer-validation-worth-the-paper-its-written-on</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/is-computer-validation-worth-the-paper-its-written-on">&lt;p&gt;Please forgive the pun but it’s a fair question. What is the value of validating your control system or process historian? Many industries don’t bother and leave it to the domain of the regulated manufacturers such as the Pharmaceuticals, Aerospace and Nuclear industries as it is often considered to be a very time consuming and expensive process which offers little in return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But could other industries such as food, textiles, paper, oil and gas etc benefit from this approach? I would say definitely!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s true to say that, initially at least, computer system validation will add work-load to a project while staff come to terms with the process. However, the benefits thereon are manyfold – not least that you will end up with a properly documented system built to the relevant standards which you can then use to fault find and diagnose faults or manufacturing issues and when upgrading or changing the system. The validation process also leaves a documentation chain newcomers can use to understand how the software system works so it can be effectively and efficiently supported and modified in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many times have you heard, &lt;em&gt;“I don’t know how it works – Joe wrote the software originally and he’s the only one who understands it”&lt;/em&gt;. Never helpful, especially if Joe left the company 18 months ago!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also has the benefit of making you think during the design process as validating a system does not only involve the prospective design of a computer system but also as to whether it will work by virtue of a comprehensive testing regime. In this sense it is often argued that both design and test processes should be run in parallel – in other words when you design a piece of software have you considered whether you can you test it? If the answer to this is no, then you will struggle to get the software to work in the first place! In fact if you can’t test it you can’t be sure it works!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is Computer System Validation? The text book definition is ‘the process of ensuring a software system meets specifications and requirements so it fulfils its intended purpose’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went to a computer system validation conference years ago and heard this definition for Computer System Validation, which I prefer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Say what you are going to do&lt;/strong&gt; – Write the relevant specifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do what you said you would do&lt;/strong&gt; – Build the system according to the specifications you’ve written.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prove you did what you said you would do&lt;/strong&gt; – Test the system according to the specifications you’ve written.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For help getting started with computer system validation I recommend taking a look at the ISPE’s (International Society of Pharmaceutical Engineering) excellent publication called GAMP5 (Good Automated Manufacturing Practice) which explains this recognised methodology for computer system validation. It also provides a comprehensive list of documentation type templates (e.g. URS, FDS etc).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The website is: &lt;a href=&quot;https://ispe.org/publications/guidance-documents&quot;&gt;ispe.org/publications/guidance-documents&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Roger Halliwell</name><email>roger.halliwell@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><category term="software" /><category term="food&amp;drink" /><category term="textiles" /><category term="chemicals" /><category term="power" /><summary type="html">Please forgive the pun but it’s a fair question. What is the value of validating your control system or process historian? Many industries don’t bother and leave it to the domain of the regulated manufacturers such as the Pharmaceuticals, Aerospace and Nuclear industries as it is often considered to be a very time consuming and expensive process which offers little in return.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22beatriz-perez-moya-XN4T2PVUUgk-unsplash_thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22beatriz-perez-moya-XN4T2PVUUgk-unsplash_thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22beatriz-perez-moya-XN4T2PVUUgk-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Documentation.%20Is%20it%20worth%20it?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22beatriz-perez-moya-XN4T2PVUUgk-unsplash_thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22beatriz-perez-moya-XN4T2PVUUgk-unsplash_thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22beatriz-perez-moya-XN4T2PVUUgk-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Documentation.%20Is%20it%20worth%20it?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What’s the diagnosis?</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/whats-the-diagnosis" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What’s the diagnosis?" /><published>2022-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/whats-the-diagnosis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/whats-the-diagnosis">&lt;p&gt;We have four cars in our household and three of them are more than 10 years old. They all have engine management lights showing. The trouble is, the engine management light doesn’t tell you what the actual fault is – it’s just a warning to tell you something’s up. To help understand the problem you need to interrogate the car’s control system, known as the ECU (Engine Control Unit) by reading the fault codes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowing I could buy a code scanner to help decipher the conditions behind these fault codes I bought one and began looking into the cause of the errors on cars which were otherwise running just fine!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the process I picked up a little of the jargon in the code scanner world. A few key terms follow, to demystify this area of vehicle ownership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OBD-II&lt;/strong&gt; - On Board Diagnostics 2. A standard pretty much all cars now follow as it was made mandatory for all cars manufactured in the US since 1996.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MIL&lt;/strong&gt; - Malfunction Indicator Lamp. The scary yellow light (or sometimes orange or red light depending on the severity of the fault) which appears on the dashboard as an engine symbol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DTC&lt;/strong&gt; - Diagnostic Trouble Code. Alphanumeric codes OBD-II scanners display once plugged in and connected to your vehicle. They are split into 4 categories (Power, Chassis, Body and User Network) followed by a number of digits further describing the fault (e.g. P0215).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s worth noting: although OBD-II is a standard it isn’t necessarily the end of the story. Many car manufacturers add functionality into their diagnostic systems in addition to the standard OBD-II facilities available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do you use an OBD-II Scanner? Simply plug it into the OBD connector, normally found somewhere behind the trim  on the driver’s side by the dashboard, and it should spring into life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My scanner is a very simple one (it cost me £36 from Amazon). It starts reading data immediately it is plugged into the car, presenting a menu from where I can interrogate the car’s status. Even the simplest scanners will enable you to read fault codes and reset them and also show live engine data such as engine speeds, mass air flow etc. More expensive units show graphs of live data too. The most expensive scanners allow you to manipulate the cars settings, termed bidirectional control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first tried the scanner on my daughter’s car, the photo below shows the code displayed. I quickly worked out why they are called “codes”! ‘Mass or Volume Air Flow A Circuit Range/Performance – Air Flow too Low’ didn’t really tell me exactly what was wrong. It did point us in the right direction though. On further examination the fault was found to be a blocked pipe which cost £26.00 to fix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/OBD-II_scanner_output.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Output from an OBD-II scanner&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expect you’re hoping for a punchline to this article. Well in my mind its what you can come to understand by using diagnostic systems and how they can save you money. It’s interesting to observe the motor industry providing advanced diagnostic systems to consumers, while many manufacturers supplying the very same industry remain reluctant to adopt similar technology. Systems such as &lt;a href=&quot;/latest/control-system-types&quot;&gt;SCADAs&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/knowledge/process-historians&quot;&gt;Process Historians&lt;/a&gt; can be used to diagnose faults and better understand how to run a plant at maximum efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my punchline (or moral to the story) is to advocate you implement a diagnosis system to drive (pun intended) process optimisation in your company. Get past measuring success by not breaking down and move to being able to predict failures and tune the performance of your equipment. Develop a diagnostic system which provides a clear visualisation of everything happening in your plant. Then alerts you when something needs attention and how to correct it - before it goes wrong!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Roger Halliwell</name><email>roger.halliwell@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><category term="software" /><category term="food&amp;drink" /><category term="textiles" /><category term="chemicals" /><category term="power" /><summary type="html">We have four cars in our household and three of them are more than 10 years old. They all have engine management lights showing. The trouble is, the engine management light doesn’t tell you what the actual fault is – it’s just a warning to tell you something’s up. To help understand the problem you need to interrogate the car’s control system, known as the ECU (Engine Control Unit) by reading the fault codes.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22c-joyful-heFTscwGDCA-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22c-joyful-heFTscwGDCA-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22c-joyful-heFTscwGDCA-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Do%20you%20know%20what%20you're%20looking%20for?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22c-joyful-heFTscwGDCA-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22c-joyful-heFTscwGDCA-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22c-joyful-heFTscwGDCA-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Do%20you%20know%20what%20you're%20looking%20for?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Give your manufacturing business an MOT</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/give-your-manufacturing-business-an-MOT" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Give your manufacturing business an MOT" /><published>2022-09-26T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-09-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/give-your-manufacturing-business-an-MOT</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/give-your-manufacturing-business-an-MOT">&lt;p&gt;It’s a statutory requirement that once your car is over 3 years old it be MOT’d every year. This ensures it is both safe and not hurling huge levels of emissions into the atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If only there was a mandate for businesses to carry out similar testing of their manufacturing processes. Not only from an emissions and safety point of view, but also from an efficiency standpoint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently visited a manufacturing facility here in the UK and was amazed at the levels of waste that could easily be overcome by deploying standard automation technology. We surveyed the site in terms of wasted energy, damaged product, manual operations and wasted time, finding and reporting many instances of waste. We also determined that for a small investment (under £50k) the payback period for improvements would be less than 13 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you may know waste is often categorised in Lean Manufacturing in terms of the following 7 categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1) Transport&lt;/strong&gt; - unnecessary transportation of goods before they reach the manufacturing facility&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2) Inventory&lt;/strong&gt; - where too high stock levels waste working capital&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3) Movement&lt;/strong&gt; - unnecessary movement of goods within the manufacturing facility&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4) Time&lt;/strong&gt; - delays waiting for partly finished goods or raw materials&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5) Defects&lt;/strong&gt; - goods being either thrown away or reworked due to quality issues&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6) Overprocessing&lt;/strong&gt; - goods worked for too long or produced at too high a specification&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7) Overproduction&lt;/strong&gt; - the manufacture of too many goods compared to demand&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d also like to add a further category: wasted talent – i.e., we often don’t get the most out of our staff either because they are overlooked, not inspired or not involved in the management side of the business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps if we spend a little time considering the above we could improve our businesses, make them more profitable, enjoyable to work in, kinder to the planet - and in this current economic climate - more sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Roger Halliwell</name><email>roger.halliwell@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><category term="software" /><category term="food&amp;drink" /><category term="textiles" /><category term="chemicals" /><summary type="html">It’s a statutory requirement that once your car is over 3 years old it be MOT’d every year. This ensures it is both safe and not hurling huge levels of emissions into the atmosphere.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22sten-rademaker-UZUzvJEvKnI-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22sten-rademaker-UZUzvJEvKnI-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22sten-rademaker-UZUzvJEvKnI-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Huge%20efficiency%20improvements%20are%20often%20available%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22sten-rademaker-UZUzvJEvKnI-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22sten-rademaker-UZUzvJEvKnI-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22sten-rademaker-UZUzvJEvKnI-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Huge%20efficiency%20improvements%20are%20often%20available%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Can you compete with your local coffee shop?</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/can-you-compete-with-your-local-coffee-shop" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can you compete with your local coffee shop?" /><published>2022-09-23T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-09-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/can-you-compete-with-your-local-coffee-shop</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/can-you-compete-with-your-local-coffee-shop">&lt;p&gt;There’s a good chance your local independent coffee shop employs technology far more advanced than that running your factory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can I say this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently discovered many espresso machines offer an abundance of monitoring, analytics and automation to local businesses who are keener than ever to increase their efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most cafés coffee is the bread winner. A reputation for great coffee attracts new customers and ensures they keep coming back. So brewing coffee (known as extraction in the espresso world) at an optimum yield and quality is vitally important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern espresso machines monitor production to make sure the perfect amount of coffee and the brew time are used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consistency of the ground coffee is a key variable. Coarser grounds allow water to pass through quicker than finer grounds which have a longer brew time. Knowing the perfect brewing time (say 27s, +/- 1s) machines can alert baristas to the need to adjust the grinder to produce a coarser or finer grade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look again at the image above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of espresso shots is monitored along with the performance of individual group heads so variability can be reduced. Daily counts of perfect brews Vs imperfect ones also provide a metric equivalent to the coffee machine’s OEE (&lt;a href=&quot;/tools/OEE-get-started&quot;&gt;Operational Equipment Effectiveness&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cafés also use EPOS (Electronic Point of Sale) systems to enable customers to undertake cashless transactions. These can connect to accounting and inventory management software enabling automated stock control based on the ingredients used for specific recipes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So next time you visit or pass a coffee shop consider whether your company could better employ technology to maximise yield and maintain high quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.croziersofbirkdale.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Croziers of Birkdale&lt;/a&gt; for giving me insight into their business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[Taken from our ‘breakfast email’ archive, sign up &lt;a href=&quot;/receive-emails&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Richard Banyard</name><email>richard.banyard@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><category term="software" /><category term="food&amp;drink" /><category term="textiles" /><category term="power" /><category term="chemicals" /><category term="oil&amp;gas" /><category term="pharmaceuticals" /><summary type="html">There’s a good chance your local independent coffee shop employs technology far more advanced than that running your factory.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22espresso-machine-dashboard_thumb.png%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22espresso-machine-dashboard_thumb.png%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22espresso-machine-dashboard.png%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Example%20report%20from%20a%20smart%20espresso%20machine%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22espresso-machine-dashboard_thumb.png%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22espresso-machine-dashboard_thumb.png%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22espresso-machine-dashboard.png%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Example%20report%20from%20a%20smart%20espresso%20machine%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How much process data should you collect?</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/how-much-process-data-should-you-collect" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How much process data should you collect?" /><published>2022-08-05T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-08-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/how-much-process-data-should-you-collect</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/how-much-process-data-should-you-collect">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Do we really need to collect so much data?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A question I get asked frequently. While discussing anything from PLCs to process historians - so many devices and machines are capable of logging historical data these days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re currently faced with the challenge of deciding how much operational data to collect: think about your car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dashboard should be clear, concise and not cluttered with unnecessary information. Everything needed to drive on a daily basis is available, data points you don’t need to worry about aren’t displayed. Maybe it looks something like the one above?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behind the dashboard embedded computers will be monitoring and recording a vast amount of data while you drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This proves useful for maintenance, servicing and when something goes wrong. Much time and money can be saved in the diagnosis of a problem if historical events and system generated messages are available which explain what happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breakdowns and expensive repairs can also be avoided by monitoring component characteristics which indicate wear before consumable parts fail. You will then be prompted to take action avoiding damage to more expensive components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now apply this thinking to your plant or factory by classifying your data:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;KPIs&lt;/strong&gt; - What are your key performance indicators? Which data points are needed to calculate them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Daily operation&lt;/strong&gt; - Information operational staff need to do their job, monitor performance and identify opportunities for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maintenance&lt;/strong&gt; - Data, when analysed through time, provides information on the performance and condition of your assets and equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diagnostics&lt;/strong&gt; - Error and warning messages, process conditions, operator actions; these and many other data points can inform investigations when things go wrong allowing the identification of the root cause.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Richard Banyard</name><email>richard.banyard@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><category term="software" /><category term="food&amp;drink" /><category term="textiles" /><category term="power" /><category term="chemicals" /><summary type="html">“Do we really need to collect so much data?”</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22dennis-eusebio-MbiSXN8u8q4-unsplash-thumbnail.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22dennis-eusebio-MbiSXN8u8q4-unsplash-thumbnail.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22dennis-eusebio-MbiSXN8u8q4-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22There's%20more%20data%20'under%20the%20hood'%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22dennis-eusebio-MbiSXN8u8q4-unsplash-thumbnail.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22dennis-eusebio-MbiSXN8u8q4-unsplash-thumbnail.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22dennis-eusebio-MbiSXN8u8q4-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22There's%20more%20data%20'under%20the%20hood'%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>