<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-12-21T12:39:30+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/atom.xml</id><title type="html">Op-tec Systems</title><subtitle>Independent automation consultant</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Computer System Validation - a process</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/computer-system-validation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Computer System Validation - a process" /><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/computer-system-validation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/computer-system-validation">&lt;p&gt;It’s quite a while now since I was first involved with Computer System Validation (CSV). It was around 1994 if I recall correctly and it was during a large project for AstraZeneca that I cut my teeth on the computer system lifecycle approach to all things regulated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is CSV and why is it so especially important to the pharmaceutical industry?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer what CSV is I like to think back to a conference I attended in the 1990’s where one of the presenters was an American by the name of Ken Chapman. Ken was an inspirational person and had spend a huge part of his career working for Pfizer during which he developed computer system validation processes for the company while also sitting on a number of external pharmaceutical special interest boards as reviewer and advisor. I bring Ken’s name up because during the conference he dealt with a number of issues one of which If I recall correctly was regarding Electronic Signatures and Records (referred to colloquially within the industry as 21 CFR Part 11).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, at some point during the conference Ken simplified the whole validation process to the whole audience by writing down what Validation is – I’ll never forget the three lines of text he showed us:-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Say what you are going to do.&lt;/strong&gt; Specify and document your requirements and how they will be met.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do what you said you would do.&lt;/strong&gt; Develop and build the system according to the specifications you have written.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prove you did what you said you would do.&lt;/strong&gt; Test the system according to the specifications you have written.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put like this it all seems so simple doesn’t it. Essentially it is a simple process in itself but I do have to say that the pitfalls of validation are the extents that some people expect of the validation process which is a bit like asking for an extra hot latte at your local coffee shop – what do you exactly mean by extra hot (please define).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do you go about validating a computer system? Well first I would advise as to what parts of the system are to be validated. For instance if the production process requires that a compressed air system is provided then does it mean that the compressor software itself (normally provided by the OEM) is also validated? I think the argument here is how does the compressor software affect the finished product (i.e. would the operation of the air compressor by itself affect the end product’s quality attributes?). So although you may require the manufacturer to provide assurances that they have used a quality process to develop the compressor software it would not necessarily need to be validated as further upstream software would cover these requirements. What I mean by this is that lets say for parts of the process that require the use of compressed air (such as line pressure monitoring) would be validated as the critical parameter in this instance is likely to be the compressed air pressure entering the system. Another example of where CSV is normally limited is with regards to operating systems. This where the size and prevenance of the operating system weighs heavily in terms of this situation. For example by far the largest and most common operating system utilised by control systems today is Microsoft Windows. The attitude of the regulatory authorities is that the development of such a widely used operating system does not require by itself to be independently validated, rather because of such a large (and therefore proven) user base then this is not required. This is in some ways also similar to the example of the air compressor where the affect of the overall control system is dependant upon a range of systems but where in fact the actual validation of the system is covered because the overall testing process will cover the effective operation of the system. Shortlisting the areas of the system that actually need validating is important in regards to the overall validation time, effort, practicality and cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So is there a process or strategy involved in validating a computer system? The answer is that there are models and guidelines. The most popular model is known as the ‘V’ model. This is where the various documents defining the system are mapped against each other and the various test procedures. The idea is that the end user requirements are captured in the very beginning and are then used to ensure that all future documentation and requirements are included in the ensuing specifications. Figure 1 below shows the generic ‘V’ model. A small point but please note that the model gets its name from the ‘V’ shape of the model and that the ‘V’ doesn’t actually stand for Validation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/v-model.png&quot; alt=&quot;V-Model&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have an overall model that can shape the order and relationship of the various specifications and test scripts we can begin to consider the documents to be produced and the content therein.  Being an engineer I like the ideas of frameworks and guidelines and as luck would have it the ISPE (International Society of Pharmaceutical Engineering) have produced an extremely useful guideline regarding computer system validation which is directly applicable to control systems – the guide is known as GAMP (Good Automated Manufacturing Practice). It is currently on its 5th iteration and contains a wealth of information and guidance as to how to validate a computer system. It also describes the documents required together with example content lists for each document. So I strongly recommend anyone venturing into the wacky world of CSV to pick up a copy of the GAMP guidelines and save yourself hours of toil wondering just how to carry out the validation process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I finish this article there is something that I would like to mention about software in particular. It seems as though standards developers in batch circles and those involved in defining validation systems are of similar minds. Indeed, this is a very good example of good practice for all concerned. In batch circles the de-facto standard is known as ISA S88 which is used for defining batch terminology and processes (there is also the ISA 95 standard for defining the integration between enterprise planning system with control systems).  Both the ISA S88 and ISA S95 standards reference the importance and use of software modularity. In fact the ISA S88 standard also defines the hierarchy of company structures using such terms as Enterprise (to define a global company), a plant (an individual manufacturing site), an area (a manufacturing area within the plant such as a tank farm), a Unit (such as a Reactor or Centrifuge) and a control module (a number of devices that work together to provide a specific function such as an agitation).  In this regard the idea is that a software system is split into a hierarchy of smaller software modules. The idea is that it is easier (and more efficient) to provide software functionality in multiple modules than in one large piece of contiguous software. This makes sense in all sorts of ways, not least in that it is easier to specify the function of a system piece by piece (module by module). This also makes it easier to test the functionality of each piece separately before it being joined to the other software modules. Harking back to the ‘V’ model above, you will see that software modules and module tests are part of the validation process and where an integration test is used to test the system as a whole. Another benefit of this system results in only modules that share information or lines of command are joined together – thus reducing the complexity and the amount of information transfer or shared between one another and the resulting communications traffic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally ( I know I said “Before I finish” just before) but please bare with me. You may think that the above validation process is somewhat long winded. However the philosophy behind the process is not only to provide a validated system but also to provide an efficient way of developing computer based hardware and software systems. The benefit of the approach is to provide a well documented and validated system. Once documented it is easier to maintain (and modify if ever required in the future). The approach (since it is modular) also enables multiple developers to work in parallel thus reducing the overall development time of the system.  The process also lends itself to producing software in libraries for future re-use. Reusable software is extremely useful and from personal experience I recall reusing a colleague’s reporting software that originally took over 6 months to develop to only taking 3 days  to modify and reuse in another application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;application/ld+json&quot;&gt;{&quot;@context&quot;: &quot;https://schema.org&quot;,&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;FAQPage&quot;,&quot;mainEntity&quot;: 
[
{&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Question&quot;,&quot;name&quot;: &quot;What does CSV stand for?&quot;,&quot;acceptedAnswer&quot;: {&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Answer&quot;,&quot;text&quot;: &quot;Computer System Validation&quot;
}},
{&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Question&quot;,&quot;name&quot;: &quot;Is there a simple explanation for Computer System Validation?&quot;,&quot;acceptedAnswer&quot;: {&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Answer&quot;,&quot;text&quot;: &quot;Computer System Validation can be thought of in 3 stages: 1) Say what you are going to do - specify and document your requirements and how they will be met. 2) Do what you said you would do - develop and build the system according to the specifications you have written. 3) Prove you did what you said you would do - test the system according to the specifications you have written.&quot;
}}]
}&lt;/script&gt;</content><author><name>Roger Halliwell</name><email>roger.halliwell@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="knowledge" /><category term="pharmaceuticals" /><summary type="html">It’s quite a while now since I was first involved with Computer System Validation (CSV). It was around 1994 if I recall correctly and it was during a large project for AstraZeneca that I cut my teeth on the computer system lifecycle approach to all things regulated.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-pixabay-357514-small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-pixabay-357514-small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22pexels-pixabay-357514.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Computer%20System%20Validation%20creates%20documentation...%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-pixabay-357514-small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-pixabay-357514-small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22pexels-pixabay-357514.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Computer%20System%20Validation%20creates%20documentation...%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Is your DMZ a no man’s land?</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/is-your-DMZ-a-no-mans-land" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is your DMZ a no man’s land?" /><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/is-your-DMZ-a-no-mans-land</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/is-your-DMZ-a-no-mans-land">&lt;p&gt;Organisations continue to digitise. Whether intentionally via planned projects with dedicated budgets and resources, or unintentionally as suppliers embed remote monitoring into equipment and encourage migration to cloud-based software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time industrial automation (Operational Technology, OT) is making more use of the same open protocols used by Information Technology (IT). Pressures to improve efficiency mean organisations are increasingly integrating OT and IT systems to streamline processes and automate menial tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These trends mean there’s more crossover than ever between IT and OT, leading to more interaction between the teams responsible for each. The relationship between these teams can often be gauged by how they use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DMZ_(computing)&quot;&gt;demilitarised zone&lt;/a&gt; (DMZ).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the DMZ(s) in your organisation is treated as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/No_man%27s_land&quot;&gt;no man’s land&lt;/a&gt; by the IT and OT departments, a huge opportunity to increase the rate and quality of innovation and process improvement is being missed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll know this is happening if people tend to avoid communicating with the other ‘side’ when working in this network. They avoid it altogether. Or don’t take responsibility of the outcome when they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reasons friction can exist between IT and OT teams are well-documented and vary between organisations. The most common retort from people in OT is that IT personnel don’t appreciate the importance of planning system updates and changes, they don’t feel pain when systems go offline (planned or unplanned). People in IT have the opposite perspective, operational teams seem oblivious to security risks and the need to keep systems up to date so they can communicate securely with other parts of the organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of dividing people, use the DMZ to bridge the gap between them. Encourage experimentation to generate ideas for how the organisation can make use of its data. Rather than a little used buffer between networks, make the DMZ the location for proof of concepts, pilot projects and collaboration activities between business and operational teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some ideas to get you started:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set ground rules&lt;/strong&gt;. The DMZ is not a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandbox_(software_development)&quot;&gt;sandbox&lt;/a&gt;, it’s likely the only connection between your operational and business systems. Put measures in place to ensure production data moving through your DMZ can’t be impacted by trials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have clearly defined projects&lt;/strong&gt;. Ensure there is a single person responsible and accountable for every project. Then that all activity takes place within a defined project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Require, rather than expect collaboration&lt;/strong&gt;. Any work done in the DMZ - whether it’s replacing a patch lead or deploying a new process historian - should be done with the knowledge and preferably involvement of individuals from both OT and IT teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Log and record everything&lt;/strong&gt;. So you don’t lose out on any learning, and can explain why things work (or don’t).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maintain good cyber security hygiene&lt;/strong&gt;. Remember the DMZ’s main purpose is to secure your OT networks. Segregate production and non-production data. Only read data from your operational systems (you’ll likely have firewalls configured to do this already). Ensure you keep track of all assets connected to the network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if your DMZ resembles the image at the top of this article, think about taking down the razor wire and clearing the mines. Companies who master integration of their operational and business systems stand a far greater chance of remaining competitive in their markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create an environment where it raises a flag if someone mutters, “IT must have installed an update”, or “OT have plugged in another XP machine…” and make the most of this valuable resource sitting in clear view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ITandOT_DMZ.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Simplified DMZ Architecture&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Richard Banyard</name><email>richard.banyard@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><category term="chemicals" /><category term="power" /><category term="oil&amp;gas" /><summary type="html">Organisations continue to digitise. Whether intentionally via planned projects with dedicated budgets and resources, or unintentionally as suppliers embed remote monitoring into equipment and encourage migration to cloud-based software.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22picfair-06597943-no-mans-land-famagusta-cyprus-thumbnail.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22picfair-06597943-no-mans-land-famagusta-cyprus-thumbnail.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22picfair-06597943-no-mans-land-famagusta-cyprus-licensed.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Is%20this%20how%20your%20people%20treat%20the%20DMZ?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22picfair-06597943-no-mans-land-famagusta-cyprus-thumbnail.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22picfair-06597943-no-mans-land-famagusta-cyprus-thumbnail.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22picfair-06597943-no-mans-land-famagusta-cyprus-licensed.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Is%20this%20how%20your%20people%20treat%20the%20DMZ?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What my new smart watch taught me</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/What-my-new-smart-watch-taught-me" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What my new smart watch taught me" /><published>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/What-my-new-smart-watch-taught-me</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/What-my-new-smart-watch-taught-me">&lt;p&gt;I recently bought a new watch/fitness tracker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Am I happy with my investment?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well… Nobody will admit they have chosen badly, but…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d researched the alternatives, made a list of requirements (User Requirements Specification) created a comparison chart and made a good engineering decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new hardware captures all the data it sets out to; steps, pulse rate, oxygen saturation, sleep, divided into deep, light, rem and awake, altitude and depth so I know how far above or below sea level I am, and a compass and GPS. From all of this it derives and presents floors climbed, calories burned, excercise intensity, body battery (energy reserves) and stress level (something else for me to worry about).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what went wrong? The raw data capture is not all that it ought to be. Further problems lie with the assumptions made, calculations and analysis of data, and presentation of information. Example; If my calorie burn is correct then I’m heating the whole house with my body heat output, running on zero reserves with a blood oxygen level close to cyanosis of my vital organs and I don’t care one jot according to my stress level. I’m still above sea level though, which is reassuring after the recent rains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Points to ponder:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One size does not fit all when making assumptions in calculations. You need to tailor to individual needs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sense-check the results. Never abrogate responsibility to “Computer says”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get feedback from the customer and build in the ability to adjust or re-calibrate if necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are processes we at Op-tec go through as a matter of course for our customers. If we’re converting your production data into guidance for strategic decisions we will have carried out a thorough analysis of your needs and expectations, we will have made it clear what we can do and we will walk with you through the implementation process until what we have agreed has been fulfilled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://op-tec.co.uk/digital-benchmark&quot;&gt;Generate your free Digital Benchmark Report&lt;/a&gt; to learn more about our approach to technology investment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Peter Jackson</name><email>peter.jackson@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><summary type="html">I recently bought a new watch/fitness tracker.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22tim-foster-Odhl-kitI2c-unsplash-small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22tim-foster-Odhl-kitI2c-unsplash-small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22tim-foster-Odhl-kitI2c-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22A%20good%20investment?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22tim-foster-Odhl-kitI2c-unsplash-small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22tim-foster-Odhl-kitI2c-unsplash-small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22tim-foster-Odhl-kitI2c-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22A%20good%20investment?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Greenshirts of the Boiler Police are coming!</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/the-greenshirts-are-coming" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Greenshirts of the Boiler Police are coming!" /><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/the-greenshirts-are-coming</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/the-greenshirts-are-coming">&lt;p&gt;The government’s Domestic Renewable Heat Incentive is intended to reduce our reliance on using fossil fuels and to replace them with systems which use renewable energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Core to the incentive scheme is replacement of gas boilers with heat pumps. So, how do heat pumps work? Do the advantages in domestic settings stack up? And can industry benefit from heat pumps?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-heat-pumps-work&quot;&gt;How Heat Pumps Work&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heat pumps work rather like a refrigerator in reverse. Whereas a refrigerator removes heat via a liquid refrigerant to atmosphere a heat pump collects heat from the atmosphere and rejects the heat to radiators and hot water tanks. In this respect the heat pump system comprises a relatively simple circuit where refrigerant flows through an external evaporator coil where a fan is used to blow ambient air across the coil (these are the beige coloured units you see outside properties fitted with this kind of technology).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Refrigerant evaporates from a low pressure liquid state into vapour below ambient temperature so the coil takes in energy at this point. The low pressure vapour is then compressed into high pressure vapour; this process adds energy and increases its temperature (in a similar manner to the heat produced when you pump up bicycle tyres). The high pressure refrigerant vapour is then pumped to the condenser where it is cooled and condensed into high pressure liquid by water flowing through the heating system to heat the building and provide hot water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Will this provide me with a cheaper way of heating my home?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer to this question isn’t straight forward. Why? Well although the government will provide a £5,000 grant to fund the installation of a replacement heat pump system, the total cost of an installation is typically a lot more than this. For example, most contractors will quote in the region of £11,000 to £15,000 to install a heat pump system into the average 3 bedroom semi-detached house with the cost increasing for larger properties. You’ll also need to factor in the potential need for better insulation such as loft insulation, cavity wall insulation and improved double glazing. So the simple maths results in the home owner being left with a minimum installation bill of between £6,000 and £10,000. Following installation, you will then of course be able to muster free energy? Not entirely – once you have installed the system the heating source (the outside atmosphere in a home dwelling) is free but unfortunately and as mentioned above, the system relies upon a pumping system and a compressor which is powered by electricity. Although the cost of this electricity is presently less (per equivalent kWhr) than for gas, we are currently facing increased energy costs. So although less energy is expended in terms of equivalent kWhrs to gas, the running costs could end up being very little different than that of a gas boiler system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What about industry – can it benefit from heat pumps?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key point here is the re-use of already available heat. The efficiency of a heat pump is all about where you start from. In other words, more work (energy expended) is required if the initial heat source is at a lower temperature than a heat source from a higher initial temperature. For instance if there’s already an existing heat source which is not being put to good use (such as exhaust gases or steam flow) then these sources would be used to provide primary heat to a heat pump, thus increasing its efficiency hugely and potentially making the system highly viable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How effective are heat pumps in the real world?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well there’s a bit of an irony here. Remember that in a domestic setting that during the summer most people aren’t using the central heating very much apart from having hot water available for showers etc. This is a pity because during the summer months the outside ambient heat is far greater than in the winter and so the heat pump system is more efficient. The irony is that during the winter months (when the need for central heating is more obvious) domestic heat pumps do not supply the same level of efficient heating as during the summer months. In other words when we need the heat pump to provide heat to heat our houses during the winter it is less able to do so and during the summer months (when heat pumps are better able to provide heat) they aren’t needed as much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, compare this situation with an industrial setting where the initial heat source such as waste exhaust heat or steam is far more likely to be at an elevated temperature, is available all year round and relies upon what is in most cases is a by product of the industrial process. For these reasons the use of heat pumps in an industrial setting becomes extremely viable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are the green credentials behind heat pumps?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The green argument behind the use of heat pumps especially for home owners in a domestic setting is interesting. Yes, we are reducing the use of gas which power gas boilers in our homes which is a good thing. However, the system is not entirely green because the electricity used to power the pump and the compressor does not come from entirely green sources. This is due to the fact that electricity generation systems in the UK rely upon a large mix of energy sources – some renewable (e.g. Wind, Solar and Hydro) but also via a large number of gas fired power stations. However, the same can not be said in an industrial setting where the use of heat pumps can be seen as very green. This is because when using what is in many situations would be otherwise wasted heat, then the system efficiency is significant and far above that within most domestic settings. In other words, existing heat energy can be recycled through a heat pump and because the initial heat energy is relatively high to that found in many domestic settings the electrical energy expended to power the heat pump compressor in an industrial setting is comparatively less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To quote Boris Johnson recently writing in the Sun newspaper “the Greenshirts of the Boiler Police are not going to kick in your door with their sandal-clad feet and seize, at carrot-point, your trusty old combi”. But if you are approached by ‘the ‘Green Brigade’ then please be aware of the issues we have mentioned above, especially regarding domestic settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast we believe that there are many opportunities where heat pumps can be provided in industrial environments where the initial investment required is proven and where significant cost reductions can be made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One question you should be asking of any heat pump supplier is ‘Will the system that you are proposing be at least equivalent or better in terms of cost and efficiency than my existing gas boiler system whether in a domestic or industrial environment?’ To be able to answer this, a survey of your property or buildings is necessary in order to gauge the viability of a heat pump system. Such a survey should be from an independent source and will involve determining the specification of the heat pump system depending upon the heat loss of the home or buildings involved in an industrial situation. Only once armed with this information will you be able to determine the likely running costs and potential savings you may be able to enjoy and whether a heat pump is suitable for your home or for your company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;about-op-tec-systems&quot;&gt;About Op-tec Systems&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are an independent engineering consultancy with specific expertise in the provision of heating, ventilation and air conditioning systems. For further information on any of the above then please email us at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:projects@op-tec.co.uk&quot;&gt;projects@op-tec.co.uk&lt;/a&gt; or visit our web site at &lt;a href=&quot;https://op-tec.co.uk/&quot;&gt;op-tec.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Roger Halliwell</name><email>roger.halliwell@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="knowledge" /><category term="power" /><summary type="html">The government’s Domestic Renewable Heat Incentive is intended to reduce our reliance on using fossil fuels and to replace them with systems which use renewable energy.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-max-vakhtbovych-6316066-small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-max-vakhtbovych-6316066-small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22pexels-max-vakhtbovych-6316066.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Is%20a%20heat%20pump%20right%20for%20you?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-max-vakhtbovych-6316066-small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-max-vakhtbovych-6316066-small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22pexels-max-vakhtbovych-6316066.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Is%20a%20heat%20pump%20right%20for%20you?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Should you replace your DCS with PLC-SCADA?</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/should-you-replace-your-dcs-with-PLC-SCADA" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Should you replace your DCS with PLC-SCADA?" /><published>2021-09-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-09-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/should-you-replace-your-dcs-with-PLC-SCADA</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/should-you-replace-your-dcs-with-PLC-SCADA">&lt;h2 id=&quot;-white-paper-&quot;&gt;[ White Paper ]&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Download a PDF copy of this article &lt;a href=&quot;https://op-tec.co.uk/downloads/Should_you_replace_your_DCS_with_PLC-SCADA.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;u&gt;here&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For decades owners of large, complex, continuous and batch processes have relied on Distributed Control Systems (DCS) to control their plants. This technology is designed specifically for this purpose and reduces engineering costs associated with design, build, operation and maintenance phases of the project lifecycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, to gain these benefits, asset owners must pay for the greater upfront development costs DCS vendors incur with more expensive software, hardware and engineering hours – and can easily become ‘locked in’ to their suppliers ecosystem by the proprietary nature of the technology. In recent years an increasing number of end user organisations are looking to save on industrial automation by using cheaper, PLC and SCADA technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As more of a ‘blank canvas’ Programmable Logic Controllers (PLC) and Supervisory Control And Data Acquisition (SCADA) systems require more engineering time and expertise to develop and maintain solutions of equivalent complexity and function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially this discussion boils down to a trade-off between engineering a solution from scratch or buying one with a large number of components already made. As you’d expect, there’s more factors you’ll want to consider based on your company’s situation and objectives but this paper aims to give you clear guidelines for making the right decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-takeaways&quot;&gt;Key Takeaways&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gain high-level insight into the fundamental difference between these control system types&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understand the pros and cons of each, and how these impact ownership costs over system lifetime&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;See a direct costed comparison of the two system types&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learn about how DCS and PLC-SCADA solutions are likely to develop in the future&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Main factors which should drive your decision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To provide centralised control of your plant you need a DCS or SCADA based control system. These provide interfaces for staff in control rooms and on the factory/plant floor, giving them visibility and control over operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have an existing DCS, or are looking at implementing one, it pays to thoroughly understand the differences. Despite the technology these systems are based on having converged to some degree in recent years, they still represent significantly different options. The best choice for your organisation doesn’t necessarily depend on the complexity of your process - more your in-house engineering expertise, risk-appetite and supply chain strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-difference&quot;&gt;The Difference&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can be forgiven for thinking there’s no longer a big difference between DCS and PLC-SCADA systems. Nearly all the functionality offered by a DCSs can be provided by a PLC-SCADA-based system. Also, since most vendors recommend installation on Microsoft’s Windows operating systems there’s little to tell them apart when interacting with them day-to-day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we dive in, let’s clear up some ambiguity in the terminology being used. When people in the industrial automation industry typically refer to DCS, we really mean &lt;strong&gt;proprietary&lt;/strong&gt; distributed control systems. Over time the DCS acronym has moved from being used to define an architecture where &lt;em&gt;“&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Distributed_control_system&quot;&gt;autonomous controllers are distributed throughout the system&lt;/a&gt;”&lt;/em&gt; to tightly integrated control systems based on the proprietary technology of a single supplier. As opposed to PLC-SCADA solutions which, even if all components are purchased from one supplier are based on &lt;strong&gt;open&lt;/strong&gt; communication protocols.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historically, DCS solutions were best suited to large, highly automated plants, operating in highly regulated industries. Here the perceived reduction in risk associated with sourcing all process control and automation equipment from a single supplier - “having one number to call” (should things go wrong) - was worth paying a premium for. Add the fact DCSs were easier for in-house engineers to modify and expand alongside changes to the physical plant, meant previous generations of SCADA technology were unable to compete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PLC-SCADA systems on the other hand grew out of discrete manufacturing industries where automation tends to turn things on and off, rather than closely control a chemical processes. Here small, low-cost equipment was needed which didn’t often need to be connected to anything else. Over time the machines controlled have grown more sophisticated, and centralised data acquisition and supervision introduced. The resulting evolution has narrowed the gap between PLC-SCADA solutions and DCSs in terms of their capabilities. However the initial overhead associated with designing a system of comparable functionality and scale to a DCS, means PLC-SCADA solutions are still considered by many as unsuitable for large or complex applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;myths-to-dispel&quot;&gt;Myths to dispel&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the myths listed below were true at one time. However making decisions based on these common misconceptions today risks missing the opportunities available from using the latest PLC and SCADA technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PLC-based systems aren’t capable of handling large quantities of signals (I/O)&lt;/strong&gt; Modern PLCs are capable of processing just as many (sometimes more) signals as DCS controllers. Further the software and database technology adopted by modern SCADAs is more than capable of handling huge numbers of signals, powering advanced graphic displays and more.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integration with higher-level business systems is only possible with a DCS&lt;/strong&gt; Modern SCADAs are just as capable of being integrated into MES and ERP systems as DCS solutions. In fact there can be no additional license to pay unlike when these integrations are offered by DCS vendors.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;High-availability and redundant architectures require a DCS&lt;/strong&gt; PLCs are now available from a number of manufacturers which allow redundant and high-availability architectures to be built. Remote I/O systems with hot-swappable modules are also exist, compatible with industry standard, open communication protocols.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Only a DCS can provide multi-operator interfaces and advanced alarm management&lt;/strong&gt; Another area where modern SCADAs have caught up. There may be more configuration effort required but features such as alarm KPI dashboards, email and SMS texts and integration with external systems is all possible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Frequent plant modifications/extensions are easier with a DCS&lt;/strong&gt; Once a library of software modules have been created in a PLC-SCADA system the engineering time to perform plant expansions and modifications is equivalent to a DCS, and the method for doing so no more complicated providing sufficient thought has gone into this process during initial system design.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PLC-SCADA systems can’t handle batch operations&lt;/strong&gt; While complex batch processes may be easier to design and build using a DCS; simple processes and recipe management can be performed by PLC-SCADA systems.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DCSs represent the latest technology and offers a ‘higher end’ solution than PLC-SCADA&lt;/strong&gt; On the contrary, PLC-SCADA products are where the latest technological developments are introduced first. Due to the regulated industries they serve, and the certainty that vendors provide as part of their offer, DCS technology  often lags that of PLC-SCADA systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, there are few – if any – ‘hard’ technical differences between the two types of system exist. Owners of complex batch processes may still benefit from tight integration between the batch engine and PLC logic of a DCS solution but even this advantage is being eroded as Manufacturing Execution Systems develop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;So… if a “DCS” can be built with products based on open technology just as well as proprietary ones, is a discussion still needed?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-changed&quot;&gt;What’s Changed?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End-user views on this debate are changing at different rates across industries. I’ve seen chemicals manufacturers with batch processes ‘upgrade’ from DCS to PLC-SCADA solutions. Others in the same industry still see the benefits of keeping their DCS. Many however are now evaluating both technologies when they look to replace aging equipment which is no longer supported by the original manufacturer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So are there best practice guidelines? Not really. Many write on this subject, some try to distil the decision down to simple criteria such as the number of signals or whether the process is continuous. More recent thinking on the subject – at least from those without a vested interest in selling DCSs -  acknowledge the decision often comes down to “non-technical” factors. This is another way of saying the best solution for a company will likely be determined by its culture, competence, innovation strategy and the total cost of ownership over the lifetime of a system, rather than the technical limitations of available technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;current-thinking&quot;&gt;Current Thinking&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like a company’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/m/make-or-buy-decision.asp&quot;&gt;decision to make or buy&lt;/a&gt;, whether a DCS or PLC-SCADA is best is now determined by factors such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In-house control and automation expertise&lt;/strong&gt; – what expertise do you have at the moment? Are you planning to keep this into the future, increase or decrease the size of your engineering department. This likely has the biggest impact on the decision. As without in-house knowledge and capacity to own and drive development of control systems your company is likely better off buying-in engineering expertise.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supply chain management strategy&lt;/strong&gt; – how do you use equipment and technology? Whether you proactively manage assets throughout their life, or run them into the ground then replace them, has a bearing not only on the DCS vs PLC-SCADA decision but also on who you use to supply the technology.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Innovation strategy&lt;/strong&gt; – are you looking to select technology ‘once and for all’, or do you intend to continue developing and improving it throughout its life? Whether you operate in a highly regulated industry also has a bearing on this, but will not be the sole contributor to this factor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally, the choice comes down to whether your organisation is willing (and able) to take responsibility for specification of its automation technology; or happy to trust this to a supplier. To determine the best choice for your organisation you must evaluate the costs of doing this work in-house against those associated with accepting a suppliers standard solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re in a technical role, consider whether other purchases tend to be tightly controlled by an in-house subject matter expert or trusted advisor. If so, there should be appetite to invest in taking the same approach for industrial automation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or are you the budget holder? In which case, how much do you value the contribution of operational technology to your business’s strategy objectives? Are you willing to trust this to a supplier - motivated not only to show you results but also sell as much technology to you as possible?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;lifecycle-costs&quot;&gt;Lifecycle Costs&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand where the two options stand in terms of their cost of ownership, we conducted a survey of automation vendors and end users. We reviewed the prices vendors say they charge for different products and services, then compared them to the costs end users told us they’ve paid. We then normalised the results to come up with comparable numbers for a ‘typical’ control system&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A projection showing the annual costs of DCS ownership over 20 years including initial project delivery are shown below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/DCS-annual-cost-of-ownership.png&quot; alt=&quot;DCS annual cost of ownership projection&quot; style=&quot;float: left&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Annual costs are broken into the following categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Engineering – in-house and/or external engineers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hardware – physical system components&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software – one-off software licenses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Subscription – ongoing cost of incremental product updates, security patches and upgrades&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The projection for a PLC-SCADA system with the same specification:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/PLC-SCADA-annual-cost-of-ownership.png&quot; alt=&quot;PLC-SCADA annual cost of ownership projection&quot; style=&quot;float: left&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear PLC-SCADA based solutions are not always cheaper, initial project costs (shown here spread over the first 2 years) look equivalent. PLC-SCADA solutions typically need a more detailed requirements capture and design phase during the initial project – say where a legacy system is being replaced and limited documentation exists. In these cases the increased cost of engineering counters savings made in software and hardware costs associated with a DCS which comes to some degree pre-configured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our research shows initial project costs for PLC-SCADA solutions working out at £75,000 more than those for an equivalent DCS (£2.375 million, rather than £2.3 million respectively).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, savings start to be realised following the initial project, after which the cost of maintaining, updating and upgrading a PLC-SCADA solution remains cheaper throughout the lifetime of the system. This is down to PLC-SCADA system owners having a choice of potential suppliers throughout the system lifecycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To allow an easier comparison of the Total Cost of Ownership the projection below shows the accumulated costs associated with each system type.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/TCO-projections.png&quot; alt=&quot;Total cost of ownership projections&quot; style=&quot;float: left&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 20 years the total cost of ownership of each system works out to be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;DCS Total Cost of Ownership 		= 	£6,305,000&lt;br /&gt;

PLC-SCADA Total Cost of Ownership 	= 	£4,920,250&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;b&gt;Difference 				= 	£1,385,000&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stark differential during the systems’ operational phase is due to increased costs in 3 of the 4 categories analysed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Engineering – DCS vendors tend to charge more for engineering services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hardware – additional/spare hardware for DCSs tends to be more expensive&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software – charges for connecting 3rd party systems, increasing system size and adding functionality also tend to be more expensive within the ‘walled garden’ of a DCS solution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;other-considerations&quot;&gt;Other Considerations&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;pricing-risk&quot;&gt;Pricing Risk&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many end users put their decision to select a DCS down to “pricing risk”, this could also be described as “pricing convenience”. The main reason for DCS being considered “less risky” is using a single supplier for all design, system components, installation and support, removes integration risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In selecting a DCS solution you give responsibility for system design, reliability, availability and lifecycle management to your chosen supplier. Whereas buying a PLC-SCADA solution requires more of this work be done either in-house or by a 3rd party, typically a systems integrator who buys-in system components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should any aspect of the initial project or subsequent system performance not meet the agreed specification, dialogue is only needed with one party in the case of a DCS. With a PLC-SCADA solution, while the systems integrator is the first point of contact they will need to liaise with component manufacturers and/or other service providers to resolve issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether savings made over the system lifecycle justify the additional work involved in managing or outsourcing this risk is dependent on how well equipped your organisation is, or intends to be, in this area. Knowing many end user organisations have reduced headcount over recent years, outsourcing much of their high-level engineering; DCS vendors make buying their solutions easy and often discount projects to secure the higher margin ‘service’ business they know follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;innovation&quot;&gt;Innovation&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your company embraces the latest technology and aims to define, rather than adopt, industry best practice there are compelling reasons to select a PLC-SCADA solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology used to build proprietary DCSs tends to lag that used in PLC and SCADA products. This is due to its historic use in highly regulated industries where equipment typically needs to have been ‘proven in use’ before it can be put into active service. Most vendors provide both DCS and PLC-SCADA solutions. Because the number PLC-SCADA systems sold outnumbers those of DCS, development of PLC and SCADA technology is prioritised. DCS solutions can then be built on top of this software and equipment once it has spent a sufficient time running in production environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PLC and SCADA products, on the whole, come onto the market equipped with the latest features and are compatible with the latest communication protocols. Also the flexibility offered by a system based on Open Technology greatly reduces the integration costs associated with experimenting with new technology and conducting proof of concept projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;digital-transformation-and-industry-40&quot;&gt;Digital Transformation and Industry 4.0&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all companies at least considering – if not well into the process of – digitising their operations, understanding how your control system fits into your organisations’ digital strategy is essential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While DCS vendors continue to charge significant license fees to connect 3rd party systems to their products, the manufacturers of modern SCADAs encourage their connection to other systems by including the necessary functionality as standard. This allows scalable modern system architectures compatible with the latest IIoT (Industrial Internet of Things) smart devices, advanced data analytics and integration with IT systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are representations of a ‘traditional’ or Industry 3 automation architecture and that of a modern Industry 4.0 solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Control-system-architectures.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Control system architectures&quot; style=&quot;float: left&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The traditional system (left) requires all data to flow through every component, requiring updates to each when changes are made. The Industry 4.0 system architecture features a central repository (‘Unified Namespace’), automatically updated when one of the satellite systems is updated. This greatly reduces the costs of keeping systems up to date, and encourages innovation and experimentation where advanced data analytics continually propose better ways to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to their proprietary nature and way DCSs are licensed the costs of using them to build an architecture based on Industry 4.0 principles will increase significantly through time. Unfortunately we weren’t able to include for this in the projections above due to a lack of installed examples. As this will be an increasingly important consideration for most owners of DCSs, it will no doubt be the subject of a subsequent white paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;best-approach-for-you&quot;&gt;Best Approach for You&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A PLC-SCADA based solution deserves serious consideration by every company facing this discussion. To determine whether it’s the option you should select boils down to whether you can answer the following question positively:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Is your organisation equipped, willing and able to take responsibility for the design and upkeep of its control systems?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If so you are in a position to benefit from the cost savings, commercial and technological advantages of a PLC-SCADA solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use the checklist below to evaluate this in more detail. Your organisation may have other criteria which need to be considered, and likely won’t give equal weight to the considerations we outline. So before you start add any additional criteria to this list then consider a weighting to apply to each.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider how strongly you agree with the statements in each category. A higher score suggests a PLC-SCADA based solution will better suit your organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Innovation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Formal process exist for conducting proof of concept projects - justifying them, measuring their success, then acting on the results.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investment is made into generating ideas and research and development.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We develop best practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Skills&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;System documentation is kept up to date, backups are regularly taken, and lifecycle management plan is in place and technology is a key component of the business strategy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We have dedicated technical resources in-house or trusted suppliers who are reliable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Suppliers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We prefer to put technology purchases and support contracts out to competitive tender.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Going to the market with new project opportunities ensures we always consider the latest technology and make the most of supplier experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Culture&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The company invests strategically in increasing the productivity of its workforce.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our customers’ needs drive continual innovation and improvement.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We constantly update and adapt our processes to fit market and client requirements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The organisation is willing to invest now, to make future savings.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Having multiple potential suppliers is a key part of our procurement strategy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Is your organisation equipped, willing and able to take responsibility for the design and upkeep of its control systems?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t have to be done in-house, but if you plan to use external contractors it’s crucial to incentivise them correctly so their interests align with yours. Do this by effectively communicating your long-term strategy and objectives, then ensuring success of any contracts contribute towards them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your company is not in a position to take responsibility in this way, or you’d prefer to build a strategic partnership with a single supplier, a DCS represents a better solution. But if you take this route, do not begrudge the subsequent charges made to maintain and improve the system, remembering the work you saved by opting for this approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get in touch if you would like to discuss any aspect of this white paper, or are looking for help or advice making this important and enduring decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fas fa-phone-alt&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;abbr title=&quot;Phone&quot;&gt;&lt;/abbr&gt; &amp;nbsp; &lt;a href=&quot;tel:00441616604293&quot; id=&quot;number&quot;&gt;+44 161 660 4293&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fas fa-envelope&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;abbr title=&quot;Email&quot;&gt;&lt;/abbr&gt; &amp;nbsp; &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:projects@op-tec.co.uk?subject=Maximising%20the%20return%20from%20technology%20projects&quot;&gt;projects&amp;#64;op-tec.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Download a PDF copy of this article &lt;a href=&quot;https://op-tec.co.uk/downloads/Should_you_replace_your_DCS_with_PLC-SCADA.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;u&gt;here&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We based our projections on the following assumptions:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;20 year system lifetime&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;System with 3,500 signals (I/O points) and 8 operator consoles&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Commitment to vendor software subscriptions and 5 yearly updates to the latest system version&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;One plant modification project carried out every 5 years (starting in year 3)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE:&lt;/strong&gt; Cost information provided is for comparative and discussion purposes only and should not be used to budget for, benchmark or otherwise price a control system. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Richard Banyard</name><email>richard.banyard@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="knowledge" /><category term="chemicals" /><category term="power" /><category term="pharmaceuticals" /><category term="oil&amp;gas" /><summary type="html">[ White Paper ]</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22alexander-tsang-ppN1zRQrCEg-unsplash_small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22alexander-tsang-ppN1zRQrCEg-unsplash_small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22alexander-tsang-ppN1zRQrCEg-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Is%20a%20DCS%20still%20the%20best%20choice?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22alexander-tsang-ppN1zRQrCEg-unsplash_small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22alexander-tsang-ppN1zRQrCEg-unsplash_small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22alexander-tsang-ppN1zRQrCEg-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Is%20a%20DCS%20still%20the%20best%20choice?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Should you accept automation vendors’ vision of the future?</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/should-you-accept-automation-vendors-vision-of-the-future" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Should you accept automation vendors’ vision of the future?" /><published>2021-08-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/should-you-accept-automation-vendors-vision-of-the-future</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/should-you-accept-automation-vendors-vision-of-the-future">&lt;p&gt;Automation vendors develop great products and services. They excel at leveraging the latest technological developments to solve the problems facing industries they work in. After creating a vision for the future, vendors put a lot of effort into communicating it to the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of this communciation is educational, and used by many to stay up to date with automation industry trends and opportunities for improvement. Understanding what is possible allows owners of factories, plants and facilicities to plan investment and stay up to date with technological developments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But does what they’re recommending fit into &lt;strong&gt;your&lt;/strong&gt; strategy and address &lt;strong&gt;your&lt;/strong&gt; problems?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Take Integrated Control and Safety Systems (ICSS).&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;If you’re not familiar, this is the concept of sourcing all control and safety systems from one supplier in a fully integrated package.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;A big market for ICSS is the oil &amp;amp; gas industry, where safety (shutdown) systems can be as large and complex as the process control systems they supervise. Here the benefits typically cited by vendors make installing an ICSS solution very appealing:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Simplified system/network architecture&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Fast and efficient communications between control and safety systems&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Cost savings from reduction in required spares (thanks to common hardware) and engineering hours (standard programming and maintenance interfaces)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Increased visibility of safety system information&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Ability to avoid duplicating functionality (process data read by safety equipment can easily be used for process control)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Single supplier for all programmable automation equipment&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The list goes on…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;ICSS’s are, of course, good for automation vendors too. By increasing their scope of supply they can push out competitors, and have a larger ‘installed base’ to offer service and support packages on. It would seem a win-win …&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Except, something else is very important to the oil &amp;amp; gas industry: &lt;strong&gt;cyber security&lt;/strong&gt;. In particular the risk associated with losing control while integrity of the emergency shutdown system is also compromised. Security incidents in recent years have led several oil majors to review their ICSS architectures and put additional measures in place to address this risk.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;When writing this article I couldn’t find a single vendor website which mentioned cyber security on the page explaining their ICSS solution.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I’m not saying ICSSs are insecure or claims their manufacturers make are untrue.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I am saying it pays to test solutions against your own strategy, requirements and risk appetite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End-users tend to focus more on reducing initial project costs than lifecycle ownership costs. They can control the (competitive) project tendering process, but have little purchasing power when buying spare parts from a (sole) supplier. This leads automation vendors to use higher-margin service revenue to recover profit lost during projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding and avoiding the potential pitfalls of recommended solutions is crucial to building infrastructure which supports, rather than undermines, your long-term strategy. Suppliers will always be happy to save you time and money early on by using ‘tried and testeed’ or ‘standard’ solutions - they know it’ll pay them in the long-term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t only apply to highly automated and integrated companies. How many machine suppliers now build a facility for remote access into their equipment? Who owns the data, taken from your plant, driving the web portal you use to monitor energy consumption? I could go on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treat the future vision presented by suppliers with healthy scepticism. Ensuring you fully understand the long-term implications of competing designs and approaches will ensure you don’t end up living someone else’s future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Richard Banyard</name><email>richard.banyard@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><summary type="html">Automation vendors develop great products and services. They excel at leveraging the latest technological developments to solve the problems facing industries they work in. After creating a vision for the future, vendors put a lot of effort into communicating it to the market.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22artyom-kim-uydt8hNz3hE-unsplash_small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22artyom-kim-uydt8hNz3hE-unsplash_small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22artyom-kim-uydt8hNz3hE-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Are%20you%20being%20pushed%20into%20someone%20else's%20future?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22artyom-kim-uydt8hNz3hE-unsplash_small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22artyom-kim-uydt8hNz3hE-unsplash_small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22artyom-kim-uydt8hNz3hE-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Are%20you%20being%20pushed%20into%20someone%20else's%20future?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Avoid getting locked into a single automation vendor</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/how-to-avoid-vendor-lock-in" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Avoid getting locked into a single automation vendor" /><published>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/how-to-avoid-vendor-lock-in</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/how-to-avoid-vendor-lock-in">&lt;p&gt;If you represent a large multi-national company, and are looking to standardise on one automation vendor who will become a strategic partner, this article isn’t for you. With your scale you’ll have enough power over your chosen supplier to agree pricing structures, encourage development of new products, and ensure support for your equipment continues for as long as you need it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For everyone else, particularly SMEs, the downsides of being reliant on a single supplier often outweigh the ups. Do any of these sound familiar: lack of bargaining power; no access to the latest innovations until they’re adopted by your supplier; feeling forced into product updates; excessive license costs to transfer data into other systems?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If so keep reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The established automation vendors have a wealth of industry experience and expertise, product portfolios which meet almost every need, and provide high-quality support throughout the lifecycle of their products. The flip side to this is their ability to lock customers into their ecosystems, securing future revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So is it possible to benefit from the undoubtedly high quality products and services offered by the main vendors without getting locked-in? I believe so. Below is high-level guidance for how to do so, followed by more detailed considerations intended to help engineers with the practical implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guidance&quot;&gt;Guidance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-own-your-digital-infrastructure&quot;&gt;1. Own your ‘digital infrastructure’&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t just your networks and computer systems, but the intellectual property built into software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the centre of any business which has digitally transformed is a datastore containing every data point and piece of information about the company’s operations. This isn’t unstructured data, a lot of effort will have gone into developing data structures which model physical assets. These ‘Digital Twins’ not only define the characteristics of individual pieces of equipment, but also how they communicate with one another and the human workforce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having ownership and control of this central datastore sounds like a no-brainer, it contains the inner workings of your business and a substantial amount of its IP after all. But you’d be surprised at how many companies let automation vendors design these data structures. In so doing, handing them control over how they operate now and into the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-standardise-on-open-technology&quot;&gt;2. Standardise on ‘Open Technology’&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wherever possible Open communication protocols should be used, between equipment provided by different suppliers and perhaps more importantly within systems and solutions. Do not accept arguments about proprietary technology being cheaper and more efficient. This may be the case during project execution, but will almost certainly not be over the equipment’s lifecycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, you should standardise on certain protocols and technology to reduce costs associated with operation and maintenance. But an architecture built using well selected open technologies will ensure you always have a choice of supplier for any future maintenance, modification or migration work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-produce-accurate-and-comprehensive-user-requirement-specifications&quot;&gt;3. Produce accurate and comprehensive User Requirement Specifications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time invested in developing complete User Requirement Specification (URS) documents will rarely be wasted - only if you later decide not to proceed with the project. These are the vehicle for communicating your work to this point to your supply chain. Not only do accurate and comprehensive URSs make it easier to evaluate proposals, but also ensure your suppliers deliver according to your needs and not what’s easiest or most profitable for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;URSs which identify and set out how your supplier’s scope of supply will contribute to your business’s objectives also make evaluated success on contribution to the business rather than simply ‘delivered to scope’ far easier and speeds up the rate at which your organisation learns lessons and improves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-align-your-procurement-strategy-to-your-objectives&quot;&gt;4. Align your procurement strategy to your objectives&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And not cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can’t be emphasised enough. If cost was the only factor driving technology projects you’d evaluate every one against the cost of simply maintaining your current equipment. No, the benefits of technology projects need to be clearly identified and built into your procurement process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to note, this doesn’t necessitate making crucial decisions on qualitative measures of success – business cases which put a monetary value on achieving strategic objectives are a powerful tool to prioritise and justify investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implementation&quot;&gt;Implementation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-own-your-digital-infrastructure-1&quot;&gt;1. Own your ‘digital infrastructure’&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digital infrastructure, as we define it, can be broken into hardware and software components. To ensure your physical infrastructure is capable of supporting equipment from any vendor and future expansion and upgrade, you’ll need to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create and maintain an up-to-date asset register which documents all ‘active’ devices and the connections between them and external systems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Determine standards for connections at all levels of your system architecture, considering different requirements for resilience, bandwith and determinism&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decide where your central datastore/unified namespace/single source of truth will or does reside&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Review your asset register identifying objects with similar characteristics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A strong relationship with your IT department is crucial to your success. They’re your gateway to delivering data to users via higher level company networks, and can support you with expertise and resources in areas such as networking, security and cloud computing.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The software component of your infrastructure is all about establishing standards you can impose on suppliers of automation, which define how your facility runs. This largely takes the form of data structures for communications between systems, and the digital twins which reside in your central datastore. Standards are required for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Communications between equipment, systems and the human workforce&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Object types for tangible assets like shop floor equipment and fleet vehicles, as well as intangible assets like production batches and material deliveries&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All types of HMI&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data structures for all databases and communication pathways&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Security models for managing access to data and information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-standardise-on-open-technology-1&quot;&gt;2. Standardise on ‘Open Technology’&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideally all communications between your automation systems and system components should be via open protocols. In practice this isn’t always in your control, for example packaged equipment must be treated in many cases as a ‘black box’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider how far down in your architecture you wish to specify the protocols in use. You may, for example, be willing to tolerate proprietary communciation between a PLC’s processor and input/output cards. In which case you’ll have to accept using equipment from the same manufacturer for any future upgrade or expansion of this device - unless complete replacement is acceptable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now review your facility in light of this decision:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Review existing systems, noting the protocols used to communciate within individual systems (between CPUs, I/O modules, HMIs, …), and across the entire facility (between PLCs, SCADA systems, smart devices, historians, reporting tools, …)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Record this information in your asset register&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a list of the communication protocols in use across your site, noting which are proprietary and which open&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Determine the protocols you wish to standardise on for each type of communication path&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-produce-accurate-and-comprehensive-user-requirement-specifications-1&quot;&gt;3. Produce accurate and comprehensive User Requirement Specifications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Centralising requirements for HMI design, communication protocols, HMI design, alarming, etc. will ensure technology you invest in is consistent in quality and will communciate with any other system you install in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll need to create a URS, however brief, to define every project you undertake. However this will become easier as you build a core library of standards detailing your expectations and requirements for suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many specification documents you need, and the level of detail they go into, depends on many factors. These include: the scale and complexity of your operations, the currentl level of automation, in-house skills and expertise, and existing relationships with suppliers. If you are early in this process prioritise according to where your company will see the greatest gains. Below is a list of questions to get you thinking:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How much do you anticipate spending on automation in the coming years?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What impact has an over-reliance on certain suppliers had on your business to this point?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you have skills and expertise in-house?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can you allocate sufficient resource to this, not just now, but in the future?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-align-your-procurement-strategy-to-your-objectives-1&quot;&gt;4. Align your procurement strategy to your objectives&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investments in automation should be treated by the business as strategic, as those into CRM or ERP systems. Not all automation solutions are the same, and companies will have to live with the costs of selecting the wrong technology for decades. Particularly if they allow suppliers to deliver to their own specifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those responsible for procuring automation, should be educated in these consequences along with the potential upsides of putting in digital technology which will drive performance increases across the organisation. Buyers must be incentivised to provide the technology which will best deliver on the company’s strategic objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Incorporate learning back into your specification documents and guidance to buyers. Sometimes the true cost of a particular technology is only revealed once the equipment is in production, or even when the time comes to replace it. The main vendors are very adept at concealing the costs of maintaining, upgrading and modifying their systems so every effort should be made to anticipate this in your URS documentation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Systems should be supplied with any functionality and license costs included, which allow connection via open protocols. This is particularly important for users of distributed control systems (DCS), where 5 figure sums are not uncommon for the equipment and licenses needed to allow data to be retrieved from systems via OPC an extremely common industrial ethernet-based protocol. Include the additional costs suppliers apply to such functionality in any comparisons you make between solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putting the processes and procedures in place to ensure you correctly specify automation projects to avoid being locked into a suppliers’ ecosystem is not free. It may put more pressure on your existing engineering team, or even require you to recruit or contract the necessary expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether this expense is worth it will depend on your situation. By ‘commoditising’ the components of your automation systems you’ll have much greater control over the technology available and what you pay for it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Richard Banyard</name><email>richard.banyard@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="knowledge" /><category term="chemicals" /><category term="food&amp;drink" /><category term="power" /><summary type="html">If you represent a large multi-national company, and are looking to standardise on one automation vendor who will become a strategic partner, this article isn’t for you. With your scale you’ll have enough power over your chosen supplier to agree pricing structures, encourage development of new products, and ensure support for your equipment continues for as long as you need it.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22hasan-almasi-aIRBGPafi74-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22hasan-almasi-aIRBGPafi74-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22hasan-almasi-aIRBGPafi74-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Is%20a%20single%20vendor%20system%20based%20on%20open%20technology%20possible?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22hasan-almasi-aIRBGPafi74-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22hasan-almasi-aIRBGPafi74-unsplash-thumb.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22hasan-almasi-aIRBGPafi74-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Is%20a%20single%20vendor%20system%20based%20on%20open%20technology%20possible?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Waking up your data</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/waking-up-your-data" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Waking up your data" /><published>2021-04-13T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-04-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/waking-up-your-data</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/waking-up-your-data">&lt;p&gt;We live in an ever more competitive age where increasing the capability of our assets is becoming more and more important. However, we rarely think in terms of how important the data that surrounds us is and how it can help improve our operations. Many well-known institutions and blue chip companies are effectively ‘Sleeping Giants’ when it comes to this issue. They find it difficult to recognise the importance of their data because the nature of their business hasn’t changed. Simply not considering themselves technology firms, they see established supply chains, tried and tested operating procedures, and fixed assets their competitive advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what separates less data centric companies from those happy to invest in technology who analyse every heartbeat of their operations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer often lies in culture and the way manufacturing demand is perceived. All industries are subject to manufacturing and/or performance targets driven by the need to remain competitive.  However, historically much of heavy industry has been less concerned with performance, whereas ‘lighter’ industries tend to think much more in terms of cost per unit. It’s more common to see certain industries focused on how costs are measured, how the manufacturing process runs and how all of this affects product manufacturing throughput and quality. The fact many lighter industries are also discrete manufacturing entities and subject to market ‘Pull’ conditions also tends to necessitate a ‘high efficiency’ mindset. Continuous and heavy industries seem more likely to succumb to “we’ve always done it this way” thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, there are good and bad examples in all industries. Whichever way you look at it making improvements in your processes to save money can only be a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real issue is a company’s vision and strategy and whether they include the improvement of its manufacturing processes, to both increase product manufacturing capacity and improve quality. Both are key factors which ultimately increase a company’s profitability and competitiveness, but require investment. These important issues are subject to specific standards regarding asset management, the most notable being ISO 5500x (i.e. ISO 55000, 55001 and 55002) which were derived from the BSI PSA 55 2014 standard. These standards advocate a systematic process for managing company assets which: increases reliability, reduces downtime, improves quality, reduces waste, increases customer satisfaction, and ultimately makes the company more competitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investment… in our personal lives we are only too keen to invest when it provides a good return and ensures the roof doesn’t fall down. But at work one of the most common phrases remains “sweating the assets”, even if it seems to the detriment of efficiency and reliability. Surely this doesn’t make sense when for a fraction of the cost of the benefits the plant can be made to run more reliably and efficiently saving £££’s in the process?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Sweating the assets” (also known as the ‘Breakdown strategy’, incidentally) will one day result in catastrophic failure, halting production completely. Companies following such a strategy would benefit enormously from adopting the ISO 55000 standard – unless closure of the plant is in the short-term plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ISO 55000 aligns a company’s objectives and goals with a method of ensuring they are implemented via a process of continuous improvement. Once adopted as company policy by senior management the system provides a vehicle and framework for improvement. Stakeholders will be reassured the company is proactively and systematically improving the business and ensuring its sustainability and profitability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting back to the title of this article… a key concept is the ‘Hidden Plant’ and using data to uncover potential gains and enable you to measure the benefit of improvements. Once you’ve put in place a system for capturing and analysing your plant’s data you can make changes to your processes in alignment with your company’s objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These systems enable predictive maintenance to be planned reducing preventative action which shuts down plant unnecessarily. Continuously monitoring the health of assets over time also shows their gradual degradation. This tells you the most economical time to replace equipment, avoiding it operating outside defined levels of performance or where the likelihood of catastrophic failure is too great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the vast majority of cases the essential data required to improve the running and performance of your plant is already in place. The issue is how to display this data in a way that is meaningful to the plant operations staff and what the cost of this is versus the benefits. So let’s look at how we can determine whether the investment needed to provide an Asset Management system outweighs the cost of the investment. Let’s take an example where the cost of an Asset Performance System is £30k and its lifetime is 10 years:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An average cost saving of £3k/year would justify the investment. For many production facilities, one single breakdown lasting as little as 30 minutes could cost as much as £30k. So if one half-hour unplanned outage is prevented the company recovers its initial investment. Additional benefits would also be the collation and visualisation of data at the company’s HQ where the monitoring of each manufacturing facility is carried out by performance personnel, thus likely enabling local staff to be redeployed resulting in further savings via increased efficiency. Add to this maintenance savings, increased predictability (and therefore quality) and longer asset life, and hopefully the benefits of Asset Management are clear to see.*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The figure below shows how a large number of plants can benefit from a single Asset Management System. Data is published by each site location and analysed centrally, with advisory or control information sent back ensuring each plant runs optimally and continuous improvement actions can be quickly implemented across the organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/asset-management-example.png&quot; alt=&quot;Asset Management Example&quot; style=&quot;float: left&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;small&gt;Example of organisation-wide asset management system&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested to learn more about how automation technology can help you get more from your existing assets then understanding how your current situation compares to industry best practice is a good place to start. Click the button below to find out about how your bespoke Digital Benchmark Report™ provides you with this, and tailored recommended actions you can take to improve your company’s digital infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-benchmark&quot; class=&quot;btn&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Get your Digital Benchmark Report&lt;/b&gt;&amp;trade;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*This business case has been greatly simplified, ignoring the cost of capital among the many other factors which can influence investment decisions in organisations. If building business cases is an area you need help in, we are experienced in working with our clients to build robust and measurable project justifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Download a PDF copy of this article &lt;a href=&quot;https://op-tec.co.uk/downloads/Waking_up_your_data_-_Op-tec_Systems.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;u&gt;here&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Roger Halliwell</name><email>roger.halliwell@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><category term="chemicals" /><category term="power" /><category term="pharmaceuticals" /><summary type="html">We live in an ever more competitive age where increasing the capability of our assets is becoming more and more important. However, we rarely think in terms of how important the data that surrounds us is and how it can help improve our operations. Many well-known institutions and blue chip companies are effectively ‘Sleeping Giants’ when it comes to this issue. They find it difficult to recognise the importance of their data because the nature of their business hasn’t changed. Simply not considering themselves technology firms, they see established supply chains, tried and tested operating procedures, and fixed assets their competitive advantage.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-thisisengineering-3861969_small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-thisisengineering-3861969_small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22pexels-thisisengineering-3861969.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22How%20valuable%20is%20your%20data?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-thisisengineering-3861969_small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-thisisengineering-3861969_small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22pexels-thisisengineering-3861969.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22How%20valuable%20is%20your%20data?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Quantum Leap Technologies</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/client-profile/QL-Tech" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quantum Leap Technologies" /><published>2021-04-07T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-04-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/client-profile/QL-Tech</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/client-profile/QL-Tech">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Even if you can’t recall exactly where you were when you heard the news of the Gulf of Mexico Deepwater Horizon disaster, it’s likely that you will remember quite a lot about one of the most environmentally and commercially damaging incidents in the history of oil and gas operations, which cost the lives of 11 people. After the immediate explosion, oil continued leaking from the well at a rate of up to 60,000 barrels a day.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A company based in Aberdeen, Scotland, has developed an ingenious solution for blowout prevention in collaboration with Op-tec Systems that involves repurposing electric motors and drivetrain technology similar to carmaker Tesla’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We were contracted by a large oil and gas company in the USA to build a blowout prevention application for offshore drilling and extraction operations,” says Ben Bamford, founder and CEO of Quantum Leap Technologies (QL Tech). “They were looking for new ideas of how to control that equipment and to ensure a high level of assurance that the issues were being addressed.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thinking-laterally&quot;&gt;Thinking laterally&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conventional way of preventing, managing or suppressing a blowout or similar emergency is to use huge, gas-filled bottles to push liquid out at high pressure. QL Tech and Op-tec came up with something rather different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We took the heart of a Tesla Model S car: the battery, inverter and motor. Instead of putting wheels on it, we attached a pump to the electric motor,” Ben says. “Our solution, which provides hydraulic fluid to operate the safety equipment, is powered from a battery system and can accelerate output equivalent to doing 0 to 60 mph in a few seconds. We were integrating advanced technology that has recently come to the fore and been qualified for electric car applications. The engineering challenge was to demonstrate that the system can be used robustly for a safety application.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Battery power is maintained by trickle-feed of electricity so that it is always ready to be deployed, with zero notice. The whole system had to be made sufficiently robust to withstand the harsh environment at a marine depth of 3,000 metres, including ultra-high pressure, currents, temperature and the corrosive influence of saltwater, and to do so in an emergency where time was critical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-project-put-into-practice-ideas-and-objectives-that-op-tec-and-ql-tech-have-in-common&quot;&gt;The project put into practice ideas and objectives that Op-tec and QL Tech have in common.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Op-tec helped us with PLC (programmable logic control) and software elements. Richard (Banyard) and I are kindred spirits, in feeling there is so much more that can be done with low-cost hardware, the application of a bit more machine intelligence and a bit more focus on integrating with existing systems,” Ben explains. “Some of the new pieces of technology and commoditised software building blocks are really changing the game.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;QL Tech has three operating divisions: Integrated Power Solutions, which provides class-leading battery, inverter and control systems; 57 Degrees, which develops and delivers intelligent robotics for industrial applications; and Leap Automation, which provides accessible, affordable automation services to the manufacturing sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unusually for the automation sector, it is a vertically-integrated company. It designs and builds its own robot arms and tools, as well as working with specialist collaborators and partners, like Op-tec. It has a novel approach to the application of artificial intelligence, as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dont-over-engineer-solutions-that-arent-needed&quot;&gt;Don’t over-engineer solutions that aren’t needed&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Building a robot arm is easier and cheaper than it has ever been before and we have found that, in many applications, artificial intelligence-driven robots don’t need the same level of precision of conventional robots,” Ben explains. It’s quite a bold assertion when precision for many automated tasks is essential. “Some robots are being sold to food and drink companies, for example, that are over -engineered, in our view. Very much more basic systems can provide tremendous amounts of value. By engineering solutions that are specific to the customers we can make the economics work and hit economies of scale much sooner.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ben mentioned a brewery that had examined a machine to automate the sorting and packing of cans. QL Tech suggested a solution that, instead of being absolutely precise, was ‘good enough’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our solution was much simpler mechanically but much more complex from a software perspective,” he continues. “The artificial intelligence we are using and the vision system we have built-in allows the robot to interpret the world around it. We don’t need the cans to be in exactly the right spot; it just needs to be in the right area and the robot will pick and pack it successfully.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;QL Tech is bringing similar thinking to a solution for painting undersea pipe and pumping applications, and to systems for detecting faults in food processing lines, such as spotting and removing defective bread rolls. Quantum Leap Technologies believes so strongly in its approach to business that it allows customers to rent a solution and to try before buying, which helps reduce risk and make automation more available for SMEs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Download a PDF copy of this article &lt;a href=&quot;https://op-tec.co.uk/downloads/QL_Tech_&amp;amp;_Op-tec_Systems_-_Better_than_Cure.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;u&gt;here&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Projects</name><email>projects@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="client-profile" /><category term="oil&amp;gas" /><summary type="html">Even if you can’t recall exactly where you were when you heard the news of the Gulf of Mexico Deepwater Horizon disaster, it’s likely that you will remember quite a lot about one of the most environmentally and commercially damaging incidents in the history of oil and gas operations, which cost the lives of 11 people. After the immediate explosion, oil continued leaking from the well at a rate of up to 60,000 barrels a day.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-zukiman-mohamad-87236.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-zukiman-mohamad-87236.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-zukiman-mohamad-87236.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-zukiman-mohamad-87236.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Much ado about heating</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/Much-ado-about-heating" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Much ado about heating" /><published>2021-03-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-03-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/Much-ado-about-heating</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/Much-ado-about-heating">&lt;p&gt;There is much debate on the efficacy of heat pumps for domestic heating, but heat pumps alone are not the answer. There are a number of technologies in the heat transfer, energy storage and electricity supply industries that need to be integrated, and done successfully, the whole will be greater than the sum of the parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an attempt to add light as well as heat to the discussion we must consider the heat pump paradox: When you need it most it gives you least. And to make sure it gives you enough in the worst case scenario, you have to over-size it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worst case scenario would be an air source heat pump operating in the depths of winter. Being expected to produce viable domestic hot water and heat a dwelling simultaneously  really is scraping the bottom of the cost-efficiency barrel and should be considered as the desperate last resort. It will work, but  the plant will be uneconomically oversized, it will be working at the limits of its envelope, there will be frequent periods without heat due to defrosts, efficiency will be at its lowest and the demand for, and hence the price of, electricity will be at its highest. This is what the heat-pump user remembers long after the glossy advertising brochures have been recycled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The air-source heat pump needs some help. Consider adding alternative resources, such as a borehole to transfer heat from deep beneath the ground. If the ground can offer a higher grade source of heat than ambient air, then it would make sense to use that as the preferred heat source. The challenge then is that as surely as digging coal out, or pumping oil out of the ground, the energy source viability will be depleted gradually unless you have the luxury of local volcanic activity, which can bring its own problems. You still have the issue of high electricity price, but the plant could be more economically sized, and efficiency for at least the first year will far exceed what air source could achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summer, domestic hot water is the dominant but lesser heating demand, air temperature is high, sun is shining on the photo-voltaic panels, fresh breezes are spinning the turbines, and on the smart grid electricity demand and hence the price, is low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the heat pump paradox: When you need it least it gives you most. And if a heat pump is sized for winter operation then it will give you far more than you actually need in summer. The excess capacity can be used to replace the heat extracted from the ground during winter whilst providing the benefit of comfort cooling, and this can be done while electricity is plentiful and cheap and the air heat source is good, so the ground can now used as an efficient heat sink to store cheap energy when the heat pump efficiency and cost-effectiveness is at its best. Summer is the perfect opportunity to deposit heat into the energy bank surrounding the borehole, for use later, in winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dual source, dual sink heat pump technology is well proven in hundreds of commercial and retail premises throughout the land, and the principles hold good to fulfil a domestic role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smart Grid technology is also well proven and can feed electricity price and availability data into controllers equipped with the intelligence to use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowledge is having information. Wisdom is knowing how to use knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logical steps would be the combination of the air source heat pump with its ground resource counterpart, capitalising on the best efficiencies at the best times as identified by smart grid pricing, to maximise heat transfer and minimise expenditure on electricity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Integrating an intelligent controller that can measure and record the heat transfer from air-resource to load, or air-resource to ground-resource, or ground-resource to load, and learn to optimise the energy usage, would enable selection of the most appropriate operating mode to maximise the overall annual efficiency of not merely an intelligent heat pump installation, but wise heat pump operation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Peter Jackson</name><email>peter.jackson@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><summary type="html">There is much debate on the efficacy of heat pumps for domestic heating, but heat pumps alone are not the answer. There are a number of technologies in the heat transfer, energy storage and electricity supply industries that need to be integrated, and done successfully, the whole will be greater than the sum of the parts.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-2581922.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-2581922.jpg%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-2581922.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-2581922.jpg%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>