<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-03-15T19:54:38+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/atom.xml</id><title type="html">Op-tec Systems</title><subtitle>Independent automation consultant</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Improving Your Automation System</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/improving-your-automation-system" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Improving Your Automation System" /><published>2022-03-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/improving-your-automation-system</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/improving-your-automation-system">&lt;p&gt;The below quote, often attributed to Einstein, suggests whatever got us to where we are now can’t take us to where we want to be. This can definitely be said for automation systems!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“We cannot solve our problems with the same thinking we used when creating them!”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Albert Einstein?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article aims to highlight the fact many automation systems were developed and installed years ago. Since, a whole series of events and changes have occurred which means investing in your automation system can bring a huge amount of value and benefit to your organisation. We’d like to highlight 5 reasons why continual investment in your automation systems is a great idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-productivity&quot;&gt;1.	Productivity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This should be the most common reason for investing in your automation system. The number of products your manufacturing facility can produce over a period of time ultimately determines your income revenue. In our experience, we can’t think of a single manufacturing plant that couldn’t be made more productive through improvements in throughput.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite frankly, there are always ways of improving productivity via automation. Areas of the plant presently manually operated can be incorporated into existing automation systems, often for very little cost, all activities could be further optimised. This is why the following sections on Obsolescence, Reliability, Efficiency and Ease of Use have such an important and inextricable effect on improving your plant’s productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-obsolescence&quot;&gt;2.	Obsolescence&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This issue concerns all companies, regardless of size or the industry they operate in. Obsolescence puts companies at risk in two ways: in the short, and long-term. In the short-term obsolescence means a lack of spare parts. This prevents future expansion or modification of the system and means reliance on a shrinking pool of technical specialists for maintenance and repairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the long-term as assets age, they likely become less fit for purpose. Typically, older equipment will be less efficient and flexible, whilst providing less ‘feedback’ on its status preventing predictive maintenance or identification of improvement opportunities. While this longer-term risk doesn’t threaten to disrupt the business, we’ve seen it lead to “death by a thousand cuts” to product lines, plants and even entire facilities as they becomes slowly less competitive in their marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To guard against obsolescence monitor the availability and status of your systems on a regular basis (easily missed in the day to day process of keeping your plant running). Determine when upgrading the system will offer the best cost-benefit, ensuring you look at the risks involved if your system fails catastrophically in the meantime or the project doesn’t go smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3-reliability&quot;&gt;3.	Reliability&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poor reliability is the bane of any production system. Wherever you sit in your organisation (e.g. CEO, Operations Manager, Engineer or Operator) you’ll be aware of the result of faults which cause equipment to fail as they damage your numbers, customer relationships or generate more work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The root causes of poor reliability often end up overlooked or ignored once things are back up and running. Treating shutdowns as a nuisance rather than something which can be prevented stores issues up for a later date. It may not be convenient to address things now, but will it really be easier in a few years’ time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing this also encourages a culture of: “if it ain’t broke, don’t fix it!”. Taking this approach, rather than driving improvements through specific targeted and measurable criteria ultimately leads to: “if it isn’t totally broken, don’t fix it!”. Human nature then means the actual cost-benefit is never properly determined and temporary work-arounds remain in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;4-efficiency&quot;&gt;4.	Efficiency&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This compliments Productivity. Rather than doing more with the same, this can be seen as doing the same with less. We often see the benefits of investing to reduce ongoing personal expenditure, whether it’s a more fuel efficient vehicle, insulating the house or buying better quality items ‘built to last’. However due to a focus on short-term profits often make different decisions on behalf of our businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funding capital expenditure is the most common reason given for not investing in the efficiency of production equipment. In reality it’s often easier for individuals to ‘save up’ low cost opportunities then attempt to solve as many as possible with a large project than justify each separately. This leads to numerous low cost opportunities for increasing efficiency being missed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This “low hanging fruit” can range from optimising (tuning) control algorithms to improve quality, reducing raw material consumption and better machine utilisation to save energy. Further, efficiency gains are not limited to reduced consumption, they can be realised by lowering change-over times or speeding up cleaning stages. Think of inefficiency as waste of any kind, be it waste product, reworked product, systems standing idle, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;5-ease-of-use&quot;&gt;5.	Ease of Use&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there’s an easier way, people will take it. Old equipment is often seen as easier to use. This can stand in the way of new technology being adopted, or even existing systems being used if people find it easier to bypass them. Likewise, current manual operations may be simplified by automating certain activities allowing operators to focus on more valuable things - like identifying opportunities for further improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same goes for those overseeing production from a computer screen. If the information they need to make decisions is at their fingertips, displayed in an easy to read format, they’re far more likely to use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We still find things such as metering readings being recorded by someone walking around the plant with a clipboard, who enters the data they’ve written down into a spreadsheet then emails it to colleagues. The data is then either visualised in a presentation, entered into an business planning system, or both. This process is labour intensive, takes skilled workers attention away from important tasks and is completely unnecessary considering the business planning software likely has the ability to accept meter readings directly. Automating data collection in this situation would make several jobs easier and allow attention to be directed to acting on the information recorded in real-time, rather than after the delay caused by manual activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this may seem an extreme example, we assure it is not. There will be similar opportunities in your workplace, and you may be surprised at what your existing systems are capable of, particularly if they were configured some time ago with your original processes in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope this article has inspired you to look again at ways you can improve your automation systems and better use them to drive operational excellence in your company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information on how we can help you do this follow the link below to the Services section of our website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/services&quot;&gt;https://op-tec.co.uk/services&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Projects</name><email>projects@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="knowledge" /><category term="food&amp;drink" /><category term="textiles" /><category term="power" /><category term="chemicals" /><summary type="html">The below quote, often attributed to Einstein, suggests whatever got us to where we are now can’t take us to where we want to be. This can definitely be said for automation systems!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22petr-magera-KR9j7uqFhnI-unsplash-colour-small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22petr-magera-KR9j7uqFhnI-unsplash-colour-small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22petr-magera-KR9j7uqFhnI-unsplash-colour.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Is%20your%20equipment%20ready%20for%20tomorrow's%20challenges?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22petr-magera-KR9j7uqFhnI-unsplash-colour-small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22petr-magera-KR9j7uqFhnI-unsplash-colour-small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22petr-magera-KR9j7uqFhnI-unsplash-colour.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Is%20your%20equipment%20ready%20for%20tomorrow's%20challenges?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Programmable Logic Controllers</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/using-programmable-logic-controllers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Programmable Logic Controllers" /><published>2022-03-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/using-programmable-logic-controllers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/using-programmable-logic-controllers">&lt;p&gt;Programmable Logic Controllers are widely used to automate, control and monitor all manner of equipment and proceses. PLCs are available for installation in almost any environment. As technology has matured PLCs have become increasingly affordable and highly capable devices, able to handle discrete, continuous and batch processes in any industry application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;key-technologies&quot;&gt;Key Technologies&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PLCs are microprocessor-based devices equipped with a variety of electrical terminals for connecting to sensors and actuators on the shop or plant floor. They read signal inputs to gain awareness of current process conditions, then based on the software program running in their processor, send output signals to control equipment they are connected to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PLCs can communicate with a wide variety of devices using both ‘hard-wired’ electrical signals (4-20mA, 0-10V, 24V, …) and serial communications for equipment connected using fieldbus protocols (Modbus, Profibus, DeviceNet, …). Combined with extensive mathematical functions, high computational power, compatibility with ethernet-based protocols (OPC, MQTT, AMQP, …), and internet connectivity means modern PLC’s are able to replace PCs and servers in many cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Basic-PLC-architecture.png&quot; alt=&quot;Basic PLC architecture&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This enables PLC’s to be used in a wide variety of applications, for instance both to control processes but also as data concentrators - collecting and pre-processing data before sending it to higher level systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;benefits&quot;&gt;Benefits&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Small footprint and robust industrial design&lt;/strong&gt; – PLCs can be installed almost anywhere, and have low power consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Modular, scalable architecture&lt;/strong&gt;  – Minimises cost of future modification, expansion or integration. Being able to function alone or connected to hundreds, even thousands of others, means PLCs are used in applications of all sizes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Industry standard programming languages&lt;/strong&gt; – Widescale use of the IEC 61131-3 standard for software programming makes it relatively easy for technical personnel to interpret and maintain PLC logic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Equipped with latest ‘web’ technology&lt;/strong&gt; – Compatibility with open protocols make PLCs easy to interface with almost any system, from business systems and high-level dashboarding tools, to individual sensors on the factory floor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Real-time calculations&lt;/strong&gt; – Operational insights such as Operational Equipment Effectivenes (OEE), energy consumption or quality monitoring can be provided without exposing equipment to the internet or third-party systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information follow the link below to the Services section of our website where you can learn more about the help we can offer on this topic and many others relating to industrial process and manufacturing automation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/services&quot;&gt;https://op-tec.co.uk/services&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Roger Halliwell</name><email>roger.halliwell@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="knowledge" /><category term="tech-note" /><category term="food&amp;drink" /><category term="textiles" /><category term="power" /><category term="chemicals" /><summary type="html">Programmable Logic Controllers are widely used to automate, control and monitor all manner of equipment and proceses. PLCs are available for installation in almost any environment. As technology has matured PLCs have become increasingly affordable and highly capable devices, able to handle discrete, continuous and batch processes in any industry application.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22S7-1500_thumbnail.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22S7-1500_thumbnail.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22S7-1500.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Siemens%20S7-1500%20PLC%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22S7-1500_thumbnail.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22S7-1500_thumbnail.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22S7-1500.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Siemens%20S7-1500%20PLC%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Using Variable Speed Drives to increase quality and reduce energy costs</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/using-variable-speed-drives-to-increase-quality-and-reduce-energy-costs" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Using Variable Speed Drives to increase quality and reduce energy costs" /><published>2022-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/using-variable-speed-drives-to-increase-quality-and-reduce-energy-costs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/using-variable-speed-drives-to-increase-quality-and-reduce-energy-costs">&lt;p&gt;Many industrial applications can benefit from the use of Variable Speed Drives (also known as Variable Frequency or Inverter Drives). The increased motor control VSDs provide can improve product quality, and reduce energy consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;key-technologies&quot;&gt;Key Technologies&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most automation vendors offer VSDs. Market leaders such as ABB and Siemens have wide product portfolios to suit the needs of every type and size of application. VSD technology is well established and involves input power (AC) is rectified and is then switched (either in single or 3 phase configurations) to supply the motor windings. This switching determines the motor frequency feeding the motor windings which in turn determines the motor speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;benefits&quot;&gt;Benefits&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Variable torque applications such as pumps and fans typically have the most scope for reducing energy consumption. In these applications more energy is required to drive increased air or fluid flow as motor speed increases. This relationship is demonstrated in the power curve for an example 50kW fan motor (shown). In many situations, motors are oversized to allow for peak demand meaning that in normal operation the motor is running at a higher speed demanded by the process. This is sometimes exacerbated by mechanical throttling of the motor with some form of restriction such as a damper or throttle valve in order to control the air or fluid flow at a fixed rate (analogous to driving your car on the motorway with one foot on the accelerator and with the other foot on the brake to control the speed). By controlling the motor to run at slower speeds and by removing any unnecessary restriction then a drastic reduction in energy consumption can be achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/motor-power-curve.png&quot; alt=&quot;Typical 50kw motor power curve&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VSDs don’t only have the advantage of being able to control motor speeds but are also able to provide other advantages such as soft starting and, if fitted with suitable filtering systems can also reduce the effects of harmonics across the electrical network. The fact VSDs can be incorporated in closed loop control systems means processes can also be optimised. Another benefit of using VSDs is the motor bearings and associated hardware is less prone to stress and is therefore far more likely to operate over extended periods and with reduced maintenance. In short there really aren’t any disadvantages to introducing VSDs to your site except perhaps the initial capital costs. However, the payback periods can easily be calculated based on the energy savings which simply depend upon the reduced duty and reduced speeds that would be implemented following installation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information follow the link below to the Services section of our website where you can learn more about the help we can offer on this topic and many others relating to industrial process and manufacturing automation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/services&quot;&gt;https://op-tec.co.uk/services&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Roger Halliwell</name><email>roger.halliwell@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="knowledge" /><category term="tech-note" /><category term="food&amp;drink" /><category term="textiles" /><category term="power" /><category term="chemicals" /><summary type="html">Many industrial applications can benefit from the use of Variable Speed Drives (also known as Variable Frequency or Inverter Drives). The increased motor control VSDs provide can improve product quality, and reduce energy consumption.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22crystal-kwok-XUEdfpPIhXg-unsplash-small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22crystal-kwok-XUEdfpPIhXg-unsplash-small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22crystal-kwok-XUEdfpPIhXg-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Would%20your%20motors%20benefit%20from%20better%20control?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22crystal-kwok-XUEdfpPIhXg-unsplash-small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22crystal-kwok-XUEdfpPIhXg-unsplash-small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22crystal-kwok-XUEdfpPIhXg-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Would%20your%20motors%20benefit%20from%20better%20control?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Avoid being disappointed by your control system upgrade</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/avoid-being-disappointed-by-your-control-system-upgrade" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Avoid being disappointed by your control system upgrade" /><published>2022-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/avoid-being-disappointed-by-your-control-system-upgrade</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/avoid-being-disappointed-by-your-control-system-upgrade">&lt;p&gt;For many of us looking to upgrade our long loved (or hated) incumbent control systems fills us with both excitement and concern. Excitement because we always feel that something new will be better than something that is old, but concern because we always wonder whether the replacement system will meet all of our expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having worked in automation longer than I care to remember I’ve seen this situation countless times. Often, customers are only too keen to race ahead and get a replacement system only to suffer disappointment that the new system did not solve all their problems and deliver the improvements that they desired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why is this? Well there are a number of reasons which when you think about it are quite obvious but rarely heeded!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reason 1: Lack of Documentation&lt;/strong&gt; - The existing system operation was not monitored or documented on how it originally worked prior to the upgrade. This is a huge mistake because neglecting to carry out an inspection and review how the existing system operates could mean that the existing functionality is lost and this could be extremely expensive when commissioning begins. This situation arises when the system documentation is not kept up to date and often occurs when changes are made on the fly or in the heat of the moment and without the necessary change control procedures in place. So you might think that how a system operates is obvious where you simply watch it, watch the operator does and that’s it. Unfortunately, this is seldom the case. An analogy is a printed circuit board containing microprocessor chips, memory ICs, capacitors and resistors, etc. – do you think you could tell me exactly how it functions? No of course not and its similar with control systems where you really need to look under the hood to understand how the software operates – especially under fault conditions. This leads me to the next reason that is so often overlooked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reason 2: Purpose&lt;/strong&gt; - What helps enormously in replacing an existing system is the unambiguous purpose. Once we understand the purpose we begin to ask all sorts of questions we must be aware of and that may well have changed since the system was initially installed such as the Environment (does the system have to be IP66 rated or ATEX rated etc) are there safety issues to consider (e.g. manual operations where operators must be safe from any moving parts?), does the system need to communicate with other parts of the company (e.g. ERP Systems, 3rd Party Equipment etc)?. Not only this but we must also understand if there are any requirements in terms of speed of operation, productivity rates etc.  Then of course the issue of functionality must be carefully documented e.g. the order of preparation in a chemicals manufacturing plant, in-flight considerations, PID control, Alarms, Interlocks and the HMI (Human Machine Interface).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reason 3: Cheapest Price Wins&lt;/strong&gt; - As the old saying goes ‘You get what you pay for’. In automation this is undoubtedly true and really companies should be very careful here to ensure that the system that they are getting will provide both the existing system functionality plus the new functionality required and according to current standards and regulations. Many suppliers play the game of providing a so called ‘fixed’ price for replacing an existing system only to result in a list of variations as long as your arm. To avoid this you should make sure that the existing operation is understood (getting back to Reason No 1). You can either do this yourself if you have the inhouse skills and resource or use an external control systems supplier that you can trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reason 4: Vendor ‘Lock In’&lt;/strong&gt; - By Vendor ‘Lock In’ we mean that you as a customer have little alternative but to report back to the initial OEM Vendor whenever you want to add, change, or upgrade your system. This situation often arises when a Vendor is supplying multiple sections of the automation stack (e.g. Control System, MES, Data Historian) and where the Vendor has chosen to use proprietary interfaces forcing you to use their systems. So be mindful of this issue and consider a system that utilises ‘Best in Class’ systems and components that interface and communicate with each other using Open standards. Furthermore, look into the concept of the Unified Name Space where additional systems can be easily added as they communicate via a common Data Pool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, once you have considered the above it is worth looking into the maturity and life expectancy of prospective systems. In this respect you don’t want to invest significant investment in a system that you find is immature (and prone to faults) or at the other end of the spectrum in a system that is at the end of its development lifecycle where any future improvements or developments will not occur as the vendor is more interested in the development of new systems to sell to their customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information follow the link below to the Services section of our website where you can learn more about the help we can offer on this topic and many others relating to industrial process and manufacturing automation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/services&quot;&gt;https://op-tec.co.uk/services&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Roger Halliwell</name><email>roger.halliwell@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><summary type="html">For many of us looking to upgrade our long loved (or hated) incumbent control systems fills us with both excitement and concern. Excitement because we always feel that something new will be better than something that is old, but concern because we always wonder whether the replacement system will meet all of our expectations.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22robin-sommer-wnOJ83k8r4w-unsplash_small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22robin-sommer-wnOJ83k8r4w-unsplash_small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22robin-sommer-wnOJ83k8r4w-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Notice%20an%20improvement?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22robin-sommer-wnOJ83k8r4w-unsplash_small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22robin-sommer-wnOJ83k8r4w-unsplash_small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22robin-sommer-wnOJ83k8r4w-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Notice%20an%20improvement?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Disaster Recovery Planning in Theory and Practice</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/disaster-recovery-planning-in-theory-and-practice" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Disaster Recovery Planning in Theory and Practice" /><published>2022-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/disaster-recovery-planning-in-theory-and-practice</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/disaster-recovery-planning-in-theory-and-practice">&lt;p&gt;The scenario: a server collecting historical data from a distributed control system running an industrial process. The server is 15 years old and creaking, with bits and bytes falling off its hard drive. The software is also legacy and well outside manufacturer’s support. The whole thing is being replaced but needs to be supported, and the hard drive is being worked very hard during the transition. Access to site is denied due to covid restrictions. Access through the client’s firewalls is limited, with no facility for file transfer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preparation is key. To enable rapid disaster recovery we loaded the original software installation disk and all subsequent updates and patches on a reserved partition of the storage where they could be accessed and executed from our remote and isolated workstations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worst happened, data acquisition and presentation failed. Corruption of files and software were suspected, services checked and the disaster recovery plan to restore functionality was put into action. All historical archive files and backups were removed from the historian data to a quarantine folder. The historian program was removed from the hard drive and a clean installation was carried out. Updates and patches were reinstalled, the system was returned to its previous operating condition, and data acquisition was restored. Data files were imported from the quarantined backup files, the result being full data recording, reporting and presentation available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are relying on legacy equipment, are you prepared for a crash?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you have a Disaster Recovery Plan in place?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you answer ‘no’ or ‘I don’t know’ to either of those questions then call Op-tec to get you ready to recover and resume normal operations with minimal delay and no drama.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Peter Jackson</name><email>peter.jackson@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><summary type="html">The scenario: a server collecting historical data from a distributed control system running an industrial process. The server is 15 years old and creaking, with bits and bytes falling off its hard drive. The software is also legacy and well outside manufacturer’s support. The whole thing is being replaced but needs to be supported, and the hard drive is being worked very hard during the transition. Access to site is denied due to covid restrictions. Access through the client’s firewalls is limited, with no facility for file transfer.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-pixabay-33278-small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-pixabay-33278-small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22pexels-pixabay-33278.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22How%20quickly%20can%20you%20respond%20to%20failures?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-pixabay-33278-small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-pixabay-33278-small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22pexels-pixabay-33278.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22How%20quickly%20can%20you%20respond%20to%20failures?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How to enjoy Christmas</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/how-to-enjoy-christmas" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to enjoy Christmas" /><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/how-to-enjoy-christmas</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/how-to-enjoy-christmas">&lt;p&gt;While I’m sure some reading this will be working during the holiday period almost everyone will enjoy at least a few days off during the next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However I can’t be the only one who’ll be hoping the phone doesn’t ring once I’ve closed my laptop lid on 2021. If you’re familiar with this feeling here’s a few things you to check before finishing work for the year to reduce the chance of your holiday being interrupted:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Procedures&lt;/strong&gt; - Make sure all standard operating, disaster recovery, incident response (and any other) procedures are easily accessible and everyone who has a chance of needing them knows where they are.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Backups&lt;/strong&gt; - Ensure recent backups of every programmable system have been taken, and are stored in a location accessible to anyone who may need them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Escalation&lt;/strong&gt; - Review your escalation procedure. Who really needs to know? Who can (and is in a position to) do something about it?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maintenance&lt;/strong&gt; - If any work is taking place while you’re away, are those doing it have access to all the information and resources they need to handle any eventuality?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Access&lt;/strong&gt; - Do those who may be called on to resolve issues have access to the necessary resources (physical and electronic), people (contact details) and locations?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you notice a gap, hopefully it won’t take too long to put a temporary measure in place. If you do, &lt;em&gt;please&lt;/em&gt; remember to set a reminder to address the issue in the new year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy the Christmas holidays!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Richard Banyard</name><email>richard.banyard@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><summary type="html">While I’m sure some reading this will be working during the holiday period almost everyone will enjoy at least a few days off during the next week.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22paige-cody-bdse1gz3EPg-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22paige-cody-bdse1gz3EPg-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22paige-cody-bdse1gz3EPg-unsplash-large.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Make%20sure%20you%20relax%20over%20the%20holidays%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22paige-cody-bdse1gz3EPg-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22paige-cody-bdse1gz3EPg-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22paige-cody-bdse1gz3EPg-unsplash-large.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Make%20sure%20you%20relax%20over%20the%20holidays%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Computer System Validation - a process</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/computer-system-validation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Computer System Validation - a process" /><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/computer-system-validation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/computer-system-validation">&lt;p&gt;It’s quite a while now since I was first involved with Computer System Validation (CSV). It was around 1994 if I recall correctly and it was during a large project for AstraZeneca that I cut my teeth on the computer system lifecycle approach to all things regulated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is CSV and why is it so especially important to the pharmaceutical industry?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer what CSV is I like to think back to a conference I attended in the 1990’s where one of the presenters was an American by the name of Ken Chapman. Ken was an inspirational person and had spend a huge part of his career working for Pfizer during which he developed computer system validation processes for the company while also sitting on a number of external pharmaceutical special interest boards as reviewer and advisor. I bring Ken’s name up because during the conference he dealt with a number of issues one of which If I recall correctly was regarding Electronic Signatures and Records (referred to colloquially within the industry as 21 CFR Part 11).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, at some point during the conference Ken simplified the whole validation process to the whole audience by writing down what Validation is – I’ll never forget the three lines of text he showed us:-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Say what you are going to do.&lt;/strong&gt; Specify and document your requirements and how they will be met.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do what you said you would do.&lt;/strong&gt; Develop and build the system according to the specifications you have written.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prove you did what you said you would do.&lt;/strong&gt; Test the system according to the specifications you have written.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put like this it all seems so simple doesn’t it. Essentially it is a simple process in itself but I do have to say that the pitfalls of validation are the extents that some people expect of the validation process which is a bit like asking for an extra hot latte at your local coffee shop – what do you exactly mean by extra hot (please define).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do you go about validating a computer system? Well first I would advise as to what parts of the system are to be validated. For instance if the production process requires that a compressed air system is provided then does it mean that the compressor software itself (normally provided by the OEM) is also validated? I think the argument here is how does the compressor software affect the finished product (i.e. would the operation of the air compressor by itself affect the end product’s quality attributes?). So although you may require the manufacturer to provide assurances that they have used a quality process to develop the compressor software it would not necessarily need to be validated as further upstream software would cover these requirements. What I mean by this is that lets say for parts of the process that require the use of compressed air (such as line pressure monitoring) would be validated as the critical parameter in this instance is likely to be the compressed air pressure entering the system. Another example of where CSV is normally limited is with regards to operating systems. This where the size and prevenance of the operating system weighs heavily in terms of this situation. For example by far the largest and most common operating system utilised by control systems today is Microsoft Windows. The attitude of the regulatory authorities is that the development of such a widely used operating system does not require by itself to be independently validated, rather because of such a large (and therefore proven) user base then this is not required. This is in some ways also similar to the example of the air compressor where the affect of the overall control system is dependant upon a range of systems but where in fact the actual validation of the system is covered because the overall testing process will cover the effective operation of the system. Shortlisting the areas of the system that actually need validating is important in regards to the overall validation time, effort, practicality and cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So is there a process or strategy involved in validating a computer system? The answer is that there are models and guidelines. The most popular model is known as the ‘V’ model. This is where the various documents defining the system are mapped against each other and the various test procedures. The idea is that the end user requirements are captured in the very beginning and are then used to ensure that all future documentation and requirements are included in the ensuing specifications. Figure 1 below shows the generic ‘V’ model. A small point but please note that the model gets its name from the ‘V’ shape of the model and that the ‘V’ doesn’t actually stand for Validation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/v-model.png&quot; alt=&quot;V-Model&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have an overall model that can shape the order and relationship of the various specifications and test scripts we can begin to consider the documents to be produced and the content therein.  Being an engineer I like the ideas of frameworks and guidelines and as luck would have it the ISPE (International Society of Pharmaceutical Engineering) have produced an extremely useful guideline regarding computer system validation which is directly applicable to control systems – the guide is known as GAMP (Good Automated Manufacturing Practice). It is currently on its 5th iteration and contains a wealth of information and guidance as to how to validate a computer system. It also describes the documents required together with example content lists for each document. So I strongly recommend anyone venturing into the wacky world of CSV to pick up a copy of the GAMP guidelines and save yourself hours of toil wondering just how to carry out the validation process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I finish this article there is something that I would like to mention about software in particular. It seems as though standards developers in batch circles and those involved in defining validation systems are of similar minds. Indeed, this is a very good example of good practice for all concerned. In batch circles the de-facto standard is known as ISA S88 which is used for defining batch terminology and processes (there is also the ISA 95 standard for defining the integration between enterprise planning system with control systems).  Both the ISA S88 and ISA S95 standards reference the importance and use of software modularity. In fact the ISA S88 standard also defines the hierarchy of company structures using such terms as Enterprise (to define a global company), a plant (an individual manufacturing site), an area (a manufacturing area within the plant such as a tank farm), a Unit (such as a Reactor or Centrifuge) and a control module (a number of devices that work together to provide a specific function such as an agitation).  In this regard the idea is that a software system is split into a hierarchy of smaller software modules. The idea is that it is easier (and more efficient) to provide software functionality in multiple modules than in one large piece of contiguous software. This makes sense in all sorts of ways, not least in that it is easier to specify the function of a system piece by piece (module by module). This also makes it easier to test the functionality of each piece separately before it being joined to the other software modules. Harking back to the ‘V’ model above, you will see that software modules and module tests are part of the validation process and where an integration test is used to test the system as a whole. Another benefit of this system results in only modules that share information or lines of command are joined together – thus reducing the complexity and the amount of information transfer or shared between one another and the resulting communications traffic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally ( I know I said “Before I finish” just before) but please bare with me. You may think that the above validation process is somewhat long winded. However the philosophy behind the process is not only to provide a validated system but also to provide an efficient way of developing computer based hardware and software systems. The benefit of the approach is to provide a well documented and validated system. Once documented it is easier to maintain (and modify if ever required in the future). The approach (since it is modular) also enables multiple developers to work in parallel thus reducing the overall development time of the system.  The process also lends itself to producing software in libraries for future re-use. Reusable software is extremely useful and from personal experience I recall reusing a colleague’s reporting software that originally took over 6 months to develop to only taking 3 days  to modify and reuse in another application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;application/ld+json&quot;&gt;{&quot;@context&quot;: &quot;https://schema.org&quot;,&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;FAQPage&quot;,&quot;mainEntity&quot;: 
[
{&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Question&quot;,&quot;name&quot;: &quot;What does CSV stand for?&quot;,&quot;acceptedAnswer&quot;: {&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Answer&quot;,&quot;text&quot;: &quot;Computer System Validation&quot;
}},
{&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Question&quot;,&quot;name&quot;: &quot;Is there a simple explanation for Computer System Validation?&quot;,&quot;acceptedAnswer&quot;: {&quot;@type&quot;: &quot;Answer&quot;,&quot;text&quot;: &quot;Computer System Validation can be thought of in 3 stages: 1) Say what you are going to do - specify and document your requirements and how they will be met. 2) Do what you said you would do - develop and build the system according to the specifications you have written. 3) Prove you did what you said you would do - test the system according to the specifications you have written.&quot;
}}]
}&lt;/script&gt;</content><author><name>Roger Halliwell</name><email>roger.halliwell@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="knowledge" /><category term="pharmaceuticals" /><summary type="html">It’s quite a while now since I was first involved with Computer System Validation (CSV). It was around 1994 if I recall correctly and it was during a large project for AstraZeneca that I cut my teeth on the computer system lifecycle approach to all things regulated.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-pixabay-357514-small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-pixabay-357514-small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22pexels-pixabay-357514.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Computer%20System%20Validation%20creates%20documentation...%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-pixabay-357514-small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-pixabay-357514-small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22pexels-pixabay-357514.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Computer%20System%20Validation%20creates%20documentation...%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Is your DMZ a no man’s land?</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/is-your-DMZ-a-no-mans-land" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is your DMZ a no man’s land?" /><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/is-your-DMZ-a-no-mans-land</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/is-your-DMZ-a-no-mans-land">&lt;p&gt;Organisations continue to digitise. Whether intentionally via planned projects with dedicated budgets and resources, or unintentionally as suppliers embed remote monitoring into equipment and encourage migration to cloud-based software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time industrial automation (Operational Technology, OT) is making more use of the same open protocols used by Information Technology (IT). Pressures to improve efficiency mean organisations are increasingly integrating OT and IT systems to streamline processes and automate menial tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These trends mean there’s more crossover than ever between IT and OT, leading to more interaction between the teams responsible for each. The relationship between these teams can often be gauged by how they use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DMZ_(computing)&quot;&gt;demilitarised zone&lt;/a&gt; (DMZ).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the DMZ(s) in your organisation is treated as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/No_man%27s_land&quot;&gt;no man’s land&lt;/a&gt; by the IT and OT departments, a huge opportunity to increase the rate and quality of innovation and process improvement is being missed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll know this is happening if people tend to avoid communicating with the other ‘side’ when working in this network. They avoid it altogether. Or don’t take responsibility of the outcome when they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reasons friction can exist between IT and OT teams are well-documented and vary between organisations. The most common retort from people in OT is that IT personnel don’t appreciate the importance of planning system updates and changes, they don’t feel pain when systems go offline (planned or unplanned). People in IT have the opposite perspective, operational teams seem oblivious to security risks and the need to keep systems up to date so they can communicate securely with other parts of the organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of dividing people, use the DMZ to bridge the gap between them. Encourage experimentation to generate ideas for how the organisation can make use of its data. Rather than a little used buffer between networks, make the DMZ the location for proof of concepts, pilot projects and collaboration activities between business and operational teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some ideas to get you started:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set ground rules&lt;/strong&gt;. The DMZ is not a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandbox_(software_development)&quot;&gt;sandbox&lt;/a&gt;, it’s likely the only connection between your operational and business systems. Put measures in place to ensure production data moving through your DMZ can’t be impacted by trials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have clearly defined projects&lt;/strong&gt;. Ensure there is a single person responsible and accountable for every project. Then that all activity takes place within a defined project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Require, rather than expect collaboration&lt;/strong&gt;. Any work done in the DMZ - whether it’s replacing a patch lead or deploying a new process historian - should be done with the knowledge and preferably involvement of individuals from both OT and IT teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Log and record everything&lt;/strong&gt;. So you don’t lose out on any learning, and can explain why things work (or don’t).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maintain good cyber security hygiene&lt;/strong&gt;. Remember the DMZ’s main purpose is to secure your OT networks. Segregate production and non-production data. Only read data from your operational systems (you’ll likely have firewalls configured to do this already). Ensure you keep track of all assets connected to the network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if your DMZ resembles the image at the top of this article, think about taking down the razor wire and clearing the mines. Companies who master integration of their operational and business systems stand a far greater chance of remaining competitive in their markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create an environment where it raises a flag if someone mutters, “IT must have installed an update”, or “OT have plugged in another XP machine…” and make the most of this valuable resource sitting in clear view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ITandOT_DMZ.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Simplified DMZ Architecture&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Richard Banyard</name><email>richard.banyard@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><category term="chemicals" /><category term="power" /><category term="oil&amp;gas" /><summary type="html">Organisations continue to digitise. Whether intentionally via planned projects with dedicated budgets and resources, or unintentionally as suppliers embed remote monitoring into equipment and encourage migration to cloud-based software.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22picfair-06597943-no-mans-land-famagusta-cyprus-thumbnail.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22picfair-06597943-no-mans-land-famagusta-cyprus-thumbnail.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22picfair-06597943-no-mans-land-famagusta-cyprus-licensed.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Is%20this%20how%20your%20people%20treat%20the%20DMZ?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22picfair-06597943-no-mans-land-famagusta-cyprus-thumbnail.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22picfair-06597943-no-mans-land-famagusta-cyprus-thumbnail.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22picfair-06597943-no-mans-land-famagusta-cyprus-licensed.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Is%20this%20how%20your%20people%20treat%20the%20DMZ?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What my new smart watch taught me</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/What-my-new-smart-watch-taught-me" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What my new smart watch taught me" /><published>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/What-my-new-smart-watch-taught-me</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/latest/What-my-new-smart-watch-taught-me">&lt;p&gt;I recently bought a new watch/fitness tracker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Am I happy with my investment?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well… Nobody will admit they have chosen badly, but…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d researched the alternatives, made a list of requirements (User Requirements Specification) created a comparison chart and made a good engineering decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new hardware captures all the data it sets out to; steps, pulse rate, oxygen saturation, sleep, divided into deep, light, rem and awake, altitude and depth so I know how far above or below sea level I am, and a compass and GPS. From all of this it derives and presents floors climbed, calories burned, excercise intensity, body battery (energy reserves) and stress level (something else for me to worry about).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what went wrong? The raw data capture is not all that it ought to be. Further problems lie with the assumptions made, calculations and analysis of data, and presentation of information. Example; If my calorie burn is correct then I’m heating the whole house with my body heat output, running on zero reserves with a blood oxygen level close to cyanosis of my vital organs and I don’t care one jot according to my stress level. I’m still above sea level though, which is reassuring after the recent rains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Points to ponder:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One size does not fit all when making assumptions in calculations. You need to tailor to individual needs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sense-check the results. Never abrogate responsibility to “Computer says”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get feedback from the customer and build in the ability to adjust or re-calibrate if necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are processes we at Op-tec go through as a matter of course for our customers. If we’re converting your production data into guidance for strategic decisions we will have carried out a thorough analysis of your needs and expectations, we will have made it clear what we can do and we will walk with you through the implementation process until what we have agreed has been fulfilled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://op-tec.co.uk/digital-benchmark&quot;&gt;Generate your free Digital Benchmark Report&lt;/a&gt; to learn more about our approach to technology investment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Peter Jackson</name><email>peter.jackson@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="latest" /><summary type="html">I recently bought a new watch/fitness tracker.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22tim-foster-Odhl-kitI2c-unsplash-small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22tim-foster-Odhl-kitI2c-unsplash-small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22tim-foster-Odhl-kitI2c-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22A%20good%20investment?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22tim-foster-Odhl-kitI2c-unsplash-small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22tim-foster-Odhl-kitI2c-unsplash-small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22tim-foster-Odhl-kitI2c-unsplash.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22A%20good%20investment?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Greenshirts of the Boiler Police are coming!</title><link href="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/the-greenshirts-are-coming" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Greenshirts of the Boiler Police are coming!" /><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/the-greenshirts-are-coming</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://op-tec.co.uk/knowledge/the-greenshirts-are-coming">&lt;p&gt;The government’s Domestic Renewable Heat Incentive is intended to reduce our reliance on using fossil fuels and to replace them with systems which use renewable energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Core to the incentive scheme is replacement of gas boilers with heat pumps. So, how do heat pumps work? Do the advantages in domestic settings stack up? And can industry benefit from heat pumps?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-heat-pumps-work&quot;&gt;How Heat Pumps Work&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heat pumps work rather like a refrigerator in reverse. Whereas a refrigerator removes heat via a liquid refrigerant to atmosphere a heat pump collects heat from the atmosphere and rejects the heat to radiators and hot water tanks. In this respect the heat pump system comprises a relatively simple circuit where refrigerant flows through an external evaporator coil where a fan is used to blow ambient air across the coil (these are the beige coloured units you see outside properties fitted with this kind of technology).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Refrigerant evaporates from a low pressure liquid state into vapour below ambient temperature so the coil takes in energy at this point. The low pressure vapour is then compressed into high pressure vapour; this process adds energy and increases its temperature (in a similar manner to the heat produced when you pump up bicycle tyres). The high pressure refrigerant vapour is then pumped to the condenser where it is cooled and condensed into high pressure liquid by water flowing through the heating system to heat the building and provide hot water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Will this provide me with a cheaper way of heating my home?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer to this question isn’t straight forward. Why? Well although the government will provide a £5,000 grant to fund the installation of a replacement heat pump system, the total cost of an installation is typically a lot more than this. For example, most contractors will quote in the region of £11,000 to £15,000 to install a heat pump system into the average 3 bedroom semi-detached house with the cost increasing for larger properties. You’ll also need to factor in the potential need for better insulation such as loft insulation, cavity wall insulation and improved double glazing. So the simple maths results in the home owner being left with a minimum installation bill of between £6,000 and £10,000. Following installation, you will then of course be able to muster free energy? Not entirely – once you have installed the system the heating source (the outside atmosphere in a home dwelling) is free but unfortunately and as mentioned above, the system relies upon a pumping system and a compressor which is powered by electricity. Although the cost of this electricity is presently less (per equivalent kWhr) than for gas, we are currently facing increased energy costs. So although less energy is expended in terms of equivalent kWhrs to gas, the running costs could end up being very little different than that of a gas boiler system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What about industry – can it benefit from heat pumps?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key point here is the re-use of already available heat. The efficiency of a heat pump is all about where you start from. In other words, more work (energy expended) is required if the initial heat source is at a lower temperature than a heat source from a higher initial temperature. For instance if there’s already an existing heat source which is not being put to good use (such as exhaust gases or steam flow) then these sources would be used to provide primary heat to a heat pump, thus increasing its efficiency hugely and potentially making the system highly viable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How effective are heat pumps in the real world?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well there’s a bit of an irony here. Remember that in a domestic setting that during the summer most people aren’t using the central heating very much apart from having hot water available for showers etc. This is a pity because during the summer months the outside ambient heat is far greater than in the winter and so the heat pump system is more efficient. The irony is that during the winter months (when the need for central heating is more obvious) domestic heat pumps do not supply the same level of efficient heating as during the summer months. In other words when we need the heat pump to provide heat to heat our houses during the winter it is less able to do so and during the summer months (when heat pumps are better able to provide heat) they aren’t needed as much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, compare this situation with an industrial setting where the initial heat source such as waste exhaust heat or steam is far more likely to be at an elevated temperature, is available all year round and relies upon what is in most cases is a by product of the industrial process. For these reasons the use of heat pumps in an industrial setting becomes extremely viable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are the green credentials behind heat pumps?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The green argument behind the use of heat pumps especially for home owners in a domestic setting is interesting. Yes, we are reducing the use of gas which power gas boilers in our homes which is a good thing. However, the system is not entirely green because the electricity used to power the pump and the compressor does not come from entirely green sources. This is due to the fact that electricity generation systems in the UK rely upon a large mix of energy sources – some renewable (e.g. Wind, Solar and Hydro) but also via a large number of gas fired power stations. However, the same can not be said in an industrial setting where the use of heat pumps can be seen as very green. This is because when using what is in many situations would be otherwise wasted heat, then the system efficiency is significant and far above that within most domestic settings. In other words, existing heat energy can be recycled through a heat pump and because the initial heat energy is relatively high to that found in many domestic settings the electrical energy expended to power the heat pump compressor in an industrial setting is comparatively less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To quote Boris Johnson recently writing in the Sun newspaper “the Greenshirts of the Boiler Police are not going to kick in your door with their sandal-clad feet and seize, at carrot-point, your trusty old combi”. But if you are approached by ‘the ‘Green Brigade’ then please be aware of the issues we have mentioned above, especially regarding domestic settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast we believe that there are many opportunities where heat pumps can be provided in industrial environments where the initial investment required is proven and where significant cost reductions can be made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One question you should be asking of any heat pump supplier is ‘Will the system that you are proposing be at least equivalent or better in terms of cost and efficiency than my existing gas boiler system whether in a domestic or industrial environment?’ To be able to answer this, a survey of your property or buildings is necessary in order to gauge the viability of a heat pump system. Such a survey should be from an independent source and will involve determining the specification of the heat pump system depending upon the heat loss of the home or buildings involved in an industrial situation. Only once armed with this information will you be able to determine the likely running costs and potential savings you may be able to enjoy and whether a heat pump is suitable for your home or for your company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;about-op-tec-systems&quot;&gt;About Op-tec Systems&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are an independent engineering consultancy with specific expertise in the provision of heating, ventilation and air conditioning systems. For further information on any of the above then please email us at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:projects@op-tec.co.uk&quot;&gt;projects@op-tec.co.uk&lt;/a&gt; or visit our web site at &lt;a href=&quot;https://op-tec.co.uk/&quot;&gt;op-tec.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Roger Halliwell</name><email>roger.halliwell@op-tec.co.uk</email></author><category term="knowledge" /><category term="power" /><summary type="html">The government’s Domestic Renewable Heat Incentive is intended to reduce our reliance on using fossil fuels and to replace them with systems which use renewable energy.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-max-vakhtbovych-6316066-small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-max-vakhtbovych-6316066-small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22pexels-max-vakhtbovych-6316066.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Is%20a%20heat%20pump%20right%20for%20you?%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://op-tec.co.uk/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22pexels-max-vakhtbovych-6316066-small.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22pexels-max-vakhtbovych-6316066-small.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22pexels-max-vakhtbovych-6316066.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Is%20a%20heat%20pump%20right%20for%20you?%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>